Earth

Earth is the third planet↗ from the Sun and the only astronomical object↗ known to harbor life↗. This is made possible by Earth being an ocean world↗, the only one in the Solar System sustaining liquid surface water↗. Almost all of Earth's water is contained in its global ocean, covering 70.8%↗ of Earth's crust↗. The remaining 29.2% of Earth's crust is land, most of which is located in the form of continent↗al landmass↗es within Earth's land hemisphere↗. Most of Earth's land is at least somewhat humid↗ and covered by vegetation, while large ice sheet↗s at Earth's polar desert↗s retain more water than Earth's groundwater↗, lakes, rivers, and atmospheric water↗ combined. Earth's crust consists of slowly moving tectonic plates↗, which interact to produce mountain ranges, volcano↗es, and earthquakes. Earth has a liquid outer core↗ that generates a magnetosphere↗ capable of deflecting most of the destructive solar wind↗s and cosmic radiation↗.

Earth has a dynamic atmosphere↗, which sustains Earth's surface conditions and protects it from most meteoroid↗s and UV-light at entry↗. It is composed primarily of nitrogen↗ and oxygen↗. Water vapor↗ is widely present in the atmosphere, forming clouds↗ that cover most of the planet. The water vapor acts as a greenhouse gas↗ and, together with other greenhouse gases in the atmosphere, particularly carbon dioxide↗ (CO2), creates the conditions for both liquid surface water and water vapor to persist via the capturing of energy from the Sun's light↗. This process maintains the current average surface temperature of 14.76 °C, at which water is liquid under normal atmospheric pressure↗. Differences in the amount of captured energy between geographic regions (as with the equatorial region↗ receiving more sunlight than the polar regions) drive atmospheric↗ and ocean current↗s, producing a global climate system↗ with different climate region↗s, and a range of weather phenomena such as precipitation↗, allowing components such as carbon↗ and nitrogen↗ to cycle↗.

Earth is rounded↗ into an ellipsoid↗ with a circumference↗ of about 40000 km. It is the densest planet in the Solar System↗. Of the four rocky planets↗, it is the largest and most massive. Earth is about eight light-minute↗s (1 AU↗) away from the Sun and orbits it↗, taking a year (about 365.25 days) to complete one revolution. Earth rotates↗ around its own axis in slightly less than a day (in about 23 hours and 56 minutes). Earth's axis of rotation is tilted with respect to the perpendicular to its orbital plane around the Sun, producing seasons. Earth is orbit↗ed by one permanent natural satellite↗, the Moon↗, which orbits Earth at 384400 km—1.28 light seconds—and is roughly a quarter as wide as Earth. The Moon's gravity helps stabilize Earth's axis↗, causes tide↗s and gradually slows Earth's rotation↗. Likewise, Earth's gravitational pull has already made the Moon's rotation tidally locked↗, keeping the same near side↗ facing Earth.

Earth, like most other bodies in the Solar System, formed about 4.5 billion years ago↗ from gas and dust in the early Solar System↗. The formation of the ocean and the subsequent development of life↗ occurred during the first billion years of Earth's history↗. Life spread globally and has been altering Earth's atmosphere and surface, leading to the Great Oxidation Event↗ two billion years ago. Humans emerged 300,000 years ago in Africa and have spread across every continent on Earth. Humans depend on Earth's biosphere↗ and natural resources for their survival, but have increasingly impacted the planet's environment↗. Humanity's current impact on Earth's climate and biosphere is unsustainable, threatening the livelihood of humans and many other forms of life, and causing widespread extinctions↗.

Etymology and symbol

The Modern English↗ word Earth developed, via Middle English↗, from an Old English↗ noun most often spelled eorðe. It has cognates in every Germanic language↗, from which has been reconstructed. In its earliest attestation, the word eorðe was used to translate the many senses of Latin terra and Greek : the ground, its soil, dry land, the human world, the surface of the world (including the sea), and the globe itself. As with Roman↗ (or ) and Greek↗ , Earth may have been a personified goddess↗ in Germanic paganism↗: late Norse mythology↗ included ('Earth'), a giantess often given as the mother of Thor↗.

Historically, Earth has been written in lowercase. During the Early Middle English↗ period, its definite sense↗ as "the globe" began being expressed using the phrase the earth. By the period of Early Modern English↗, capitalization of nouns began to prevail↗, and the earth was also written the Earth, particularly when referenced along with other heavenly bodies. More recently, the name is sometimes simply given as Earth, by analogy with the names of the other planets, though earth and forms with the earth remain common. House styles↗ now vary: Oxford spelling↗ recognizes the lowercase form as the more common, with the capitalized form an acceptable variant. Another convention capitalizes Earth when appearing as a name, such as a description of the "Earth's atmosphere", but employs the lowercase when it is preceded by the, such as "the atmosphere of the earth". It almost always appears in lowercase in colloquial expressions such as "what on earth are you doing?"

The name Terra [ˈtɛrə] TERR-ə is occasionally used in scientific writing; it also sees use in science fiction to distinguish humanity's inhabited planet from others, while in poetry Tellus [ˈtɛləs] TELL-əs has been used to denote personification of the Earth. Terra is also the name of the planet in some Romance languages↗, languages that evolved from Latin, like Italian and Portuguese, while in other Romance languages the word gave rise to names with slightly altered spellings, like the Spanish Tierra and the French Terre. The Latinate form Gaea (['dʒiː.ə] DJEE-ə) of the Greek poetic name Gaia↗ ([ɡâi̯.a] or [ɡâj.ja]) is rare, though the alternative spelling Gaia has become common due to the Gaia hypothesis↗, in which case its pronunciation is [ˈgaɪ.ə] GYE-ə rather than the more traditional English [ˈgeɪ.ə] GAY-ə.

There are a number of adjectives for the planet Earth. The word earthly is derived from Earth. From the Latin Terra comes terran [ˈtɛrən] TERR-ən, terrestrial [təˈrɛstriəl] tərr-EHST-ree-əl, and (via French) terrene [təˈriːn] tə-REEN, and from the Latin Tellus comes tellurian [tɛˈlʊəriən] teh-LUURR-ee-ən and telluric.

Symbol

The standard astronomical symbols↗ of Earth are a quartered circle, , representing the four corners of the world↗, and a globus cruciger↗, .

Natural history

Main articles: History of Earth↗ and Timeline of natural history↗

Formation

Further information: Early Earth↗ and Hadean↗

The oldest material found in the Solar System is dated to Ga↗ (billion years) ago. By the primordial Earth had formed. The bodies in the Solar System formed and evolved↗ with the Sun. In theory, a solar nebula↗ partitions a volume out of a molecular cloud↗ by gravitational collapse, which begins to spin and flatten into a circumstellar disk↗, and then the planets grow out of that disk with the Sun. A nebula contains gas, ice grains, and dust↗ (including primordial nuclide↗s). According to nebular theory↗, planetesimal↗s formed by accretion↗, with the primordial Earth being estimated as likely taking anywhere from 70 to 100 million years to form.

Estimates of the age of the Moon range from 4.5 Ga to significantly younger. A leading hypothesis↗ is that it was formed by accretion from material loosed from Earth after a Mars-sized object with about 10% of Earth's mass, named Theia↗, collided with Earth. It hit Earth with a glancing blow and some of its mass merged with Earth. Between approximately 4.0 and , numerous asteroid impacts↗ during the Late Heavy Bombardment↗ caused significant changes to the greater surface environment of the Moon and, by inference, to that of Earth.

After formation

Main article: Geological history of Earth↗

Earth's atmosphere↗ and oceans were formed by volcanic activity↗ and outgassing↗. Water vapor from these sources condensed↗ into the oceans, augmented by water and ice from asteroids, protoplanet↗s, and comet↗s. Sufficient water to fill the oceans may have been on Earth since it formed. In this model, atmospheric greenhouse gas↗es kept the oceans from freezing when the newly forming Sun had only 70%↗ of its current luminosity↗. By , Earth's magnetic field↗ was established, which helped prevent the atmosphere from being stripped away by the solar wind↗.

As the molten outer layer of Earth cooled it formed↗ the first solid crust↗, which is thought to have been mafic↗ in composition. The first continental crust↗, which was more felsic↗ in composition, formed by the partial melting of this mafic crust. Hadean-aged zircon↗ grains found in Western Australia↗, dating back as far as , provide the oldest direct evidence of Earth's surface, indicating that felsic continental crust and liquid water existed within 140–160 million years of the planet's formation. There are two main models of how this initial small volume of continental crust evolved to reach its current abundance: (1) a relatively steady growth up to the present day, which is supported by the radiometric dating of continental crust globally and (2) an initial rapid growth in the volume of continental crust during the Archean↗, forming the bulk of the continental crust that now exists, which is supported by isotopic evidence from hafnium↗ in zircon↗s and neodymium↗ in sedimentary rocks. The two models and the data that support them can be reconciled by large-scale recycling of the continental crust↗, particularly during the early stages of Earth's history.

New continental crust forms as a result of plate tectonics↗, a process ultimately driven by the continuous loss of heat from Earth's interior. Over the period↗ of hundreds of millions of years, tectonic forces have caused areas of continental crust to group together to form supercontinent↗s that have subsequently broken apart. At approximately , one of the earliest known supercontinents, Rodinia↗, began to break apart. The continents later recombined to form Pannotia↗ at , then finally Pangaea↗, which also began to break apart at .

The most recent pattern of ice age↗s began about , and then intensified during the Pleistocene↗ about . High-↗ and middle-latitude↗ regions have since undergone repeated cycles of glaciation and thaw, repeating about every 21,000, 41,000, and 100,000 years. The Last Glacial Period↗, colloquially called the "last ice age", covered large parts of the continents, to the middle latitudes, in ice and ended about 11,700 years ago.

Origin of life and evolution

Main articles: Abiogenesis↗, Earliest known life forms↗, and History of life↗

Chemical reaction↗s led to the first self-replicating molecules about four billion years ago. A half billion years later, the last common ancestor of all current life↗ arose. The evolution of photosynthesis↗ allowed the Sun's energy to be harvested directly by life forms. The resultant molecular oxygen↗ () accumulated in the atmosphere and due to interaction with ultraviolet solar radiation, formed a protective ozone layer↗ () in the upper atmosphere. The incorporation of smaller cells within larger ones resulted in the development of complex cells↗ called eukaryote↗s. True multicellular organisms formed as cells within colonies↗ became increasingly specialized. Aided by the absorption of harmful ultraviolet radiation↗ by the ozone layer, life colonized Earth's surface. Among the earliest fossil↗ evidence for life is microbial mat↗ fossils found in 3.48 billion-year-old sandstone↗ in Western Australia↗, biogenic↗ graphite↗ found in 3.7 billion-year-old metasediment↗ary rocks in Western Greenland↗, and remains of biotic material↗ found in 4.1 billion-year-old rocks in Western Australia. The earliest direct evidence of life↗ on Earth is contained in 3.45 billion-year-old Australian↗ rocks showing fossils of microorganism↗s.

During the Neoproterozoic↗, , much of Earth might have been covered in ice. This hypothesis has been termed "Snowball Earth↗", and it is of particular interest because it preceded the Cambrian explosion↗, when multicellular life forms significantly increased in complexity. Following the Cambrian explosion, , there have been at least five major mass extinctions↗ and many minor ones. Apart from the proposed current Holocene extinction↗ event, the most recent↗ was , when an asteroid impact↗ triggered the extinction of non-avian dinosaurs and other large reptiles, but largely spared small animals, such as insects, mammal↗s, lizards, and birds. Mammalian life has diversified over the past , and several million years ago, an African ape↗ species gained the ability to stand upright. This facilitated tool use and encouraged communication that provided the nutrition and stimulation needed for a larger brain, which led to the evolution of humans↗. The development of agriculture↗, and then civilization↗, led to humans having an influence on Earth↗ and the nature and quantity of other life forms that continues to this day.

Future

Main article: Future of Earth↗

See also: Global catastrophic risk↗

Earth's expected long-term future is tied to that of the Sun. Over the next , solar luminosity will increase by 10%, and over the next by 40%. Earth's increasing surface temperature will accelerate the inorganic carbon cycle↗, possibly reducing concentration to levels lethally low for current plants ( for C4 photosynthesis↗) in approximately . A lack of vegetation would result in the loss of oxygen in the atmosphere, making current animal life impossible. Due to the increased luminosity, Earth's mean temperature may reach 100 °C in 1.5 billion years, and all ocean water will evaporate and be lost to space, which may trigger a runaway greenhouse effect↗, within an estimated 1.6 to 3 billion years. Even if the Sun were stable and eternal, a significant fraction of the water in the modern oceans would descend into the mantle↗, due to reduced steam venting from mid-ocean ridges as the core of the Earth slowly cools.

The Sun will evolve↗ to become a red giant↗ in about . Models predict that the Sun will expand to roughly 1 AU, about 250 times its present radius. Earth's fate is less clear. As a red giant, the Sun will lose roughly 30% of its mass, so, without tidal effects, Earth will move to an orbit 1.7 AU from the Sun when the star reaches its maximum radius, otherwise, with tidal effects, it may enter the Sun's atmosphere and be vaporized, with the heavier elements sinking to the core of the dying sun.

Composition and structure

Further information: Geophysics↗

Earth is a rocky planet↗ and an ocean world↗, the only one of the Solar System with liquid surface water↗. Among all rocky Solar System object↗s it is the most massive, 81 times that of Earth's Moon↗, and among all planetary-mass object↗s of the Solar System it is the object with the highest density↗.

Earth has a rounded shape, through hydrostatic equilibrium↗, with an average diameter of 12742 km, making it the fifth largest↗ planetary sized and largest terrestrial object of the Solar System, and 3.7 times larger than Earth's Moon.

Chemical composition

Further information: Abundance of the chemical elements#Earth↗ See also: Abundance of elements in Earth's crust↗

Earth's mass↗ is approximately (). It is composed mostly of iron (32.1% by mass↗), oxygen↗ (30.1%), silicon↗ (15.1%), magnesium↗ (13.9%), sulfur↗ (2.9%), nickel↗ (1.8%), calcium↗ (1.5%), and aluminum↗ (1.4%), with the remaining 1.2% consisting of trace amounts of other elements. Due to gravitational separation↗, the core is primarily composed of the denser elements: iron (88.8%), with smaller amounts of nickel (5.8%), sulfur (4.5%), and less than 1% trace elements. The most common rock constituents of the crust are oxide↗s. Over 99% of the crust↗ is composed of various oxides of eleven elements, principally oxides containing silicon (the silicate mineral↗s), aluminum, iron, calcium, magnesium, potassium, or sodium.

Internal structure

Main article: Internal structure of Earth↗

+Geologic layers of Earth | Illustration of Earth's cutaway, not to scale
Depth | Component | Density
0–60 | Lithosphere↗ | —
0–35 | Crust↗ | 2.2–2.9
35–660 | Upper mantle↗ | 3.4–4.4
660–2,890 | Lower mantle↗ | 3.4–5.6
100–700 | Asthenosphere↗ | —
2,890–5,100 | Outer core↗ | 9.9–12.2
5,100–6,378 | Inner core↗ | 12.8–13.1

Earth's interior, like that of the other terrestrial planets, is divided into layers by their chemical↗ or physical (rheological↗) properties. The outer layer is a chemically distinct silicate↗ solid crust, which is underlain by a highly viscous↗ solid mantle. The crust is separated from the mantle by the Mohorovičić discontinuity↗. The thickness of the crust varies from about 6 km under the oceans to 30 - for the continents. The crust and the cold, rigid, top of the upper mantle↗ are collectively known as the lithosphere, which is divided into independently moving tectonic plates.

Beneath the lithosphere is the asthenosphere↗, a relatively low-viscosity layer on which the lithosphere rides. Important changes in crystal structure within the mantle occur at 410 km and 660 km below the surface, spanning a transition zone↗ that separates the upper and lower mantle. Beneath the mantle, an extremely low viscosity liquid outer core↗ lies above a solid inner core↗. Earth's inner core may be rotating at a slightly higher angular velocity↗ than the remainder of the planet, advancing by 0.1–0.5° per year, although both somewhat higher and much lower rates have also been proposed. The radius of the inner core is about one-fifth of that of Earth. The density increases with depth.

Internal heat

Main article: Earth's internal heat budget↗

The major contributors to Earth's internal heat are primordial heat (heat left over from Earth's formation) and radiogenic heat (heat produced by radioactive decay). The major heat-producing isotope↗s within Earth are potassium-40↗, uranium-238↗, and thorium-232↗. At the center, the temperature may be up to 6000 °C, and the pressure could reach 360 GPa. Because much of the heat is provided by radioactive decay, scientists postulate that early in Earth's history, before isotopes with short half-lives were depleted, Earth's heat production was much higher. At approximately , twice the present-day heat would have been produced, increasing the rates of mantle convection↗ and plate tectonics, and allowing the production of uncommon igneous rock↗s such as komatiite↗s that are rarely formed today.

The mean heat loss from Earth is , for a global heat loss of . A portion of the core's thermal energy is transported toward the crust by mantle plume↗s, a form of convection consisting of upwellings of higher-temperature rock. These plumes can produce hotspots↗ and flood basalt↗s. More of the heat in Earth is lost through plate tectonics, by mantle upwelling associated with mid-ocean ridge↗s. The final major mode of heat loss is through conduction through the lithosphere, the majority of which occurs under the oceans.

Tectonic plates

Main article: Plate tectonics↗

Earth's mechanically rigid outer layer of Earth's crust↗ and upper mantle↗, the lithosphere↗, is divided into tectonic plates↗. These plates are rigid segments that move relative to each other at one of three boundaries types: at convergent boundaries↗, two plates come together; at divergent boundaries↗, two plates are pulled apart; and at transform boundaries↗, two plates slide past one another laterally. Along these plate boundaries, earthquakes, volcanic activity↗, mountain-building↗, and oceanic trench↗ formation can occur. The tectonic plates ride on top of the asthenosphere↗, the solid but less-viscous part of the upper mantle that can flow and move along with the plates.

As the tectonic plates migrate, oceanic crust is subducted↗ under the leading edges of the plates at convergent boundaries. At the same time, the upwelling of mantle material at divergent boundaries creates mid-ocean ridges. The combination of these processes recycles the oceanic crust back into the mantle. Due to this recycling, most of the ocean floor is less than old. The oldest oceanic crust is located in the Western Pacific and is estimated to be old. By comparison, the oldest dated continental crust is , although zircons have been found preserved as clasts within Eoarchean sedimentary rocks that give ages up to , indicating that at least some continental crust existed at that time.

The seven major plates are the Pacific↗, North American↗, Eurasian↗, African↗, Antarctic↗, Indo-Australian↗, and South American↗. Other notable plates include the Arabian Plate↗, the Caribbean Plate↗, the Nazca Plate↗ off the west coast of South America and the Scotia Plate↗ in the southern Atlantic Ocean. The Australian Plate fused with the Indian Plate between . The fastest-moving plates are the oceanic plates, with the Cocos Plate↗ advancing at a rate of 75 mm/year and the Pacific Plate moving 52 –. At the other extreme, the slowest-moving plate is the South American Plate, progressing at a typical rate of 10.6 mm/year.

Crust

Earth's crust may be divided into oceanic↗ and continental↗ crust. The oceanic crust is predominantly basalt↗ic, while the continental crust has more of lower density materials such as granite↗, metamorphic rocks and sediments, which while covering nearly 75% of the continental surfaces make only about 5% of the mass of the crust.

While the oceanic crust is covered by the ocean↗, the ocean also covers continental crust, the continental shelves↗, which makes these parts of the ocean shelf sea↗s. The oceanic crust forms large oceanic basin↗s with features like abyssal plain↗s, seamount↗s, submarine volcano↗es, oceanic trench↗es, submarine canyon↗s, oceanic plateau↗s, and a globe-spanning mid-ocean ridge↗ system. This submarine terrain of the ocean floor has an average bathymetric↗ depth of 4 km, and is as varied as the terrain above sea level.

Surface

Further information: Planetary surface↗, Land cover↗, Land↗, and Pedosphere↗

Earth's surface is the boundary between the atmosphere and the solid Earth and oceans. The surface is continually being shaped by internal plate tectonic↗ processes including earthquakes↗ and volcanism↗; by weathering↗ and erosion↗ driven by ice, water, wind and temperature; and by biological processes↗ including the growth and decomposition of biomass↗ into soil↗.

Earth's surface has an area of about 510 e6km2 and can be divided into two hemispheres↗: by latitude↗ into the polar Northern↗ and Southern↗ hemispheres, by longitude↗ into the continental Eastern↗ and Western↗ hemispheres or by its roughly as Water↗ and Land hemisphere↗.

Most of Earth's surface is ocean water: 70.8% or 361 e6km2. This vast pool of salty water is often called the world ocean, and makes Earth with its dynamic hydrosphere↗ a water world or ocean world↗. Indeed, in Earth's early history the ocean may have covered Earth completely. The world ocean is commonly divided into the Pacific Ocean, Atlantic Ocean, Indian Ocean, Southern Ocean, and Arctic Ocean, from largest to smallest. At Earth's polar regions↗, the ocean surface↗ is covered by seasonally variable amounts of sea ice↗ that often connects with polar land, permafrost↗ and ice sheet↗s, forming polar ice cap↗s.

Earth's land covers 29.2%, or 149 e6km2 of Earth's surface. The land surface includes many island↗s around the globe, but most of the land surface is taken by the four continental landmass↗es, which are (in descending order): Africa-Eurasia↗, America↗, Antarctica↗, and Australia↗. These landmasses are further broken down and grouped into the continent↗s. Land can be covered↗ by surface water↗, snow, ice, artificial structures or vegetation. Most of Earth's land hosts vegetation, but considerable amounts of land are ice sheet↗s (10%, not including the equally large area of land under permafrost↗) or desert↗s (33%).

The pedosphere↗ is the outermost layer of Earth's land surface and is composed of soil↗ and subject to soil formation↗ processes. Soil is crucial for land to be arable. Earth's total arable land↗ is 10.7% of the land surface, with 1.3% being permanent cropland. Earth has an estimated 16.7 e6km2 of cropland and 33.5 e6km2 of pastureland.

Surface topography

Earth's surface topography↗ comprises both the topography of the ocean surface↗, and the shape↗ of Earth's land surface. The terrain↗ of the land surface varies greatly and consists of mountains, desert↗s, plain↗s, plateau↗s, and other landform↗s. The elevation of the land surface varies from a low point of -418 m at the Dead Sea↗, to a maximum altitude of 8848 m at the top of Mount Everest↗. The mean height of land above sea level is about 797 m.

Shape

Main article: Figure of the Earth↗

Further information: Earth radius↗, Earth's circumference↗, Spherical Earth{{!}}Earth curvature↗, and Geomorphology↗ See also: List of highest mountains on Earth↗

Due to Earth's rotation its shape↗ is that of an ellipsoid↗, bulging at its equator↗; its diameter is 43 km longer there than at its poles↗. Earth's shape also has local topographic↗ variations; the largest local variations, like the Mariana Trench↗ (10925 m below local sea level), shortens Earth's average radius by 0.17% and Mount Everest↗ (8848 m above local sea level) lengthens it by 0.14%. Since Earth's surface is farthest out from its center of mass↗ at its equatorial bulge, the summit of the volcano Chimborazo↗ in Ecuador (6384.4 km) is its farthest point out. Parallel to the rigid land topography the ocean exhibits a more dynamic topography↗.

To measure the local variation of Earth's topography, geodesy↗ employs an idealized Earth producing a geoid↗ shape. Such a shape is gained if the ocean is idealized, covering Earth completely and without any perturbations such as tides and winds. The result is a smooth but irregular geoid surface, providing a mean sea level as a reference level for topographic measurements.

Gravity and magnetic field

Magnetic field

Main article: Earth's magnetic field↗

The main part of Earth's magnetic field is generated in the core, the site of a dynamo↗ process that converts the kinetic energy of thermally and compositionally driven convection into electrical and magnetic field energy. The field extends outwards from the core, through the mantle, and up to Earth's surface, where it is approximately a dipole↗. The poles of the dipole are located close to Earth's geographic poles. At the equator of the magnetic field, the magnetic-field strength at the surface is 3.05 T↗, with a magnetic dipole moment↗ of 7.79 Am at epoch 2000, decreasing nearly 6% per century (although it still remains stronger than its long time average). The convection movements in the core are chaotic; the magnetic poles drift and periodically change alignment. This causes secular variation↗ of the main field and field reversals↗ at irregular intervals averaging a few times every million years. The most recent reversal occurred approximately 700,000 years ago.

The extent of Earth's magnetic field in space defines the magnetosphere↗. Ions and electrons of the solar wind are deflected by the magnetosphere; solar wind pressure compresses the day-side of the magnetosphere, to about 10 Earth radii, and extends the night-side magnetosphere into a long tail. Because the velocity of the solar wind is greater than the speed at which waves propagate through the solar wind, a supersonic bow shock↗ precedes the day-side magnetosphere within the solar wind. Charged particle↗s are contained within the magnetosphere; the plasmasphere is defined by low-energy particles that essentially follow magnetic field lines as Earth rotates. The ring current is defined by medium-energy particle↗s that drift relative to the geomagnetic field, but with paths that are still dominated by the magnetic field, and the Van Allen radiation belt↗s are formed by high-energy particles whose motion is essentially random, but contained in the magnetosphere. During magnetic storm↗s and substorm↗s, charged particles can be deflected from the outer magnetosphere and especially the magnetotail, directed along field lines into Earth's ionosphere↗, where atmospheric atoms can be excited and ionized, causing an aurora↗.

Gravitational field

Main article: Gravity of Earth↗

The gravity of Earth is the acceleration↗ that is imparted to objects due to the distribution of mass within Earth. Near Earth's surface, gravitational acceleration↗ is approximately 9.8 m/s2. Local differences in topography, geology, and deeper tectonic structure cause local and broad regional differences in Earth's gravitational field, known as gravity anomalies↗. The Hill sphere↗, or the sphere of gravitational influence↗, of Earth is about 1.5 e6km in radius. This is the maximum distance at which Earth's gravitational influence is stronger than that of the more distant Sun and planets. Objects must orbit Earth within this radius, or they can become unbound by the gravitational perturbation of the Sun.

Moon and orbital space

Further information: Satellite system (astronomy)↗

Moon

Main articles: Moon↗, Lunar theory↗, and Orbit of the Moon↗

The Moon is a relatively large, terrestrial↗, planet-like natural satellite↗, with a diameter about one-quarter of Earth's. It is the largest moon in the Solar System relative to the size of its planet, although Charon↗ is larger relative to the dwarf planet Pluto↗. The natural satellites of other planets are also referred to as "moons", after Earth's. The Moon and Earth orbit a common barycenter↗ every 27.32 days relative to the background stars. When combined with the Earth–Moon system's common orbit around the Sun, the period of the synodic month↗, from new moon to new moon, is 29.53 days.

Viewed from the celestial north pole↗, the motion of Earth, the Moon, and their axial rotations are all counterclockwise↗. Viewed from Earth, the Moon is just far enough away to have almost the same apparent-sized disk as the Sun. The angular size↗ (or solid angle↗) of these two bodies match because, although the Sun's diameter is about 400 times as large as the Moon's, it is also 400 times more distant. This allows total and annular solar eclipses to occur on Earth. The orbital planes are not precisely aligned: the Earth-Moon plane is tilted up to ±5.1 degrees against the Earth–Sun plane (the ecliptic↗). Without this tilt, there would be an eclipse every two weeks, alternating between lunar eclipse↗s and solar eclipse↗s.

The gravitational attraction between Earth and the Moon causes lunar tide↗s on Earth. The same effect on the Moon has led to its tidal locking↗: its rotation period is the same as the time it takes to orbit Earth. As a result, it always presents the same face to the planet. As the Moon orbits Earth, different parts of its face are illuminated by the Sun, leading to the lunar phase↗s. Due to their tidal interaction↗, the Moon recedes from Earth at the rate of approximately 38 mm/yr. Over millions of years, these tiny modifications—and the lengthening of Earth's day by about 23 μs↗/yr—add up to significant changes. During the Ediacaran↗ period, for example, (approximately ) there were 400±7 days in a year, with each day lasting 21.9±0.4 hours.

The Moon may have dramatically affected the development of life by moderating the planet's climate. Paleontological↗ evidence and computer simulations show that Earth's axial tilt is stabilized by tidal interactions with the Moon. Some theorists think that without this stabilization against the torque↗s applied by the Sun and planets to Earth's equatorial bulge, the rotational axis might be chaotically unstable, exhibiting large changes over millions of years, as is the case for Mars, though this is disputed.

The most widely accepted theory of the Moon's origin, the giant-impact hypothesis↗, states that it formed from the collision of a Mars-size protoplanet called Theia with the early Earth. This hypothesis explains the Moon's relative lack of iron and volatile elements and the fact that its composition is nearly identical to that of Earth's crust. Computer simulations suggest that two blob-like remnants of this protoplanet could be inside the Earth.

Asteroids and artificial satellites

Main articles: Near-Earth object↗ and Claimed moons of Earth↗

Earth's co-orbital asteroids↗ population consists of quasi-satellite↗s, objects with a horseshoe orbit↗ and trojans↗. There are at least seven quasi-satellites, including 469219 Kamoʻoalewa↗, ranging in diameter from 10 m to 5000 m. A trojan asteroid↗ companion, , is librating↗ around the leading Lagrange triangular point↗, L4, in Earth's orbit↗ around the Sun. The tiny near-Earth asteroid↗ makes close approaches to the Earth–Moon system roughly every twenty years. During these approaches, it can orbit Earth for brief periods of time.

As of September 2021, there are 4,550 operational, human-made satellite↗s orbiting Earth. There are also inoperative satellites, including Vanguard 1↗, the oldest satellite currently in orbit, and over 16,000 pieces of tracked space debris↗. Earth's largest artificial satellite is the International Space Station↗ (ISS).

Orbit and rotation

Rotation

Main article: Earth's rotation↗

Earth's rotation period relative to the Sun—its mean solar day—is 86,400 seconds of mean solar time (86,400.0025 SI↗ seconds). Because Earth's solar day is now slightly longer than it was during the 19th century due to tidal deceleration↗, each day varies between 0 and 2 ms↗ longer than the mean solar day.

Earth's rotation period relative to the fixed star↗s, called its stellar day by the International Earth Rotation and Reference Systems Service↗ (IERS), is 86,164.0989 seconds of mean solar time (UT1↗), or 23 56 4.0989. Earth's rotation period relative to the precessing↗ or moving mean March equinox↗ (when the Sun is at 90° on the equator), is 86,164.0905 seconds of mean solar time (UT1) (23 56 4.0905). Thus the sidereal day is shorter than the stellar day by about 8.4 ms.

Apart from meteors within the atmosphere and low-orbiting satellites, the main apparent motion of celestial bodies in Earth's sky is to the west at a rate of 15°/h = 15'/min. For bodies near the celestial equator↗, this is equivalent to an apparent diameter of the Sun or the Moon every two minutes; from Earth's surface, the apparent sizes of the Sun and the Moon are approximately the same.

Orbit and location

Main articles: Earth's orbit↗ and Earth's location↗

Earth orbits the Sun at an average distance is about 150 e6km. This makes Earth the third-closest planet to the Sun and part of the inner Solar System↗. Its orbital distance is the basis for the astronomical unit↗ (AU) and is equal to roughly 8.3 light minute↗s or 380 times Earth's distance to the Moon↗. Earth orbits the Sun every 365.2564 mean solar day↗s, or one sidereal year↗. With an apparent movement of the Sun in Earth's sky at a rate of about 1°/day eastward, which is one apparent Sun or Moon diameter every 12 hours. Due to this motion, on average it takes 24 hours—a solar day—for Earth to complete a full rotation about its axis so that the Sun returns to the meridian↗, slightly longer than the sidereal day.

The orbital speed of Earth averages at 29.7827 km/s, which is fast enough to travel a distance equal to Earth's diameter, about 12742 km, in seven minutes, and the distance from Earth to the Moon, 384400 km, in about 3.5 hours. Viewed from a vantage point above the Sun and Earth's north poles, Earth orbits in a counterclockwise direction about the Sun. Earth, along with all of the other planets in the Solar System, orbits roughly in the same flat plane, known as the invariable plane↗. Earth's inclination to this plane is about 1.58°.

Earth, along with rest of the Solar System, is situated in the Milky Way↗ and orbits about 28,000 light-year↗s from its center. It is about 20 light-years above the galactic plane↗ in the Orion Arm↗.

Axial tilt and seasons

Main article: Axial tilt#Earth↗

The axial tilt of Earth is approximately 23.439281° with the axis of the plane of Earth's orbit↗ by definition pointing always towards the Celestial Poles↗. Due to Earth's axial tilt, the amount of sunlight reaching any given point on the surface varies over the course of the year. This causes the seasonal change in climate, with summer in the Northern Hemisphere↗ occurring when the Tropic of Cancer↗ is facing the Sun, and in the Southern Hemisphere↗ when the Tropic of Capricorn↗ faces the Sun. In each instance, winter occurs simultaneously in the opposite hemisphere.

During the summer, the day lasts longer, and the Sun climbs higher in the sky. In winter, the climate becomes cooler and the days shorter. Above the Arctic Circle↗ and below the Antarctic Circle↗ there is no daylight at all for part of the year, causing a polar night↗, and this night extends for several months at the poles themselves. These same latitudes also experience a midnight sun↗, where the sun remains visible all day.

By astronomical convention, the four seasons can be determined by the solstices—the points in the orbit of maximum axial tilt toward or away from the Sun—and the equinox↗es, when Earth's rotational axis is aligned with its orbital axis. In the Northern Hemisphere, winter solstice↗ currently occurs around 21 December; summer solstice↗ is near 21 June, spring equinox is around 20 March and autumnal equinox↗ is about 22 or 23 September. In the Southern Hemisphere, the situation is reversed, with the summer and winter solstices exchanged and the spring and autumnal equinox dates swapped.

The angle of Earth's axial tilt is relatively stable over long periods of time. Its axial tilt does undergo nutation↗; a slight, irregular motion with a main period of 18.6 years. The orientation (rather than the angle) of Earth's axis also changes over time, precessing↗ around in a complete circle over each 25,800-year cycle; this precession is the reason for the difference between a sidereal year and a tropical year↗. Both of these motions are caused by the varying attraction of the Sun and the Moon on Earth's equatorial bulge. The poles also migrate a few meters across Earth's surface. This polar motion↗ has multiple, cyclical components, which collectively are termed quasiperiodic motion↗. In addition to an annual component to this motion, there is a 14-month cycle called the Chandler wobble↗. Earth's rotational velocity also varies in a phenomenon known as length-of-day variation.

Earth's orbit is slightly elliptical rather than perfectly circular, and its closest approach to the Sun is called perihelion↗. In modern times, Earth's perihelion occurs around 3 January, and its aphelion↗ around 4 July. These dates shift over time due to precession and changes to the orbit, the latter of which follows cyclical patterns known as Milankovitch cycles↗. The annual change in the Earth–Sun distance causes an increase of about 6.8% in solar energy reaching Earth at perihelion relative to aphelion. Because the Southern Hemisphere is tilted toward the Sun at about the same time that Earth reaches the closest approach to the Sun, the Southern Hemisphere receives slightly more energy from the Sun than does the northern over the course of a year. This effect is much less significant than the total energy change due to the axial tilt, and most of the excess energy is absorbed by the higher proportion of water in the Southern Hemisphere.

Atmosphere and climate

Main article: Atmosphere of Earth↗

Earth's atmosphere has no definite boundary, gradually becoming thinner and fading into outer space. Three-quarters of the atmosphere's mass is contained within the first 11 km of the surface; this lowest layer is called the troposphere. Energy from the Sun heats this layer, and the surface below, causing expansion of the air. This lower-density air then rises and is replaced by cooler, higher-density air. The result is atmospheric circulation↗ that drives the weather and climate through redistribution of thermal energy.

The atmosphere is composed of 78.084% nitrogen↗, 20.946% oxygen, 0.934% argon↗, and trace amounts of carbon dioxide and other gaseous molecules. Water vapor↗ content varies between 0.01% and 4% but averages about 1%. Earth's biosphere↗ has significantly altered its atmosphere↗. Oxygenic photosynthesis↗ evolved , forming↗ the primarily nitrogen–oxygen atmosphere of today. This change enabled the proliferation of aerobic organisms↗ and, indirectly, the formation of the ozone layer due to the subsequent conversion of atmospheric into↗. The ozone layer blocks ultraviolet solar radiation↗, permitting life on land. Other atmospheric functions important to life include transporting water vapor, providing useful gases, causing small meteors to burn up before they strike the surface, and moderating temperature. This last phenomenon is the greenhouse effect↗: trace molecules within the atmosphere serve to capture thermal energy↗ emitted from the surface, thereby raising the average temperature. Water vapor, carbon dioxide, methane↗, nitrous oxide↗, and ozone↗ are the primary greenhouse gases in the atmosphere. Without this heat-retention effect, the average surface temperature would be -18 °C, in contrast to the current +15 °C, and life on Earth probably would not exist in its current form.

Exosphere

The exosphere↗ is where the atmosphere thins out into the magnetosphere, where the geomagnetic fields interact with the solar wind.

Thermal energy causes some of the molecules at the outer edge of the atmosphere to increase their velocity to the point where they can escape from Earth's gravity. This causes a slow but steady loss of the atmosphere into space↗. Because unfixed hydrogen↗ has a low molecular mass↗, it can achieve escape velocity↗ more readily, and it leaks into outer space at a greater rate than other gases. The leakage of hydrogen into space contributes to the shifting of Earth's atmosphere and surface from an initially reducing↗ state to its current oxidizing one. Photosynthesis provided a source of free oxygen, but the loss of reducing agents such as hydrogen is thought to have been a necessary precondition for the widespread accumulation of oxygen in the atmosphere. Hence the ability of hydrogen to escape from the atmosphere may have influenced the nature of life that developed on Earth. In the current, oxygen-rich atmosphere most hydrogen is converted into water before it has an opportunity to escape. Instead, most of the hydrogen loss comes from the destruction of methane in the upper atmosphere.

Upper atmosphere

The upper atmosphere, the atmosphere above the troposphere, is usually divided into the stratosphere↗, mesosphere↗, and thermosphere↗. Each layer has a different lapse rate, defining the rate of change in temperature with height.

Within the stratosphere is the ozone layer, a component that partially shields the surface from ultraviolet light and thus is important for life on Earth. The Kármán line↗, defined as 100 km above Earth's surface, is a working definition for the boundary between the atmosphere and outer space↗.

Troposphere

Main article: Troposphere↗

The troposphere lies below the stratosphere of the upper atmosphere, and immediate above Earth's surface (including the peplosphere↗). As such it is the atmospheric layer of Earth's surface weather and climate. Its height varies with latitude, ranging between 8 km at the poles to 17 km at the equator, with some variation resulting from weather and seasonal factors.

The atmospheric pressure↗ at Earth's sea level averages 101.325 kPa, with a scale height↗ of about 8.5 km.

Weather and climate

Main articles: Weather↗ and Climate↗

Earth receives 1361 W/m2 of solar irradiance↗. The amount of solar energy that reaches Earth's surface decreases with increasing latitude. At higher latitudes, the sunlight reaches the surface at lower angles, and it must pass through thicker columns of the atmosphere. As a result, the mean annual air temperature at sea level decreases by about 0.4 C-change per degree of latitude from the equator.

Earth's surface can be subdivided into specific latitudinal belts of approximately homogeneous climate. Ranging from the equator to the polar regions, these are the tropical (or equatorial), subtropical↗, temperate↗ and polar↗ climates. The primary atmospheric circulation bands consist of the trade winds↗ in the equatorial region below 30° latitude and the westerlies↗ in the mid-latitudes between 30° and 60°. Ocean heat content↗ and currents↗ are also important factors in determining climate, particularly the thermohaline circulation↗ that distributes thermal energy from the equatorial oceans to the polar regions.

Water vapor generated through surface evaporation forms clouds and is transported by circulatory patterns in the atmosphere. Clouds cover↗ around two-thirds of Earth's surface, more so over oceans than land. When this water condenses and gets heavy enough it falls to the surface as precipitation↗. If not frozen, the resulting surface water slowly evaporates again. This water cycle↗ is a vital mechanism for supporting life on land and is a primary factor in the erosion of surface features over geological periods. Precipitation patterns vary widely, ranging from several meters of water per year to less than a millimeter. Atmospheric circulation, topographic features, and temperature differences determine the average precipitation that falls in each region.

Major local factors that affect a location's climates are its proximity to oceans↗, the oceanic and atmospheric circulation, and topology. Places close to oceans typically have colder summers and warmer winters, due to the fact that oceans can store large amounts of heat. The wind transports the cold or the heat of the ocean to the land. Atmospheric circulation also plays an important role: San Francisco and Washington DC are both coastal cities at about the same latitude. San Francisco's climate is significantly more moderate as the prevailing wind direction is from sea to land. Finally, temperatures decrease with height↗ causing mountainous areas to be colder than low-lying areas.

The commonly used Köppen climate classification↗ system has five broad groups (humid tropics↗, arid↗, humid middle latitudes↗, continental↗ and cold polar↗), which are further divided into more specific subtypes. The Köppen system rates regions based on observed temperature and precipitation. Surface air temperature can rise to↗ around 55 °C in hot desert↗s, such as Death Valley↗, and can fall as low as↗ -89 °C in Antarctica↗.

Hydrosphere

Main article: Hydrosphere↗

Further information: Ocean↗, Sea↗, and Cryosphere↗ Earth's hydrosphere is the sum of Earth's water and its distribution. Most of Earth's hydrosphere consists of Earth's global ocean. Earth's hydrosphere also consists of water in the atmosphere and on land, including clouds, inland seas, lakes, rivers, and underground waters. The mass of the oceans is approximately 1.35 metric ton↗s or about 1/4400 of Earth's total mass. The oceans cover an area of 361.8 e6km2 with a mean depth of 3682 m, resulting in an estimated volume of 1.332 e9km3.

If all of Earth's crustal surface were at the same elevation as a smooth sphere, the depth of the resulting world ocean would be 2.7 to 2.8 km. About 97.5% of the water is saline↗; the remaining 2.5% is fresh water↗. Most fresh water, about 68.7%, is present as ice in ice cap↗s and glacier↗s. The remaining 30% is ground water↗, 1% surface water↗ (covering only 2.8% of Earth's land) and other small forms of fresh water deposits such as permafrost↗, water vapor↗ in the atmosphere, biological binding, etc.

In Earth's coldest regions, snow survives over the summer and changes into ice↗. This accumulated snow and ice eventually forms into glacier↗s, bodies of ice that flow under the influence of their own gravity. Alpine glaciers↗ form in mountainous areas, whereas vast ice sheets↗ form over land in polar regions. The flow of glaciers erodes the surface, changing it dramatically, with the formation of U-shaped valley↗s and other landforms. Sea ice↗ in the Arctic covers an area about as big as the United States, although it is quickly retreating as a consequence of climate change.

The average salinity↗ of Earth's oceans is about 35 grams of salt per kilogram of seawater (3.5% salt). Most of this salt was released from volcanic activity or extracted from cool igneous rocks. The oceans are also a reservoir of dissolved atmospheric gases, which are essential for the survival of many aquatic life forms. Sea water has an important influence on the world's climate, with the oceans acting as a large heat reservoir↗. Shifts in the oceanic temperature distribution can cause significant weather shifts, such as the El Niño–Southern Oscillation↗.

The abundance of water, particularly liquid water, on Earth's surface is a unique feature that distinguishes it from other planets in the Solar System. Solar System planets with considerable atmospheres do partly host atmospheric water vapor, but they lack surface conditions for stable surface water. Despite some moons↗ showing signs of large reservoirs of extraterrestrial liquid water↗, with possibly even more volume than Earth's ocean, all of them are large bodies of water↗ under a kilometers-thick frozen surface layer.

Biosphere

Main article: Biosphere↗

Earth is the only known place that has ever been habitable↗ for life. Earth's life developed↗ in Earth's early bodies of water some hundred million years after Earth formed, roughly 4 billion years ago. Earth provides liquid water—an environment where complex organic molecules↗ can assemble and interact, and sufficient energy to sustain a metabolism↗. Plants and other organisms take up nutrient↗s from water, soils and the atmosphere. These nutrients are constantly recycled between different species.

Earth's life has been shaping and inhabiting many particular ecosystem↗s on Earth and has eventually expanded globally forming an overarching biosphere. Earth's life has also over time greatly diversified, allowing the biosphere to have different biome↗s, which are inhabited by comparatively similar plants and animals. The different biomes developed at distinct elevations or water depths↗, planetary temperature latitude↗s and on land also with different humidity↗. Earth's species diversity↗ and biomass↗ reaches a peak in shallow waters and with forests, particularly in equatorial, warm and humid conditions↗. While freezing polar regions↗ and high altitudes↗, or extremely arid areas↗ are relatively barren of plant and animal life.

Therefore, life has impacted Earth, significantly altering Earth's atmosphere and surface over long periods of time, causing changes like the Great Oxidation Event↗.

Challenges for life on Earth

Extreme weather↗, such as tropical cyclone↗s, occurs over most of Earth's surface and has a large impact on life in those areas. From 1980 to 2000, these events caused an average of 11,800 human deaths per year. Many places are subject to earthquake↗s, landslide↗s, tsunami↗s, volcanic eruption↗s, tornado↗es, blizzard↗s, flood↗s, drought↗s, wildfire↗s, and other calamities and disasters. Human impact↗ is felt in many areas due to pollution of the air and water, acid rain↗, loss of vegetation (overgrazing↗, deforestation↗, desertification↗), loss of wildlife, species extinction↗, soil degradation↗, soil depletion↗ and erosion↗. Human activities release greenhouse gases into the atmosphere which cause global warming↗. This is driving changes↗ such as the melting of glaciers and ice sheets↗, a global rise in average sea levels↗, increased risk of drought and wildfires, and migration of species to colder areas.

Human geography

Main article: Human geography↗

See also: World↗

Humans, who originated from earlier primate↗s in Eastern Africa 300,000 years ago, have since been migrating↗ around Earth, and with the advent of agriculture in the 10th millennium BCE, have been increasingly settling↗ Earth's land. In the 20th century, Antarctica↗ became the last continent to be explored and settled by humans, although human presence there remains limited. Since the 19th century, the human population↗ has grown exponentially to eight billion in the 2020s, and is projected to peak at around ten billion in the second half of the 21st century. Most of the growth is expected to take place in sub-Saharan Africa↗.

Distribution and density of human population↗ varies greatly around the world with the majority living in south to eastern Asia and 90% inhabiting the Northern Hemisphere↗ of Earth, partly due to the hemispherical predominance of the world's land mass↗, with 68% of the world's land mass being in the Northern Hemisphere. Furthermore, since the 19th century humans have increasingly converged into urban area↗s, with the majority living in urban areas by the 21st century.

Beyond Earth's surface, humans have lived only in a few special-purpose deep underground↗ and underwater↗ presences and a few space station↗s. The human population virtually completely remains on Earth's surface, fully depending on Earth and the environment it sustains. Since the second half of the 20th century, some hundreds of humans have temporarily stayed beyond Earth↗, a tiny fraction of whom have reached another celestial body, the Moon.

Earth has been subject to extensive human settlement, and humans have developed diverse societies and cultures. Most of Earth's land has been territorially claimed since the 19th century by sovereign state↗s (countries) separated by political borders↗, and 205 such states↗ exist today, with only parts of Antarctica and a few small regions remaining unclaimed↗. Together, most of these states form the United Nations↗, the leading worldwide intergovernmental organization↗, which extends human governance over the ocean↗ and Antarctica↗, and therefore all of Earth.

Natural resources and land use

Main articles: Natural resource↗ and Land use↗

Earth has resources that have been exploited by humans. Those termed non-renewable resource↗s, such as fossil fuel↗s, are only replenished over geological timescales. Large deposits of fossil fuels are obtained from Earth's crust, consisting of coal, petroleum, and natural gas. These deposits are used by humans both for energy production and as feedstock for chemical production. Mineral ore↗ bodies have also been formed within the crust through a process of ore genesis↗, resulting from actions of magmatism↗, erosion, and plate tectonics. These metals and other elements are extracted by mining, a process which often causes environmental and health damage.

Earth's biosphere produces many useful biological products for humans, including food, wood, pharmaceutical↗s, oxygen, and the recycling of organic waste. The land-based ecosystem depends upon topsoil↗ and fresh water, and the oceanic ecosystem depends on dissolved nutrients washed down from the land. In 2019, 39 e6km2 of Earth's land surface consisted of forest and woodlands, 12 e6km2 was shrub and grassland, 40 e6km2 were used for animal feed production and grazing, and 11 e6km2 were cultivated as croplands. Of the 1214% of ice-free land that is used for croplands, 2 percentage point↗s were irrigated in 2015. Humans use natural and manufactured building material↗s to construct shelters and infrastructure.

Environmental impact

Main articles: Human impact on the environment↗ and Climate change↗

Human activities have impacted Earth's environments. Through activities such as the burning of fossil fuels, humans have been increasing the amount of greenhouse gas↗es in the atmosphere, altering Earth's energy budget↗ and climate. It is estimated that global temperatures in the year 2020 were 1.2 C-change warmer than the preindustrial baseline. This increase in temperature, known as global warming↗, has contributed to the melting of glaciers↗, rising sea levels↗, increased risk of drought and wildfires, and migration of species to colder areas.

The concept of planetary boundaries↗ was introduced to quantify humanity's impact on Earth. Of the nine identified boundaries, five have been crossed: Biosphere integrity↗, climate change, chemical pollution, destruction of wild habitats and the nitrogen cycle↗ are thought to have passed the safe threshold. As of 2018, no country meets the basic needs of its population without transgressing planetary boundaries. It is thought possible to provide all basic physical needs globally within sustainable levels of resource use.

In culture

Main articles: Earth in culture↗ and Earth in science fiction↗

Human cultures↗ have developed many views of the planet. Earth is sometimes personified↗ as a deity↗. In many cultures, it is a mother goddess↗ that is also the primary fertility deity↗. Creation myth↗s in many religions involve the creation of Earth by a supernatural deity or deities. The Gaia hypothesis↗, developed in the mid-20th century, compared Earth's environments and life as a single self-regulating organism leading to broad stabilization of the conditions of habitability.

Scientific investigation has resulted in several culturally transformative shifts in people's view of the planet. Initial belief in a flat Earth↗ was gradually displaced in Ancient Greece↗ by the idea of a spherical Earth↗, which was attributed to both the philosophers Pythagoras↗ and Parmenides↗. Earth was generally believed to be the center of the universe↗ until the 16th century, when scientists first concluded that it was a moving object↗, one of the planets of the Solar System.

It was only during the 19th century that geologists realized Earth's age↗ was at least many millions of years. Lord Kelvin↗ used thermodynamics↗ to estimate the age of Earth to be between 20 million and 400 million years in 1864, sparking a vigorous debate on the subject; it was only when radioactivity and radioactive dating↗ were discovered in the late 19th and early 20th centuries that a reliable mechanism for determining Earth's age was established, proving the planet to be billions of years old.

Images of Earth taken from space↗, particularly Earthrise↗ and The Blue Marble↗, have been credited with altering the way that people viewed the planet that they lived on, called the overview effect↗, emphasizing its beauty, uniqueness, community and apparent fragility. In particular, this caused a realization of the scope of effects from human activity on Earth's environment. Enabled by science, particularly Earth observation↗, humans have started to take action on environmental issues↗ globally, acknowledging the impact of humans and the interconnectedness of Earth's environments↗.

See also

Notes

References

External links

Earth – Profile – Solar System Exploration – NASA↗
Earth Observatory – NASA
Earth – Videos – International Space Station:
Video (01:02) on YouTube – Earth (time-lapse)
Video (00:27) on YouTube – Earth and aurora↗s (time-lapse)
Google Earth 3D, interactive map
Interactive 3D visualization of the Sun, Earth and Moon system
GPlates Portal (University of Sydney)

Venus

Venus is the second planet↗ from the Sun. Similar in size and mass to Earth, Venus has no liquid water↗, and its atmosphere↗ is far thicker and denser than that of any other rocky body in the Solar System. The atmosphere is composed mostly of carbon dioxide↗ and has a thick cloud layer of sulfuric acid↗ that spans the whole planet. At the mean surface level, the atmosphere reaches a temperature of 737 K and a pressure↗ 92 times greater than Earth's at sea level, turning the lowest layer of the atmosphere into a supercritical fluid↗. From Earth, Venus is visible as a star-like point of light, appearing brighter↗ than any other natural point of light in the sky, as either the brightest "morning star" or "evening star".

Venus orbits closer to the Sun than the Earth does. The orbits of Venus and Earth make the two planets approach each other in synodic period↗s of 1.6 years. In the course of this, Venus comes closer to Earth than any other planet. In interplanetary spaceflight↗ from Earth, Venus is frequently used as a waypoint for gravity assist↗s, offering a faster and more economical route. Venus has no moons↗ and a very slow retrograde↗ rotation about its axis, a result of competing forces of solar tidal locking and differential heating of Venus's massive atmosphere. As a result, a Venusian day is 116.75 Earth days long, about half a Venusian solar year↗, which is 224.7 Earth days long.

Venus has a weak magnetosphere↗; lacking an internal dynamo↗, it is induced by the solar wind↗ interacting with the atmosphere. Internally, Venus has a core↗, a mantle↗, and a crust↗. Internal heat↗ escapes through active volcanism↗, resulting in resurfacing↗, instead of plate tectonics↗. Venus may have had liquid surface water early in its history with a habitable environment↗, before a runaway greenhouse effect↗ evaporated any water and turned Venus into its present state. There are atmospheric conditions at cloud layer altitudes that are the most similar ones to Earth in the Solar System and have been identified as possibly favourable for life on Venus↗, with potential biomarkers found in 2020, spurring new research and missions to Venus↗.

Throughout history humans across the globe have observed Venus and it has acquired particular importance in many cultures. With telescopes, the phases of Venus↗ became discernible and, by 1613, were presented as decisive evidence disproving the then-dominant geocentric model↗ and supporting the heliocentric model↗. Venus was visited for the first time in 1961 by Venera 1↗, which flew past the planet, achieving the first interplanetary spaceflight. The first data from Venus were returned during the second interplanetary mission, Mariner 2↗, in 1962. In 1967, the first interplanetary impactor, Venera 4↗, reached Venus, followed by the lander Venera 7↗ in 1970. As of 2025, Solar Orbiter↗ is on its way to fly-by Venus in 2026, and the next mission planned to launch to Venus is the Venus Life Finder↗, scheduled for 2026 as well.

Physical characteristics

Venus is one of the four terrestrial planet↗s in the Solar System, meaning that it is a rocky body like Earth. It is similar to Earth in size and mass and is often described as Earth's "sister" or "twin". Venus is very close to spherical due to its slow rotation. It has a diameter of 12103.6 km—only 638.4 km less than Earth's—and its mass is 81.5% of Earth's, making it the third-smallest planet in the Solar System. Conditions on the surface of Venus differ radically from those on Earth because its dense atmosphere↗ is 96.5% carbon dioxide, causing an intense greenhouse effect↗, with most of the remaining 3.5% being nitrogen↗. The surface pressure is 9.3 MPa, and the average surface temperature is 737 K, above the critical points↗ of both major constituents and making the surface atmosphere a supercritical fluid↗ of mainly supercritical carbon dioxide↗ and some supercritical nitrogen.

Natural history

Formation

Further information: Nebular hypothesis↗ The rocky terrestrial planets including Venus are thought to have formed in 5 stages: dust settling, planetesimal↗ formation, planetary embryos, giant impacts, and finally formation of atmospheres. Limited measurements from Venus have prevented a more detailed analysis of the formation timeline.

Future

Venus is expected to be destroyed, along with Mercury, and possibly the Earth and the Moon, when the Sun becomes a red giant↗ in approximately seven or eight billion years.

Geography

Main articles: Geology of Venus↗, Geodynamics of Venus↗, Mapping of Venus↗, and Surface features of Venus↗

The Venusian surface was a subject of speculation until some of its secrets were revealed by probes in the 20th century. Venera↗ landers in 1975 and 1982 returned images of a surface covered in sediment and relatively angular rocks. The surface was mapped in detail by Magellan↗ in 1990–91. There is evidence of extensive volcanism, and variations in the atmospheric sulphur dioxide↗ may indicate that there are active volcanoes.

About 80% of the Venusian surface is covered by smooth, volcanic plains, consisting of 70% plains with wrinkle ridges and 10% smooth or lobate plains. Two highland "continents"↗ make up the rest of its surface area, one lying in the planet's northern hemisphere and the other just south of the equator. The northern continent is called Ishtar Terra↗ after Ishtar↗, the Babylon↗ian goddess of love, and is about the size of Australia. The Maxwell Montes↗ mountain range lies on Ishtar Terra. The southern continent is called Aphrodite Terra↗, after the Greek mythological↗ goddess of love, and is the larger of the two highland regions at roughly the size of South America. A network of fractures and faults covers much of this area.

There is recent evidence of lava↗ flow on Venus (2024), such as flows on Sif Mons↗, a shield volcano, and on Niobe Planitia↗, a flat plain. There are visible caldera↗s. The planet has few impact crater↗s, demonstrating that the surface is relatively young, at 300–600million years old. Venus has some unique surface features in addition to the impact craters, mountains, and valleys commonly found on rocky planets. Among these are flat-topped volcanic features called "farra↗", which look somewhat like pancakes and range in size from 20 to 50 km across, and from 100 to 1000 m high; radial, star-like fracture systems called "novae"; features with both radial and concentric fractures resembling spider webs, known as "arachnoids↗"; and "coronae", circular rings of fractures sometimes surrounded by a depression. These features are volcanic in origin.

Most Venusian surface features↗ are named after historical and mythological women. Exceptions are Maxwell Montes, named after James Clerk Maxwell↗, and highland regions Alpha Regio↗, Beta Regio↗, and Ovda Regio↗. The last three features were named before the current system was adopted by the International Astronomical Union↗, the body which oversees planetary nomenclature↗.

The longitude of physical features on Venus is expressed relative to its prime meridian↗. The original prime meridian passed through the radar-bright spot at the centre of the oval feature Eve, located south of Alpha Regio. After the Venera missions were completed, the prime meridian was redefined to pass through the central peak in the crater Ariadne↗ on Sedna Planitia↗.

The stratigraphically oldest tessera terrains↗ have consistently lower thermal emissivity than the surrounding basaltic plains measured by Venus Express↗ and Magellan↗, indicating a different, possibly a more felsic↗, mineral assemblage. The mechanism to generate a large amount of felsic crust usually requires the presence of a water ocean and plate tectonics↗, implying that habitable condition existed on early Venus, with large bodies of water at some point. However, the nature of tessera terrains is far from certain.

Studies reported in 2023 suggested for the first time that Venus may have had plate tectonics↗ during ancient times and, as a result, may have had a more habitable environment↗, possibly one capable of sustaining life↗. Venus has gained interest as a case for research into the development of Earth-like planets↗ and their habitability↗.

Volcanism

Main article: Volcanism on Venus↗

Much of the Venusian surface appears to have been shaped by volcanic activity. Venus has several times as many volcanoes as Earth, and it has 167 large volcanoes that are over 100 km across. The only volcanic complex of this size on Earth is the Big Island↗ of Hawaii. p. 154 More than 85,000 volcanoes on Venus have been identified and mapped. This is not because Venus is more volcanically active than Earth, but because its crust is older and is not subject to the erosion↗ processes active on Earth. Earth's oceanic crust↗ is continually recycled by subduction↗ at the boundaries of tectonic plates, and has an average age of about 100 million years, whereas the Venusian surface is estimated to be 300–600million years old.

Several lines of evidence point to ongoing volcanic↗ activity on Venus. Sulfur dioxide concentrations in the upper atmosphere dropped by a factor of 10 between 1978 and 1986, jumped in 2006, and again declined 10-fold. This may mean that levels were boosted several times by large volcanic eruptions. It has been suggested that Venusian lightning (discussed below) could originate from volcanic activity (i.e. volcanic lightning↗). In January 2020, astronomers reported evidence suggesting that Venus is currently volcanically active, specifically the detection of olivine↗, a volcanic product that would weather quickly on the planet's surface.

This massive volcanic activity is fuelled by a hot interior, which models say could be explained by energetic collisions when the planet was young, as well as radioactive decay↗ as in the case of the earth. Impacts would have had significantly higher velocity than on Earth, both because Venus moves faster due to its closer proximity to the Sun and because high-eccentricity objects colliding with the planet would have high speeds.

In 2008 and 2009, the first direct evidence for ongoing volcanism was observed by Venus Express, in the form of four transient localized infrared hot spots within the rift zone Ganis Chasma↗, near the shield volcano Maat Mons↗. Three of the spots were observed in more than one successive orbit. These spots are thought to represent lava freshly released by volcanic eruptions. The actual temperatures are not known, because the size of the hot spots could not be measured, but are likely to have been in the 800 - range, relative to a normal temperature of 740 K. In 2023, scientists reexamined topographical images of the Maat Mons region taken by the Magellan↗ orbiter. Using computer simulations, they determined that the topography had changed during an 8-month interval, and concluded that active volcanism was the cause.

Craters

There are almost a thousand impact craters on Venus, evenly distributed across its surface. On other cratered bodies, such as Earth and the Moon, craters show a range of states of degradation. On the Moon, degradation is caused by subsequent impacts, whereas on Earth it is caused by wind and rain erosion. On Venus, about 85% of the craters are in pristine condition. The number of craters, together with their well-preserved condition, indicates the planet underwent a global resurfacing event 300–600million years ago, followed by a decay in volcanism. Whereas Earth's crust is in continuous motion, Venus is thought to be unable to sustain such a process. Without plate tectonics to dissipate heat from its mantle, Venus instead undergoes a cyclical process in which mantle temperatures rise until they reach a critical level that weakens the crust. Then, over a period of about 100million years, subduction occurs on an enormous scale, completely recycling the crust.

Venusian craters range from 3 to 280 km in diameter. No craters are smaller than 3km, because of the effects of the dense atmosphere on incoming objects. Objects with less than a certain kinetic energy↗ are slowed so much by the atmosphere that they do not create an impact crater. Incoming projectiles less than 50 m in diameter will fragment and burn up in the atmosphere before reaching the ground.

Internal structure

Without data from reflection seismology↗ or knowledge of its moment of inertia↗, little direct information has been available about the internal structure and geochemistry↗ of Venus. The similarity in size and density between Venus and Earth suggests that they share a similar internal structure: a core↗, mantle↗, and crust↗. Like that of Earth, the Venusian core is most likely at least partially liquid because the two planets have been cooling at about the same rate, although a completely solid core cannot be ruled out. The slightly smaller size of Venus means pressures are 24% lower in its deep interior than Earth's. The predicted values for the moment of inertia based on planetary models suggest a core radius of 2,900–3,450 km. There is now an estimate of 3,500 km from the moment of inertia↗ based on the rate of axial precession↗, measured between 2006 and 2020.

The crust of Venus is estimated to be 40 kilometers thick on average and at most 65 kilometers thick.

The principal difference between the two planets is the lack of evidence for plate tectonics on Venus, possibly because its crust is too strong to subduct↗ without water to make it less viscous↗. This results in reduced heat loss from the planet, preventing it from cooling and providing a likely explanation for its lack of an internally generated magnetic field↗. Instead, Venus may lose its internal heat in periodic major resurfacing events.

Magnetic field and core

In 1967, Venera 4↗ found Venus's magnetic field↗ to be much weaker than that of Earth. This magnetic field is induced by an interaction between the ionosphere↗ and the solar wind↗, rather than by an internal dynamo↗ as in the Earth's core↗. Venus's small induced magnetosphere↗ provides negligible protection to the atmosphere against solar↗ and cosmic radiation↗.

The lack of an intrinsic magnetic field on Venus was surprising, given that it is similar to Earth in size and was expected to contain a dynamo at its core. A dynamo requires three things: a conducting↗ liquid, rotation, and convection↗. The core is thought to be electrically conductive and, although its rotation is often thought to be too slow, simulations show it is adequate to produce a dynamo. This implies that the dynamo is missing because of a lack of convection in Venus's core. On Earth, convection occurs in the liquid outer layer of the core because the bottom of the liquid layer is much higher in temperature than the top. On Venus, a global resurfacing event may have shut down plate tectonics and led to a reduced heat flux↗ through the crust. This insulating↗ effect would cause the mantle temperature to increase, thereby reducing the heat flux out of the core. As a result, no internal geodynamo is available to drive a magnetic field. Instead, the heat from the core is reheating the crust.

One possibility is that Venus has no solid inner core, or that its core is not cooling, so that the entire liquid part of the core is at approximately the same temperature. Another possibility is that its core has already been completely solidified. The state of the core is highly dependent on the concentration of sulphur↗, which is unknown at present.

Another possibility is that the absence of a large impact on Venus (contra the Earth's "Moon-forming" impact) left the core of Venus stratified from the core's incremental formation, and without the forces to initiate/sustain convection, and thus a "geodynamo".

The weak magnetosphere around Venus means that the solar wind interacts directly with its outer atmosphere. Here, ions of hydrogen and oxygen are being created by the dissociation↗ of water molecules due to ultraviolet↗ radiation. The solar wind then supplies energy that gives some of these ions sufficient speed to escape Venus's gravity field. This erosion process results in a steady loss of low-mass hydrogen, helium, and oxygen ions, whereas higher-mass molecules, such as carbon dioxide, are more likely to be retained. Atmospheric erosion by the solar wind could have led to the loss of most of Venus's water during the first billion years after it formed. However, the planet may have retained a dynamo for its first 2–3 billion years, so the water loss may have occurred more recently. The erosion has increased the ratio of higher-mass deuterium↗ to lower-mass hydrogen in the atmosphere 100 times compared to the rest of the solar system.

Atmosphere and climate

Main article: Atmosphere of Venus↗

Further information: Extraterrestrial sky#Venus↗

Venus has a dense atmosphere↗ composed of 96.5% carbon dioxide↗, 3.5% nitrogen—both exist as supercritical fluid↗s at the planet's surface with a density 6.5% that of water—and traces of other gases including sulphur dioxide↗. The mass of its atmosphere is 92 times that of Earth's, whereas the pressure at its surface is about 93 times that at Earth's—a pressure equivalent to that at a depth of nearly 1 km under Earth's ocean surfaces. The density at the surface is 65 kg/m3, 6.5% that of water or 50 times as dense as Earth's atmosphere at 20 °C at sea level. The CO2-rich atmosphere generates the strongest greenhouse effect↗ in the Solar System, creating surface temperatures of at least 462 °C. This makes the Venusian surface hotter than Mercury↗'s, even though Venus is nearly twice Mercury's distance from the Sun and thus receives only around a quarter of Mercury's solar irradiance↗, of 2,600 W/m2 (double that of Earth). Because of its runaway greenhouse effect↗, Venus has been identified by scientists such as Carl Sagan↗ as a warning and research object linked to climate change↗ on Earth. Therefore, Venus has been called a greenhouse planet, a planet under a greenhouse inferno.

Venus's atmosphere is rich in primordial noble gas↗es compared to that of Earth. This enrichment indicates an early divergence from Earth in evolution. An unusually large comet impact or accretion of a more massive primary atmosphere↗ from the solar nebula have been proposed to explain the enrichment. However, the atmosphere is poor in radiogenic argon-40↗, a proxy for mantle degassing, suggesting an early shutdown of major magmatism.

Studies have suggested that billions of years ago, the atmosphere of Venus may have been much more like the one surrounding the early Earth, and there may have been substantial quantities of liquid water on the surface. After a period of 600 million to several billion years, the rising luminosity of the Sun and possibly large volcanic resurfacing↗ caused the evaporation of the original water. A runaway greenhouse effect was created once a critical level of greenhouse gases (including water) was reached in the atmosphere.

Thermal inertia↗ and the transfer of heat by winds in the lower atmosphere mean that the surface temperature does not vary significantly between the hemispheres facing and not facing the Sun, despite Venus's slow rotation. Winds at the surface are slow, moving at a few kilometres per hour, but because of the high density of the atmosphere at the surface, they exert a significant amount of force against obstructions, and transport dust and small stones across the surface. This alone would make it difficult for a human to walk through, even without the heat, pressure, and lack of oxygen.

Above the dense CO2 layer are thick clouds 45 to 70 km above the surface, consisting mainly of sulphuric acid↗, which is formed by a reaction catalyzed by UV radiation from sulphur dioxide molecules and then water, resulting in sulphuric acid hydrate. Additionally, the clouds contain approximately 1% ferric chloride↗. Other possible constituents of the cloud particles are ferric sulfate↗, aluminium chloride↗ and phosphoric anhydride↗. Clouds at different levels have different compositions and particle size distributions. These clouds cover the whole planet and prevent visual observation of the surface. The dense atmosphere and highly reflective clouds gives it a high albedo↗ of 0.68, meaning it reflects nearly 70% of the incident sunlight. The permanent cloud cover means that although Venus is closer than Earth to the Sun, it receives less sunlight on the ground, with only 10% of the received sunlight reaching the surface, resulting in average daytime levels of illumination at the surface of 14,000 lux↗, comparable to that on Earth "in the daytime with overcast clouds".

Venus's atmosphere rotates much faster than its solid body, a phenomenon known as atmospheric super-rotation↗. This results in strong 300 km/h winds at the cloud tops, which complete a full rotation around the planet in about 4 days, corresponding to 60 times the speed of the planet's rotation, whereas Earth's strongest winds reach only 10–20% of its rotational speed.

Although Venus looks featureless in visible light, there are bands or streaks in the UV, whose origin has not been pinned down. The absorption of UV may be due to a compound of oxygen and sulfur, OSSO, which has a double bond between the sulfur atoms and exists in "cis" and "trans" forms, or due to polysulfur compounds from S2 to S8.

+ Venus temperature p. 1707
Location || Surface
Deep depressions | ~750 K
Average | ~740 K
atop Maxwell Montes | ~650 K

The surface of Venus is effectively isothermal↗; it retains a constant temperature not only between the two hemispheres but between the equator and the poles. Venus's minute axial tilt↗—less than 3°, compared to 23° on Earth—also minimizes seasonal temperature variation. Altitude is one of the few factors that affect Venusian temperatures; in particular, the coolest points occur at the highest-altitude points, such as the mountain peaks of the Maxwell Montes↗ range. In 1995, the Magellan spacecraft↗ imaged a highly reflective substance at the tops of the highest mountain peaks, a "Venus snow↗" that bore a strong resemblance to terrestrial snow. This substance likely formed by a similar process to snow, albeit at a far higher temperature. Too volatile to condense on the surface, it rose in gaseous form to higher elevations, where it is cooler and could precipitate. The identity of this substance is not known with certainty, but speculation has ranged from elemental tellurium↗ to lead sulfide (galena↗).

Although Venus has no seasons, in 2019 astronomers identified a cyclical variation in sunlight absorption by the atmosphere, possibly caused by opaque, absorbing particles suspended in the upper clouds. The variation causes observed changes in the speed of Venus's zonal winds and appears to rise and fall in time with the Sun's 11-year sunspot cycle↗.

The existence of lightning in the atmosphere of Venus has been controversial since the first suspected bursts were detected by the Soviet Venera probes↗. In 2006–07, Venus Express↗ clearly detected whistler mode waves↗, the signatures of lightning. Their intermittent↗ appearance indicates a pattern associated with weather activity. According to these measurements, the lightning rate is at least half that on Earth, however other instruments have not detected lightning at all. The origin of any lightning remains unclear, but could originate from clouds or Venusian volcanoes↗.

In 2007, Venus Express discovered that a huge double atmospheric polar vortex↗ exists at the south pole. Venus Express discovered, in 2011, that an ozone↗ layer exists high in the atmosphere of Venus. In 2013 ESA↗ scientists reported that the ionosphere↗ of Venus streams outwards in a manner similar to "the ion tail seen streaming from a comet↗ under similar conditions."

In December 2015, and to a lesser extent in April and May 2016, researchers working on Japan's Akatsuki mission observed bow-shaped objects in the atmosphere of Venus. This was considered direct evidence of the existence of perhaps the largest stationary gravity wave↗s in the solar system.

Colour and sound of the atmosphere at the surface have been recorded, with the sky↗ having an orange-yellow colour, while at higher altitudes being white.

Orbit and rotation

Main article: Orbit of Venus↗

Venus orbits the Sun at an average distance of about 0.72 AU, and completes an orbit every 224.7 days. It completes 13 orbits in 7.998 years, so its position in our sky almost repeats every eight years. Although all planetary orbit↗s are elliptical↗, Venus's orbit is currently the closest to circular, with an eccentricity↗ of less than 0.01. Simulations of the early solar system orbital dynamics have shown that the eccentricity of the Venus orbit may have been substantially larger in the past, reaching values as high as 0.31 and possibly impacting early climate evolution.

Venus has retrograde rotation↗, meaning that unlike most planets, including Earth, it rotates clockwise around its own axis, opposite to its anticlockwise↗ rotation around the Sun. Therefore, Venusian sidereal day↗, 243 Earth days, lasts longer than a Venusian year, 224.7 Earth days. If Venus were tidally locked↗ to the Sun, it would always have the same face pointed to the Sun and its sidereal day would be 224.7 days. However, Venus's atmosphere is massive and it is close to the Sun, so differential heating of the atmosphere gives Venus a small retrograde rotation. The day length also fluctuates by up to 20 minutes for the same reason. Venus's rotation period measured with Magellan spacecraft data over a 500-day period is smaller than the rotation period measured during the 16-year period between the Magellan spacecraft and Venus Express visits, with a difference of about 6.5minutes. Because of the retrograde rotation, the length of a solar day↗ on Venus is significantly shorter than the sidereal day, at 116.75 Earth days. One Venusian year is about 1.92Venusian solar days. To an observer on the surface of Venus, the Sun would rise in the west↗ and set in the east, although Venus's opaque clouds prevent observing the Sun from the planet's surface.

Venus may have formed from the solar nebula↗ with a different rotation period and obliquity, reaching its current state because of chaotic spin changes caused by planetary perturbations and tidal↗ effects on its dense atmosphere, a change that would have occurred over the course of billions of years. The rotation period of Venus may represent an equilibrium state between tidal locking to the Sun's gravitation, which tends to slow rotation, and an atmospheric tide created by solar heating of the thick Venusian atmosphere. The 584-day average interval between successive close approaches to Earth is almost exactly equal to 5Venusian solar days (5.001444 to be precise), but the hypothesis of a spin-orbit resonance with Earth has been discounted.

Venus has no natural satellites. It has several trojan asteroid↗s: the quasi-satellite↗ 524522 Zoozve and two other temporary trojans, and 2012 XE133. In the 17th century, Giovanni Cassini↗ reported a moon orbiting Venus, which was named Neith↗ and numerous sightings were reported over the following 200 years, but most were determined to be stars in the vicinity. Alex Alemi's and David Stevenson↗'s 2006 study of models of the early Solar System at the California Institute of Technology↗ shows Venus likely had at least one moon created by a huge impact event↗ billions of years ago. About 10millionyears later, according to the study, another impact reversed the planet's spin direction and the resulting tidal deceleration↗ caused the Venusian moon gradually to spiral inward until it collided with Venus. If later impacts created moons, these were removed in the same way. An alternative explanation for the lack of satellites is the effect of strong solar tides, which can destabilize large satellites orbiting the inner terrestrial planets.

The orbital space of Venus has a dust ring-cloud↗, with a suspected origin either from Venus–trailing asteroids, interplanetary dust migrating in waves, or the remains of the Solar System's original circumstellar disc↗ that formed the planetary system↗.

Orbit in respect to Earth

Earth and Venus have a near orbital resonance↗ of 13:8 (Earth orbits eight times for every 13 orbits of Venus). Therefore, they approach each other and reach inferior conjunction↗ in synodic period↗s of 584 days, on average. The path that Venus makes in relation to Earth viewed geocentrically draws a pentagram↗ over five synodic periods, shifting every period by 144°. This pentagram of Venus is sometimes referred to as the petals of Venus due to the path's visual similarity to a flower.

When Venus lies between Earth and the Sun in inferior↗ conjunction, it makes the closest approach to Earth of any planet, at an average distance of 41 e6km. Because of the decreasing eccentricity of Earth's orbit↗, the minimum distances will become greater over tens of thousands of years. From the year1 to 5383, there are 526 approaches less than 40 e6km; then, there are none for about 60,158 years.

While Venus approaches Earth the closest, Mercury is more often the closest to Earth of all planets and to any other planet. Venus has been used as a waypoint for gravity assist↗ manoeuvres, which has been identified as a faster and economic way to travel to Mercury, the Sun, asteroids, Mars, Jupiter and beyond.

Tidally Venus exerts the third strongest tidal force↗ on Earth, after the Moon and the Sun, though significantly less.

Observability

To the naked eye↗, Venus appears as a white point of light with a maximum apparent magnitude↗ of −4.92 brighter than any other planet or star apart from the Sun, even when faintest during its transit↗ with an apparent magnitude of −2.98. The planet's mean apparent magnitude is −4.14 with a standard deviation of 0.31. The brightest magnitude occurs during the crescent phase about one month before or after an inferior conjunction. Venus fades to about magnitude −3 when it is backlit by the Sun, although the exact value depends on the phase angle↗. The planet is bright enough to be seen in broad daylight, but is more easily visible when the Sun is low on the horizon or setting. As an inferior planet↗, it always lies within about 47° of the Sun.

Venus "overtakes" Earth every 584 days as it orbits the Sun. As it does so, it changes from the "Evening Star", visible after sunset, to the "Morning Star", visible before sunrise. Although Mercury, the other inferior planet, reaches a maximum elongation of only 28° and is often difficult to discern in twilight, Venus is hard to miss when it is at its brightest. Its greater maximum elongation means it is visible in dark skies long after sunset. As the brightest point-like object in the sky, Venus is a commonly misreported "unidentified flying object↗".

Because Venus comes close to the earth at inferior conjunction↗ and has an orbit inclined to the plane of the earth's orbit, it can appear more than 8° north or south of the ecliptic↗, more than any other planet or the moon. Every eight years around March it appears this far north of the ecliptic, in Pisces↗ (such as in mid-March 2025), and every eight years it appears this far south of the ecliptic in August or September in Virgo↗ (as in late August 2023). Venus can thus be north of the sun and appear as a morning star and an evening star on the same day, in the northern hemisphere. The timing of these north or south excursions becomes slowly earlier in the year, and over thirty cycles (240 years) the cycle is gradually replaced by another cycle offset by three years, so the situation returns close to the original situation after 243 orbits of Earth, 395 of Venus.

Lunar occultations of Venus↗, in which the moon blocks the view of Venus for observers in certain parts of the earth, occur on average about twice a year, sometimes several times in a year (though rarely).

Phases

Main article: Phases of Venus↗

As it orbits the Sun, Venus displays phases↗ like those of the Moon↗ in a telescopic↗ view. The planet appears as a small and "full" disc when it is on the opposite side of the Sun (at superior conjunction↗). Venus shows a larger disc and "quarter phase" at its maximum elongation↗s from the Sun, and appears at its brightest in the night sky. The planet presents a much larger thin "crescent" in telescopic views as it passes along the near side between Earth and the Sun. Venus displays its largest size and "new phase" when it is between Earth and the Sun (at inferior conjunction). Its atmosphere is visible through telescopes by the halo of sunlight refracted around it. The phases are clearly visible in a 4" telescope. Although naked eye visibility of Venus's phases is disputed, records exist of observations of its crescent.

Daylight apparitions

When Venus is sufficiently bright with enough angular distance from the sun, it is easily observed in a clear daytime sky with the naked eye, though most people do not know to look for it. Astronomer Edmund Halley↗ calculated its maximum naked eye brightness in 1716, when many Londoners were alarmed by its appearance in the daytime. French emperor Napoleon Bonaparte↗ once witnessed a daytime apparition of the planet while at a reception in Luxembourg↗. Another historical daytime observation of the planet took place during the inauguration of the American president Abraham Lincoln↗ in Washington, D.C., on 4March 1865.

Transits

Main article: Transit of Venus↗

A transit↗ of Venus is the appearance of Venus in front of the Sun, during inferior conjunction↗. Since the orbit of Venus is slightly inclined relative to Earth's orbit, most inferior conjunctions with Earth, which occur every synodic period↗ of 1.6 years, do not produce a transit of Venus. Consequently, Venus transits only occur when an inferior conjunction takes place during some days of June or December, when the orbits of Venus and Earth cross a straight line with the Sun. This results in Venus transiting above Earth in a sequence currently of 8 years, 105.5 years, 8 years and 121.5 years, forming cycles of 243 years.

Historically, transits of Venus were important, because they allowed astronomers to determine the size of the astronomical unit↗, and hence the size of the Solar System as shown by Jeremiah Horrocks↗ in 1639 with the first known observation↗ of a Venus transit (after history's first observed planetary transit in 1631, of Mercury↗).

Only seven Venus transits have been observed so far, since their occurrences were calculated in 1621 by Johannes Kepler↗. Captain Cook↗ sailed to Tahiti↗ in 1768 to record the third observed transit of Venus, which subsequently resulted in the exploration of the east coast of Australia.

The latest pair was 8 June 2004↗ and 5–6 June 2012↗. The transit could be watched live from many online outlets or observed locally with the right equipment and conditions. The preceding pair of transits occurred in December 1874↗ and December 1882↗.

The next transit will occur in December 2117 and December 2125.

Ashen light

A long-standing mystery of Venus observations is the so-called ashen light↗—an apparent weak illumination of its dark side, seen when the planet is in the crescent phase. The first claimed observation of ashen light was made in 1643, but the existence of the illumination has never been reliably confirmed. Observers have speculated it may result from electrical activity in the Venusian atmosphere, but it could be illusory, resulting from the physiological effect of observing a bright, crescent-shaped object. The ashen light has often been sighted when Venus is in the evening sky, when the evening terminator of the planet is towards Earth.

Observation and exploration history

Main article: Observations and explorations of Venus↗

Early observation

Venus is in Earth's sky bright enough to be visible without aid↗, making it one of the classical planets↗ that human cultures have known and identified throughout history, particularly for being the third brightest object in Earth's sky after the Sun and the Moon. Because the movements of Venus appear to be discontinuous (it disappears due to its proximity to the sun, for many days at a time, and then reappears on the other horizon), some cultures did not recognize Venus as a single entity; instead, they assumed it to be two separate stars on each horizon: the morning and evening star. Nonetheless, a cylinder seal↗ from the Jemdet Nasr period↗ and the Venus tablet of Ammisaduqa↗ from the First Babylonian dynasty↗ indicate that the ancient Sumerians already knew that the morning and evening stars were the same celestial object.

In the Old Babylonia↗n period, the planet Venus was known as Ninsi'anna, and later as Dilbat. The name "Ninsi'anna" translates to "divine lady, illumination of heaven", which refers to Venus as the brightest visible "star". Earlier spellings of the name were written with the cuneiform↗ sign si4 (= SU, meaning "to be red"), and the original meaning may have been "divine lady of the redness of heaven", in reference to the colour of the morning and evening sky.

The Chinese historically referred to the morning Venus as "the Great White" (Tàibái 太白) or "the Opener (Starter) of Brightness" (Qǐmíng 啟明), and the evening Venus as "the Excellent West One" (Chánggēng 長庚).

The ancient Greeks initially believed Venus to be two separate stars: Phosphorus↗, the morning star, and Hesperus↗, the evening star. Pliny the Elder↗ credited the realization that they were a single object to Pythagoras↗ in the sixth century BC, while Diogenes Laërtius↗ argued that Parmenides↗ (early fifth century) was probably responsible for this discovery. Though they recognized Venus as a single object, the ancient Romans continued to designate the morning aspect of Venus as Lucifer↗, literally "Light-Bringer", and the evening aspect as Vesper↗, both of which are literal translations of their traditional Greek names.

In the second century, in his astronomical treatise Almagest↗, Ptolemy↗ theorized that both Mercury and Venus were located between the Sun and the Earth. The 11th-century Persian↗ astronomer Avicenna↗ claimed to have observed a transit of Venus↗ (although there is some doubt about it), which later astronomers took as confirmation of Ptolemy's theory. In the 12th century, the Andalusian↗ astronomer Ibn Bajjah↗ observed "two planets as black spots on the face of the Sun"; these were thought to be the transits of Venus and Mercury by 13th-century Maragha↗ astronomer Qotb al-Din Shirazi↗, though this cannot be true as there were no Venus transits in Ibn Bajjah's lifetime. Several claims of transit observations made by mediaeval Islamic astronomers have been shown to be sunspots.

Venus and early modern astronomy

When the planet was first observed with a telescope in December 1610, by the Italian physicist Galileo Galilei↗, he found it showed phases↗ like the Moon, varying from crescent to gibbous to full and vice versa. When Venus is furthest from the Sun in the sky, it shows a half-lit phase↗, and when it is closest to the Sun in the sky, it shows as a crescent or full phase. This could be possible only if Venus orbited the Sun, reported by Galileo in his 1613 Letters on Sunspots↗, becoming one of the first observations to clearly contradict the Ptolemaic geocentric model↗ that the Solar System was concentric and centred on Earth.

The 1631 transit of Venus↗, while not recorded, was the first one successfully predicted, by Johannes Kepler↗ and his calculations, which he published in 1629. The following 1639 transit of Venus↗ was accurately predicted by Jeremiah Horrocks↗ and observed by him and his friend, William Crabtree↗, at each of their respective homes, on 4December 1639 (24 November under the Julian calendar↗ in use at that time).

The atmosphere of Venus↗ was discovered in 1761 by Russian polymath Mikhail Lomonosov↗. Venus's atmosphere was observed in 1790 by German astronomer Johann Schröter↗. Schröter found when the planet was a thin crescent, the cusps extended through more than 180°. He correctly surmised this was due to scattering↗ of sunlight in a dense atmosphere. Later, American astronomer Chester Smith Lyman↗ observed a complete ring around the dark side of the planet when it was at inferior conjunction↗, providing further evidence for an atmosphere. The atmosphere complicated efforts to determine a rotation period for the planet, and observers such as Italian-born astronomer Giovanni Cassini↗ and Schröter incorrectly estimated periods of about 24 hours from the motions of markings on the planet's apparent surface.

Early 20th century advances

Little more was discovered about Venus until the 20th century. Its almost featureless disc gave no hint what its surface might be like, and it was only with the development of spectroscopic↗ and ultraviolet↗ observations that more of its secrets were revealed.

The first ultraviolet observations were carried out in the 1920s, when Frank E. Ross↗ found that ultraviolet photographs↗ revealed considerable detail that was absent in visible and infrared↗ radiation. He suggested this was due to a dense, yellow lower atmosphere with high cirrus cloud↗s above it.

It had been noted that Venus had no discernible oblateness↗ in its disk, suggesting a slow rotation, and some astronomers concluded based on this that it was tidally locked↗ like Mercury was believed to be at the time; but other researchers had detected a significant quantity of heat coming from the planet's nightside, suggesting a quick rotation (a high surface temperature was not suspected at the time), confusing the issue. Later work in the 1950s showed the rotation was retrograde.

First missions to Venus

Further information: List of missions to Venus↗

The first interplanetary spaceflight↗ attempt was in 1961 when the robotic space probe↗ Venera 1↗ of the Soviet Venera↗ programme flew to Venus. It lost contact en route.

The first successful interplanetary mission, also to Venus, was Mariner 2↗ of the United States' Mariner program↗me, passing on 14 December 1962 at 34833 km above the surface of Venus and gathering data on the planet's atmosphere.

Additionally radar observations↗ of Venus were first carried out in the 1960s, and provided the first measurements of the rotation period, which were close to the actual value.

Venera 3↗, launched in 1966, became humanity's first probe and lander to reach and impact another celestial body other than the Moon, but could not return data as it crashed into the surface of Venus. In 1967, Venera 4↗ was launched and successfully deployed science experiments in the Venusian atmosphere before impacting. Venera 4 showed the surface temperature was hotter than Mariner 2 had calculated, at almost 500 °C, determined that the atmosphere was 95% carbon dioxide (), and discovered that Venus's atmosphere was considerably denser than Venera 4's designers had anticipated.

In an early example of space cooperation the data of Venera 4 was joined with the 1967 Mariner 5↗ data, analysed by a combined Soviet–American science team in a series of colloquia over the following year.

On 15 December 1970, Venera 7↗ became the first spacecraft to soft land on another planet↗ and the first to transmit data from there back to Earth.

In 1974, Mariner 10↗ swung by Venus to bend its path towards Mercury and took ultraviolet photographs of the clouds, revealing the extraordinarily high wind speeds in the Venusian atmosphere. This was the first interplanetary gravity assist↗ ever used, a technique which would be used by later probes.

Radar observations in the 1970s revealed details of the Venusian surface for the first time. Pulses of radio waves were beamed at the planet using the 300 m radio telescope at Arecibo Observatory↗, and the echoes revealed two highly reflective regions, designated the Alpha↗ and Beta↗ regions. The observations revealed a bright region attributed to mountains, which was called Maxwell Montes↗. These three features are now the only ones on Venus that do not have female names.

In 1975, the Soviet Venera 9↗ and 10↗ landers transmitted the first images from the surface of Venus, which were in black and white. NASA obtained additional data with the Pioneer Venus project↗, consisting of two separate missions: the Pioneer Venus Multiprobe↗ and Pioneer Venus Orbiter↗, orbiting Venus between 1978 and 1992. In 1982 the first monochrome colour filters images of the surface were obtained with the Soviet Venera 13↗ and 14↗ landers. After Venera 15↗ and 16↗ operated between 1983 and 1984 in orbit, conducting detailed mapping of 25% of Venus's terrain (from the north pole to 30°N latitude), the Soviet Venera programme came to a close.

In 1985 the Soviet Vega programme↗ with its Vega 1↗ and Vega 2↗ missions carried the last entry probes and carried the first ever extraterrestrial aerobot↗s for the first time achieving atmospheric flight outside Earth by employing inflatable balloons.

Between 1990 and 1994, Magellan↗ operated in orbit until deorbiting, mapping the surface of Venus. Furthermore, probes like Galileo↗ (1990), and Cassini–Huygens↗ (1998/1999) visited Venus with flybys en route to other destinations.

Renewed exploration

In April 2006, Venus Express↗, the first dedicated Venus mission by the European Space Agency↗ (ESA), entered orbit around Venus. Venus Express provided unprecedented observation of Venus's atmosphere. ESA concluded the Venus Express mission in December 2014 deorbiting it in January 2015. The same and following year MESSENGER↗ visited Venus with flybys en route to other destinations.

In 2010, the first successful interplanetary solar sail↗ spacecraft IKAROS↗ travelled to Venus for a flyby.

Between 2015 and 2024 Japan's Akatsuki↗ probe was active in orbit around Venus and BepiColombo↗ performed flybys in 2020/2021.

Active and planned missions

Further information: List of missions to Venus#Future missions↗

As of 2025 there are no active probes at Venus, with Parker Solar Probe↗ scheduled to return repeatedly to Venus until 2030.

Several probes are under development as well as multiple proposed missions still in their early conceptual stages. The next Venus mission scheduled is the Venus Life Finder↗, expected to launch not earlier than summer 2026.

Indian ISRO is working on Venus Orbiter Mission↗, aiming to launch it in 2028. UAE mission to asteroids, MBR Explorer↗, will perform a flyby of the planet. NASA approved two missions to the planet, VERITAS↗ and DAVINCI↗, planned to be launched not earlier than 2031. ESA plans to launch EnVision↗ also in 2031.

A project by the MIT↗ with the rocket company Rocket Lab↗ aims to be the first private interplanetary space craft with a proposal to look for organics by entering the atmosphere of Venus with a probe named Venus Life Finder↗.

Objectives

Venus has been identified for future research as an important case for understanding:

the origins of the solar system and Earth, and if systems and planets like ours are common or rare in the universe.
how planetary bodies evolve from their primordial states to today's diverse objects.
the development of conditions leading to habitable environments and life.

Crewed mission concepts

Venus has been considered since the 1960s as a waypoint for crewed missions to Mars↗ through opposition↗ missions instead of direct conjunction↗ missions with Venus gravity assist↗ flybys↗, demonstrating that they should be quicker and safer missions to Mars, with better return or abort flight windows, and less or the same amount of radiation exposure from the flight as direct Mars flights.

Possible atmospheric habitation

See also: Floating cities and islands in fiction#Venus↗ and Colonization of Venus↗

While the surface conditions of Venus are extremely hostile, the atmospheric pressure, temperature, and solar and cosmic radiation 50 km above the surface are similar to those at Earth's surface ("clement conditions"). Among the many engineering challenges for any human presence in the atmosphere of Venus are the corrosive amounts of sulfuric acid↗ in the atmosphere. Aerostat↗s for crewed exploration and possibly for permanent "floating cities↗" in the Venusian atmosphere have been proposed as an alternative to the popular idea of living on planetary surface↗s such as Mars. NASA's High Altitude Venus Operational Concept↗ was a training concept to study a crewed aerostat design.

Possibility of life

Main article: Life on Venus↗

Although the surface conditions on Venus are no longer hospitable to any terrestrial-like life that might have formed before this event, there is speculation that life may exist in the upper cloud layers of Venus, 50 km above the surface, where atmospheric conditions are the most Earth-like in the Solar System, with temperatures ranging between 30 °C and 80 °C, and the pressure and radiation being about the same as at Earth's surface, but with acidic clouds and the carbon dioxide air. More specifically, between heights of 48 and 59 km temperature and radiation conditions are suitable for life. At lower elevations water would evaporate and at higher elevation UV radiation would be too strong.

Speculation on the possibility of life on Venus's surface decreased significantly after the early 1960s when it became clear that conditions were extreme compared to those on Earth. Venus's extreme temperatures and atmospheric pressure make water-based life, as currently known, unlikely.

Some scientists have speculated that thermoacidophilic extremophile↗ microorganism↗s might exist in the cooler, acidic upper layers of the Venusian atmosphere↗. Such speculations go back to 1967, when Carl Sagan↗ and Harold J. Morowitz↗ suggested in a Nature↗ article that tiny objects detected in Venus's clouds might be organisms similar to Earth's bacteria (which are of approximately the same size): :While the surface conditions of Venus make the hypothesis of life there implausible, the clouds of Venus are a different story altogether. As was pointed out some years ago, water, carbon dioxide↗ and sunlight—the prerequisites for photosynthesis↗—are plentiful in the vicinity of the clouds.

In August 2019, astronomers led by Yeon Joo Lee reported that long-term pattern of absorbance and albedo↗ changes in the atmosphere of the planet Venus caused by "unknown absorbers", which may be chemicals or even large colonies of microorganisms high up in the atmosphere of the planet, affect the climate. Their light absorbance↗ is almost identical to that of micro-organisms in Earth's clouds. Similar conclusions have been reached by other studies.

The putative detection of an absorption line↗ of phosphine↗ in Venus's atmosphere, a gas not known to be produced by any known chemical processes on the Venusian surface or atmosphere, led to speculation in September 2020 that there could be extant life currently present in the atmosphere. Later research attributed the spectroscopic signal that was interpreted as phosphine to sulphur dioxide, or found that in fact there was no absorption line.

Planetary protection

Due to the harsh surface environment of Venus, Venus has been under the planetary protection↗ category two, the second lowest. This gives it only a remote chance that spacecraft-borne interplanetary contamination↗ could compromise investigations.

However, with findings of potential biosignatures this categorization for at least some atmospheric layers has been called into question, but since these layers have not been identified as sufficiently conducive to life, adjusting the categorization has not been recommended.

In culture

Main article: Venus in culture↗

Venus is among the most prominent features in the night sky, and has been treated as particularly important in mythology↗, astrology↗ and fiction↗ across many different cultures.

Several hymns praise Inanna↗ in her role as the goddess of the planet Venus. Theology professor Jeffrey Cooley has argued that, in many myths, Inanna's movements may correspond with the movements of the planet Venus in the sky. The discontinuous movements of Venus relate to both mythology as well as Inanna's dual nature. In Inanna's Descent to the Underworld, unlike any other deity, Inanna is able to descend into the netherworld and return to the heavens. The planet Venus appears to make a similar descent, setting in the West and then rising again in the East. An introductory hymn describes Inanna leaving the heavens and heading for Kur, what could be presumed to be, the mountains, replicating the rising and setting of Inanna to the West. In Inanna and Shukaletuda↗ and Inanna's Descent into the Underworld↗ appear to parallel the motion of the planet Venus. In Inanna and Shukaletuda, Shukaletuda is described as scanning the heavens in search of Inanna, possibly searching the eastern and western horizons. In the same myth, while searching for her attacker, Inanna herself makes several movements that correspond with the movements of Venus in the sky.

Via Mesopotamia↗n influence, it is possible that the Ancient Egypt↗ians and Greeks↗ knew that the morning star and the evening star were one and the same as early as the second millennium BC—or the Late Period↗ at the latest. The Egyptians knew the morning star as Tioumoutiri and the evening star as Ouaiti. They depicted Venus at first as a phoenix↗ or heron↗ (see Bennu↗), calling it 'the crosser' or 'star with crosses', associating it with Osiris↗, and later depicting it as two-headed (with human or falcon heads), and associated it with Horus↗, son of Isis↗ (which during the even later Hellenistic period↗ was together with Hathor↗ identified with Aphrodite↗). The Greeks used the names Phōsphoros↗, meaning 'light-bringer' (whence the element phosphorus↗; alternately Ēōsphoros, meaning 'dawn-bringer'), for the morning star, and Hesperos↗, meaning 'Western one', for the evening star, both children of dawn Eos↗ and therefore grandchildren of Aphrodite. Though by the Roman era they were recognized as one celestial object, known as "the star of Venus↗", the traditional two Greek names continued to be used, though usually translated to Latin as Lucifer↗ and Vesper↗.

Classical poets such as Homer↗, Sappho↗, Ovid↗ and Virgil↗ spoke of the star and its light. Poets such as William Blake↗, Robert Frost↗, Letitia Elizabeth Landon↗, Alfred Lord Tennyson↗ and William Wordsworth↗ wrote odes to it. The composer Holst↗ included it as the second movement↗ of his The Planets↗ suite.

In India, the name for Venus in Sanskrit was Shukra Graha, meaning 'the planet Shukra'—in reference to Shukra↗, a powerful saint. As appears in Vedic astrology↗, the Sanskrit name Shukra means 'clear, pure' or 'brightness, clearness'. One of the nine Navagraha↗, it is held to affect wealth, pleasure and reproduction; it was the son of Bhrgu↗, preceptor of the Daityas, and guru of the Asuras.

The English name Venus stems originally from the ancient Roman↗s. Romans named Venus after their goddess of love↗, who in turn was based on the ancient Greek↗ love goddess Aphrodite↗, who was herself based on the similar Sumerian religion↗ goddess Inanna↗ (which is Ishtar in Akkadian religion↗), all of whom were associated with the planet. The weekday of the planet↗ and these goddesses is Friday↗, named after the Germanic goddess Frigg↗, who has been associated with the Roman goddess Venus.

In Chinese, the planet is called metal star or gold star (金星 (Jīnxīng)); of the five elements↗ of traditional Chinese philosophy, Venus was historically associated with metal↗. These traditions are shared among modern Chinese↗, Japanese↗, Korean↗ and Vietnamese↗ cultures, including a name for the planet literally meaning 'metal star' (金星) in each language.

The Maya↗ considered Venus to be the most important celestial body after the Sun and Moon. They called it Chac ek, or Noh Ek', 'the Great Star'. The cycles of Venus were important to their calendar and were described in some of their books, such as the Maya Codex of Mexico↗ and Dresden Codex↗. The flag of Chile↗ (Estrella Solitaria, 'Lone Star') depicts Venus.

Modern culture

See also: Venus in fiction↗

The impenetrable Venusian cloud cover gave science fiction writers free rein to speculate on conditions at its surface; all the more so when early observations showed that not only was it similar in size to Earth, it possessed a substantial atmosphere. Closer to the Sun than Earth, the planet was often depicted as warmer, but still habitable↗ by humans. The genre reached its peak between the 1930s and 1950s, at a time when science had revealed some aspects of Venus, but not yet the harsh reality of its surface conditions. Findings from the first missions to Venus showed reality to be quite different and brought this particular genre to an end. As scientific knowledge of Venus advanced, science fiction authors tried to keep pace, particularly by conjecturing human attempts to terraform Venus↗.

Symbols

Main article: Venus symbol↗

The symbol of a circle with a small cross beneath is the so-called Venus symbol↗, gaining its name for being used as the astronomical symbol↗ for Venus. The symbol is of ancient Greek↗ origin, and represents more generally femininity↗, adopted by biology as gender symbol↗ for female, like the Mars symbol↗ for male and sometimes the Mercury symbol↗ for hermaphrodite↗. This gendered association of Venus and Mars has been used to pair them heteronormative↗ly, describing women and men stereotypically as being so different that they can be understood as coming from different planets, an understanding popularized in 1992 by the book titled Men Are from Mars, Women Are from Venus↗.

The Venus symbol was also used in Western alchemy↗ representing the element copper↗ (like the symbol of Mercury↗ is also the symbol of the element mercury↗), and since polished copper has been used for mirrors from antiquity the symbol for Venus has sometimes been called Venus mirror, representing the mirror of the goddess, although this origin has been discredited as an unlikely origin.

Besides the Venus symbol, many other symbols have been associated with Venus, other common ones are the crescent or particularly the star↗, as with the Star of Ishtar↗.

See also

Outline of Venus↗
Physical properties of planets in the Solar System↗
Venus-like exoplanet↗
Venus zone↗

Notes

References

Further reading

Joseph G. O'Rourke, Colin F. Wilson, Madison E. Borrelli, Paul K. Byrne, Caroline Dumoulin, Richard Ghail, Anna J. P. Gülcher, and Seth A. Jacobson. "Venus, the Planet: Introduction to the Evolution of Earth's Sister Planet". Space Science Reviews. 6 February 2023, vol. 219, no. 1, pp. 10. doi:10.1007/s11214-023-00956-0
Thomas Widemann, Suzanne E. Smrekar, James B. Garvin, Anne Grete Straume-Lindner, Adriana C. Ocampo, Mitchell D. Schulte, Thomas Voirin, and Scott Hensley. "Venus Evolution Through Time: Key Science Questions, Selected Mission Concepts and Future Investigations". Space Science Reviews. October 2023, vol. 219, no. 7, pp. 56. doi:10.1007/s11214-023-00992-w

External links

Venus profile at NASA's Solar System Exploration site
Missions to Venus Archived on 10 February 2015↗ and Image catalogue Archived on 29 March 2015↗ at the National Space Science Data Center↗
Soviet Exploration of Venus and Image catalogue at Mentallandscape.com
Image catalogue from the Venera missions
Venus page at The Nine Planets↗
Transits of Venus Archived on 19 March 2012↗ at NASA.gov
Geody Venus, a search engine for surface features
Interactive 3D gravity simulation of the pentagram that the orbit of Venus traces when Earth is held fixed at the centre of the coordinate system

Cartographic resources

Map-a-Planet: Venus by the U.S. Geological Survey↗
Gazetteer of Planetary Nomenclature: Venus by the International Astronomical Union↗
Venus crater database by the Lunar and Planetary Institute↗
Map of Venus Archived on 6 November 2015↗ by Eötvös Loránd University↗
Google Venus 3D, interactive map of the planet

3.2 Mars

Name | Mars
Symbol | ♂
Image | Mars - August 30 2021 - Flickr - Kevin M. Gill.png
Mars in true color, as captured by the Hope↗ orbiter. The Tharsis Montes↗ can be seen at the center, with Olympus Mons↗ just to the left and Valles Marineris↗ at the right.
Adjectives | Martian, Arean (rare, from Ares↗), see Name of Mars↗
Epoch | J2000↗
Aphelion | 249,261,000 km
Perihelion | 206,650,000 km
Time of perihelion | 11 February 2028
Semi-major axis | 227,939,366 km
Eccentricity | 0.0934
Orbital period | 686.980 d
Synodic period | 779.94 d
Average speed | 24.07 km/s
Mean anomaly | 19.412°
Inclination |
Ascending node | 49.57854 °
Argument of perihelion | 286.5 °
Satellites | 2↗ (Phobos↗ and Deimos↗)
Mean radius | 3389.5 ± 0.2 km
Equatorial radius | 3396.2 ± 0.1 km
Polar radius | 3376.2 ± 0.1 km
Flattening | 0.00589 ± 0.00015
Surface area | 1.4437e8 km2
Volume | 1.63118 × 10^11 km3
Mass | 6.4171 × 10^23 kg
Density | 3.9335 g/cm3
Surface gravity | 3.72076 m/s2
Moment of inertia factor | 0.3644 ± 0.0005
Escape velocity | 5.027 km/s
Rotation period | 1.02749125 day
Sidereal day | 1.025957 day
Rotational velocity | 0.241 km/s
Axial tilt | 25.19 ° to its orbital plane
North pole right ascension | 317.269 °
North pole declination | 54.432 °
Albedo |
Magnitude | −2.94 to +1.86
Absolute magnitude | −1.5
Angular size | 3.5–25.1 arcsecond↗s
Single temperature | 209 K (blackbody temperature↗)
| min −110 °C
mean −60 °C
max 35 °C
Surface equivalent dose rate | 0.64 mSv/d
Surface absorbed dose rate | 0.210 mGy/d
Surface pressure | 0.636 (0.4–0.87) kPa↗
Atmosphere composition | * 95.97% carbon dioxide↗

Mars is the fourth planet↗ from the Sun. It is also known as the "Red Planet", for its orange-red↗ appearance. Mars is a desert-like rocky planet↗ with a tenuous atmosphere↗ that is primarily carbon dioxide↗ (CO2). At the average surface level the atmospheric pressure is a few thousandths of Earth's, atmospheric temperature ranges from -153 to 20 °C, and cosmic radiation↗ is high. Mars retains some water, in the ground↗ as well as thinly in the atmosphere, forming cirrus cloud↗s, fog↗, frost↗, larger polar regions of permafrost↗ and ice caps↗ (with seasonal CO2 snow), but no bodies of liquid surface water. Its surface gravity is roughly a third of Earth's or double that of the Moon. Its diameter, 6,779 km, is about half the Earth↗'s, or twice the Moon's, and its surface area is the size of all the dry land of Earth.

Fine dust↗ is prevalent across the surface and the atmosphere, being picked up and spread at the low Martian gravity even by the weak wind of the tenuous atmosphere. The terrain of Mars roughly follows a north–south divide, the Martian dichotomy↗, with the northern hemisphere mainly consisting of relatively flat, low lying plain↗s, and the southern hemisphere of cratered highland↗s. Geologically↗, the planet is fairly active with marsquake↗s trembling underneath the ground, but also hosts many enormous volcano↗es that are extinct (the tallest is Olympus Mons↗, 21.9 km tall), as well as one of the largest canyon↗s in the Solar System (Valles Marineris↗, 4,000 km long). Mars has two natural satellites↗ that are small and irregular in shape: Phobos↗ and Deimos↗. With a significant axial tilt↗ of 25 degrees, Mars experiences season↗s, like Earth (which has an axial tilt of 23.5 degrees). A Martian solar year↗ is equal to 1.88 Earth years (687 Earth days), a Martian solar day (sol↗) is equal to 24.6 hours.

Mars formed along with the other planets approximately 4.5 billion years ago. During the martian Noachian↗ period (4.5 to 3.5 billion years ago), its surface was marked by meteor impacts↗, valley formation, erosion, the possible presence of water ocean↗s and the loss of its magnetosphere↗. The Hesperian↗ period (beginning 3.5 billion years ago and ending 3.3–2.9 billion years ago) was dominated by widespread volcanic activity↗ and flooding that carved immense outflow channels↗. The Amazonian↗ period, which continues to the present, is the currently dominating and remaining influence on geological processes↗. Because of Mars's geological history, the possibility of past or present life on Mars↗ remains an area of active scientific investigation, with some possible traces needing further examination.

Being visible↗ with the naked eye in Earth's sky as a red wandering star↗, Mars has been observed throughout history↗, acquiring diverse associations in different cultures. In 1963 the first flight to Mars took place with Mars 1↗, but communication was lost en route. The first successful flyby exploration of Mars↗ was conducted in 1965 with Mariner 4↗. In 1971 Mariner 9↗ entered orbit around Mars, being the first spacecraft to orbit any body other than the Moon, Sun or Earth; following in the same year were the first uncontrolled impact (Mars 2↗) and first successful landing (Mars 3↗) on Mars. Probes have been active on Mars continuously since 1997. At times, more than ten probes have simultaneously operated↗ in orbit or on the surface, more than at any other planet beyond Earth. Mars is an often proposed target for future crewed exploration missions↗, though no such mission is currently planned.

Natural history

Main article: Geological history of Mars↗

Formation

Scientists have theorized that during the Solar System's formation↗, Mars was created as the result of a random process↗ of run-away accretion↗ of material from the protoplanetary disk↗ that orbited the Sun. Mars has many distinctive chemical features caused by its position in the Solar System. Elements with comparatively low boiling points, such as chlorine↗, phosphorus↗, and sulfur↗, are much more common on Mars than on Earth; these elements were probably pushed outward by the young Sun's energetic solar wind↗.

Late Heavy Bombardment

After the formation of the planets, the inner Solar System may have been subjected to the so-called Late Heavy Bombardment↗. About 60% of the surface of Mars shows a record of impacts from that era, whereas much of the remaining surface is probably underlain by immense impact basins caused by those events. However, more recent modeling has disputed the existence of the Late Heavy Bombardment. There is evidence of an enormous impact basin in the Northern Hemisphere of Mars, spanning 10,600 by, or roughly four times the size of the Moon's South Pole–Aitken basin↗, which would be the largest impact basin yet discovered if confirmed. It has been hypothesized that the basin was formed when Mars was struck by a Pluto↗-sized body about four billion years ago. The event, thought to be the cause of the Martian hemispheric dichotomy↗, created the smooth Borealis basin↗ that covers 40% of the planet.

A 2023 study shows evidence, based on the orbital inclination↗ of Deimos↗ (a small moon↗ of Mars), that Mars may once have had a ring system↗ 3.5 billion years to 4 billion years ago. This ring system may have been formed from a moon, 20 times more mass↗ive than Phobos↗, orbiting Mars billions of years ago; and Phobos would be a remnant of that ring.

Geological periods

The geological history of Mars can be split into many periods, but the following are the three primary periods:

Noachian↗ period: Formation of the oldest extant surfaces of Mars, 4.5 to 3.5 billion years ago. Noachian age surfaces are scarred by many large impact craters. The Tharsis↗ bulge, a volcanic upland, is thought to have formed during this period, with extensive flooding by liquid water late in the period. Named after Noachis Terra↗.
Hesperian↗ period: 3.5 to between 3.3 and 2.9 billion years ago. The Hesperian period is marked by the formation of extensive lava plains. Named after Hesperia Planum↗.
Amazonian↗ period: between 3.3 and 2.9 billion years ago to the present. Amazonian regions have few meteorite impact↗ craters but are otherwise quite varied. Olympus Mons↗ formed during this period, with lava flows elsewhere on Mars. Named after Amazonis Planitia↗.

Recent geological activity

Geological activity is still taking place on Mars. The Athabasca Valles↗ is home to sheet-like lava flows created about 200 million years ago. Water flows in the graben↗s called the Cerberus Fossae↗ occurred less than 20 million years ago, indicating equally recent volcanic intrusions. The Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter↗ has captured images of avalanches.

Physical characteristics

Main articles: Geology of Mars↗ and Composition of Mars↗

Mars is approximately half the diameter of Earth or twice that of the Moon, with a surface area only slightly less than the total area of Earth's dry land. Mars is less dense than Earth, having about 15% of Earth's volume and 11% of Earth's mass↗, resulting in about 38% of Earth's surface gravity↗. Mars is the only presently known example of a desert planet↗, a rocky planet with a surface akin to that of Earth's desert↗s. The red-orange appearance of the Martian surface is caused by iron(III) oxide↗ (nanophase↗ Fe2O3) and the iron(III) oxide-hydroxide↗ mineral goethite↗. It can look like butterscotch↗; other common surface colors include golden, brown, tan, and greenish, depending on the mineral↗s present.

Internal structure

Like Earth, Mars is differentiated↗ into a dense metallic core↗ overlaid by less dense rocky layers. The outermost layer is the crust, which is on average about 42-56 km thick, with a minimum thickness of 6 km in Isidis Planitia↗, and a maximum thickness of 117 km in the southern Tharsis plateau↗. For comparison, Earth's crust averages 27.3 ± 4.8 km in thickness. The most abundant elements in the Martian crust↗ are silicon↗, oxygen↗, iron↗, magnesium↗, aluminum↗, calcium↗, and potassium↗. Mars is confirmed to be seismically active; in 2019, it was reported that InSight↗ had detected and recorded over 450 marsquake↗s and related events.

Beneath the crust is a silicate mantle↗ responsible for many of the tectonic↗ and volcanic features↗ on the planet's surface. The upper Martian mantle is a low-velocity zone↗, where the velocity of seismic waves is lower than surrounding depth intervals. The mantle appears to be rigid down to the depth of about 250 km, giving Mars a very thick lithosphere↗ compared to Earth. Below this the mantle gradually becomes more ductile, and the seismic wave velocity starts to grow again. The Martian mantle does not appear to have a thermally insulating layer analogous to Earth's lower mantle↗; instead, below 1050 km in depth, it becomes mineralogically similar to Earth's transition zone↗. At the bottom of the mantle lies a basal liquid silicate layer↗ approximately 150–180 km thick. The Martian mantle appears to be highly heterogenous, with dense fragments up to 4 km across, likely injected deep into the planet by colossal impacts ~4.5 billion years ago; high-frequency waves from eight marsquakes slowed as they passed these localized regions, and modeling indicates the heterogeneities are compositionally distinct debris preserved because Mars lacks plate tectonics and has a sluggishly convecting interior that prevents complete homogenization.

Mars's iron and nickel↗ core is at least partially molten, and may have a solid inner core. It is around half of Mars's radius, approximately 1650–1675 km, and is enriched in light elements such as sulfur↗, oxygen, carbon↗, and hydrogen↗. compared to 5400–6230 K for Earth's solid inner core↗. Whether or not a solid inner core is present inside Mars remains a topic of active research; a 2023 study using data from the InSight↗ lander suggested the absence of a solid inner core, however a 2025 study based on the same data reported the detection of a solid inner core 613 km ± 67 km in radius.

Surface geology

Further information: Martian regolith↗

Mars is a terrestrial planet↗ with a surface that consists of minerals containing silicon↗ and oxygen, metal↗s, and other elements that typically make up rock↗. The Martian surface↗ is primarily composed of tholeiitic↗ basalt↗, although parts are more silica↗-rich than typical basalt and may be similar to andesitic↗ rocks on Earth, or silica glass. Regions of low albedo↗ suggest concentrations of plagioclase feldspar↗, with northern low albedo regions displaying higher than normal concentrations of sheet silicates and high-silicon glass. Parts of the southern highlands include detectable amounts of high-calcium pyroxene↗s. Localized concentrations of hematite↗ and olivine↗ have been found. Much of the surface is deeply covered by finely grained iron(III) oxide↗ dust.

The Phoenix↗ lander returned data showing Martian soil to be slightly alkaline and containing elements such as magnesium↗, sodium↗, potassium↗ and chlorine↗. These nutrients are found in soils on Earth, and are necessary for plant growth. Experiments performed by the lander showed that the Martian soil has a basic↗ pH↗ of 7.7, and contains 0.6% perchlorate↗ by weight, concentrations that are toxic to humans↗.

Streaks↗ are common across Mars and new ones appear frequently on steep slopes of craters, troughs, and valleys. The streaks are dark at first and get lighter with age. The streaks can start in a tiny area, then spread out for hundreds of metres. They have been seen to follow the edges of boulders and other obstacles in their path. The commonly accepted hypotheses include that they are dark underlying layers of soil revealed after avalanches of bright dust or dust devil↗s. Several other explanations have been put forward, including those that involve water or even the growth of organisms.

Environmental radiation↗ levels on the surface are on average 0.64 millisieverts↗ of radiation per day, and significantly less than the radiation of 1.84 millisieverts per day or 22 millirads↗ per day during the flight to and from Mars. For comparison the radiation levels in low Earth orbit↗, where Earth's space station↗s orbit, are around 0.5 millisieverts of radiation per day. Hellas Planitia↗ has the lowest surface radiation at about 0.342 millisieverts per day, featuring lava tube↗s southwest of Hadriacus Mons↗ with potentially levels as low as 0.064 millisieverts per day, comparable to radiation levels during flights on Earth.

Magnetic characteristics

Main article: Magnetic field of Mars↗

Although Mars has no evidence of a structured global magnetic field↗, observations show that parts of the planet's crust have been magnetized, suggesting that alternating polarity reversals of its dipole field have occurred in the past. This paleomagnetism↗ of magnetically susceptible minerals is similar to the alternating bands found on Earth's ocean floors↗. One hypothesis, published in 1999 and re-examined in October 2005 (with the help of the Mars Global Surveyor↗), is that these bands suggest plate tectonic activity↗ on Mars four billion years ago, before the planetary dynamo↗ ceased to function and the planet's magnetic field faded.

Geography and features

Main article: Geography of Mars↗

Further information: Areoid↗ See also: Category:Surface features of Mars↗

Although better remembered for mapping the Moon, Johann Heinrich von Mädler↗ and Wilhelm Beer↗ were the first areographers. They began by establishing that most of Mars's surface features were permanent and by more precisely determining the planet's rotation period. In 1840, Mädler combined ten years of observations and drew the first map of Mars.

Features on Mars are named from a variety of sources. Albedo features↗ are named for classical mythology. Craters larger than roughly 50 km are named for deceased scientists and writers and others who have contributed to the study of Mars. Smaller craters are named for towns and villages of the world with populations of less than 100,000. Large valleys are named for the word "Mars" or "star" in various languages; smaller valleys are named for rivers.

Large albedo↗ features retain many of the older names but are often updated to reflect new knowledge of the nature of the features. For example, Nix Olympica (the snows of Olympus) has become Olympus Mons↗ (Mount Olympus). The surface of Mars as seen from Earth is divided into two kinds of areas, with differing albedo. The paler plains covered with dust and sand rich in reddish iron oxides were once thought of as Martian "continents" and given names like Arabia Terra↗ (land of Arabia) or Amazonis Planitia↗ (Amazonian plain). The dark features were thought to be seas, hence their names Mare Erythraeum↗, Mare Sirenum and Aurorae Sinus↗. The largest dark feature seen from Earth is Syrtis Major Planum↗. The permanent northern polar ice cap is named Planum Boreum↗. The southern cap is called Planum Australe↗.

Mars's equator is defined by its rotation, but the location of its Prime Meridian↗ was specified, as was Earth's (at Greenwich↗), by choice of an arbitrary point; Mädler and Beer selected a line for their first maps of Mars in 1830. After the spacecraft Mariner 9↗ provided extensive imagery of Mars in 1972, a small crater (later called Airy-0↗), located in the Sinus Meridiani↗ ("Middle Bay" or "Meridian Bay"), was chosen by Merton E. Davies↗, Harold Masursky↗, and Gérard de Vaucouleurs↗ for the definition of 0.0° longitude to coincide with the original selection.

Because Mars has no oceans, and hence no "sea level↗", a zero-elevation surface had to be selected as a reference level; this is called the areoid↗ of Mars, analogous to the terrestrial geoid↗. Zero altitude was defined by the height at which there is 610.5 Pa of atmospheric pressure. This pressure corresponds to the triple point↗ of water, and it is about 0.6% of the sea level surface pressure on Earth (0.006 atm).

For mapping purposes, the United States Geological Survey↗ divides the surface of Mars into thirty cartographic quadrangles↗, each named for a classical albedo feature it contains. In April 2023, The New York Times↗ reported an updated global map of Mars based on images from the Hope spacecraft↗. A related, but much more detailed, global Mars map was released by NASA↗ on 16 April 2023.

Volcanoes

Main article: Volcanism on Mars↗

The vast upland region Tharsis↗ contains several massive volcanoes, which include the shield volcano↗ Olympus Mons↗. The edifice is over 600 km wide. Because the mountain is so large, with complex structure at its edges, giving a definite height to it is difficult. Its local relief, from the foot of the cliffs which form its northwest margin to its peak, is over 21 km, a little over twice the height of Mauna Kea↗ as measured from its base on the ocean floor. The total elevation change from the plains of Amazonis Planitia↗, over 1,000 km to the northwest, to the summit approaches 26 km, roughly three times the height of Mount Everest↗, which in comparison stands at just over 8.8 km. Consequently, Olympus Mons is either the tallest or second-tallest mountain in the Solar System↗; the only known mountain which might be taller is the Rheasilvia↗ peak on the asteroid Vesta↗, at 20-25 km.

Impact topography

The dichotomy of Martian topography↗ is striking: northern plains flattened by lava flows contrast with the southern highlands, pitted and cratered by ancient impacts. It is possible that, four billion years ago, the Northern Hemisphere of Mars was struck by an object one-tenth to two-thirds the size of Earth's Moon↗. If this is the case, the Northern Hemisphere of Mars would be the site of an impact crater↗ 10,600 by in size, or roughly the area of Europe, Asia, and Australia combined, surpassing Utopia Planitia↗ and the Moon's South Pole–Aitken basin↗ as the largest impact crater in the Solar System.

Mars is scarred by 43,000 impact craters with a diameter of 5 km or greater. The largest exposed crater is Hellas↗, which is 2,300 km wide and 7,000 m (22,966 ft) deep, and is a light albedo feature↗ clearly visible from Earth. There are other notable impact features, such as Argyre↗, which is around 1,800 km in diameter, and Isidis↗, which is around 1,500 km in diameter. Due to the smaller mass and size of Mars, the probability of an object colliding with the planet is about half that of Earth. Mars is located closer to the asteroid belt↗, so it has an increased chance of being struck by materials from that source. Mars is more likely to be struck by short-period comet↗s, i.e., those that lie within the orbit of Jupiter↗.

Martian craters can have a morphology that suggests the ground became wet after the meteor impact.

Tectonic sites

The large canyon, Valles Marineris↗ (Latin for Mariner↗ Valleys, also known as Agathodaemon in the old canal maps), has a length of 4,000 km and a depth of up to 7 km. The length of Valles Marineris is equivalent to the length of Europe and extends across one-fifth the circumference of Mars. By comparison, the Grand Canyon↗ on Earth is only 446 km long and nearly 2 km deep. Valles Marineris was formed due to the swelling of the Tharsis area, which caused the crust in the area of Valles Marineris to collapse. In 2012, it was proposed that Valles Marineris is not just a graben↗, but a plate boundary where 150 km of transverse motion↗ has occurred, making Mars a planet with possibly a two-tectonic plate↗ arrangement.

Holes and caves

Images from the Thermal Emission Imaging System↗ (THEMIS) aboard NASA's Mars Odyssey orbiter↗ have revealed seven possible cave↗ entrances on the flanks of the volcano Arsia Mons↗. The caves, named after loved ones of their discoverers, are collectively known as the "seven sisters". Cave entrances measure from 100 to 252 m wide and they are estimated to be at least 73 to 96 m deep. Because light does not reach the floor of most of the caves, they may extend much deeper than these lower estimates and widen below the surface. "Dena" is the only exception; its floor is visible and was measured to be 130 m (427 ft) deep. The interiors of these caverns may be protected from micrometeoroids, UV radiation, solar flare↗s and high energy particles that bombard the planet's surface.

Other features

Excerpt from: Geysers on Mars↗

Excerpt from: Martian dust↗

Atmosphere

Main article: Atmosphere of Mars↗

Mars lost its magnetosphere↗ 4 billion years ago, possibly because of numerous asteroid strikes, so the solar wind↗ interacts directly with the Martian ionosphere↗, lowering the atmospheric density by stripping↗ away atoms from the outer layer. Both Mars Global Surveyor↗ and Mars Express↗ have detected ionized atmospheric particles trailing off into space behind Mars, and this atmospheric loss is being studied by the MAVEN↗ orbiter. Compared to Earth, the atmosphere↗ of Mars is quite rarefied. Atmospheric pressure↗ on the surface today ranges from a low of 30 Pa on Olympus Mons↗ to over 1,155 Pa in Hellas Planitia↗, with a mean pressure at the surface level of 600 Pa. The highest atmospheric density on Mars is equal to that found 35 km above Earth's surface. The resulting mean surface pressure is only 0.6% of Earth's 101.3 kPa. The scale height↗ of the atmosphere is about 10.8 km, which is higher than Earth's 6 km, because the surface gravity of Mars↗ is only about 38% of Earth's.

The atmosphere of Mars consists of about 96% carbon dioxide↗, 1.93% argon↗ and 1.89% nitrogen↗ along with traces of oxygen↗ and water. The atmosphere is quite dusty, containing particulates about 1.5 μm↗ in diameter which give the Martian sky↗ a tawny↗ color when seen from the surface. It may take on a pink↗ hue due to iron oxide↗ particles suspended in it.

Despite repeated detections of methane on Mars↗, there is no scientific consensus as to its origin. One suggestion is that methane exists on Mars and that its concentration fluctuates seasonally. The existence of methane could be produced by non-biological process such as serpentinization↗ involving water, carbon dioxide, and the mineral olivine↗, which is known to be common on Mars, or by Martian life.

Compared to Earth, its higher concentration of atmospheric CO2 and lower surface pressure may be why sound is attenuated more on Mars, where natural sources are rare apart from the wind. Using acoustic recordings collected by the Perseverance rover, researchers concluded that the speed of sound there is approximately 240 m/s for frequencies below 240 Hz, and 250 m/s for those above.

Aurora↗s have been detected on Mars. Because Mars lacks a global magnetic field, the types and distribution of auroras there differ from those on Earth; rather than being mostly restricted to polar regions as is the case on Earth, a Martian aurora can encompass the planet. In September 2017, NASA reported radiation↗ levels on the surface of the planet Mars were temporarily doubled↗, and were associated with an aurora↗ 25 times brighter than any observed earlier, due to a massive, and unexpected, solar storm↗ in the middle of the month.

Climate

Main article: Climate of Mars↗

Mars has seasons, alternating between its northern and southern hemispheres, similar to on Earth. Additionally the orbit of Mars has, compared to Earth's, a large eccentricity↗ and approaches perihelion↗ when it is summer in its southern hemisphere and winter in its northern, and aphelion↗ when it is winter in its southern hemisphere and summer in its northern. As a result, the seasons in its southern hemisphere are more extreme and the seasons in its northern are milder than would otherwise be the case. The summer temperatures in the south can be warmer than the equivalent summer temperatures in the north by up to 30 C-change.

Martian surface temperatures vary from lows of about -110 °C to highs of up to 35 °C in equatorial summer. The wide range in temperatures is due to the thin atmosphere which cannot store much solar heat, the low atmospheric pressure (about 1% that of the atmosphere of Earth↗), and the low thermal inertia↗ of Martian soil. The planet is 1.52 times as far from the Sun as Earth, resulting in just 43% of the amount of sunlight.

Mars has the largest dust storm↗s in the Solar System, reaching speeds of over 100 mph. These can vary from a storm over a small area, to gigantic storms that cover the entire planet. They tend to occur when Mars is closest to the Sun, and have been shown to increase global temperature. Seasons also produce dry ice↗ covering polar ice caps↗.

Hydrology

Main article: Water on Mars↗

See also: Groundwater on Mars↗

While Mars contains water in larger amounts↗, most of it is dust covered water ice at the Martian polar ice caps↗. The volume of water ice in the south polar ice cap, if melted, would be enough to cover most of the surface of the planet with a depth of 11 m (36 ft).

Water in its liquid form cannot persist on the surface due to Mars's low atmospheric pressure, which is less than 1% that of Earth. Only at the lowest of elevations are the pressure and temperature high enough for liquid water to exist for short periods.

Although little water is present in the atmosphere, there is enough to produce clouds of water ice and different cases of snow↗ and frost, often mixed with snow of carbon dioxide↗ dry ice↗.

Past hydrosphere

Landforms↗ visible on Mars strongly suggest that liquid water has existed on the planet's surface. Huge linear swathes of scoured ground, known as outflow channels↗, cut across the surface in about 25 places. These are thought to be a record of erosion caused by the catastrophic release of water from subsurface aquifers, though some of these structures have been hypothesized to result from the action of glaciers or lava. One of the larger examples, Ma'adim Vallis↗, is 700 km long, much greater than the Grand Canyon, with a width of 20 km and a depth of 2 km in places. It is thought to have been carved by flowing water early in Mars's history. The youngest of these channels is thought to have formed only a few million years ago.

Elsewhere, particularly on the oldest areas of the Martian surface, finer-scale, dendritic networks of valleys↗ are spread across significant proportions of the landscape. Features of these valleys and their distribution strongly imply that they were carved by runoff↗ resulting from precipitation in early Mars history. Subsurface water flow and groundwater sapping↗ may play important subsidiary roles in some networks, but precipitation was probably the root cause of the incision in almost all cases.

Along craters and canyon walls, there are thousands of features that appear similar to terrestrial gullies↗. The gullies tend to be in the highlands of the Southern Hemisphere and face the Equator; all are poleward of 30° latitude. A number of authors have suggested that their formation process involves liquid water, probably from melting ice, although others have argued for formation mechanisms involving carbon dioxide frost or the movement of dry dust. No partially degraded gullies have formed by weathering and no superimposed impact craters have been observed, indicating that these are young features, possibly still active. Other geological features, such as deltas↗ and alluvial fan↗s preserved in craters, are further evidence for warmer, wetter conditions at an interval or intervals in earlier Mars history. Such conditions necessarily require the widespread presence of crater lakes↗ across a large proportion of the surface, for which there is independent mineralogical, sedimentological and geomorphological evidence. Further evidence that liquid water once existed on the surface of Mars comes from the detection of specific minerals such as hematite↗ and goethite↗, both of which sometimes form in the presence of water.

History of observations and findings of water evidence

Main articles: Water on Mars↗ and Chronology of discoveries of water on Mars↗

The chemical signature of water vapor on Mars was first unequivocally demonstrated in 1963 by spectroscopy using an Earth-based telescope. In 2004, Opportunity detected the mineral jarosite↗. This forms only in the presence of acidic water, showing that water once existed on Mars. The Spirit rover found concentrated deposits of silica↗ in 2007 that indicated wet conditions in the past, and in December 2011, the mineral gypsum↗, which also forms in the presence of water, was found on the surface by NASA's Mars rover Opportunity. It is estimated that the amount of water in the upper mantle of Mars, represented by hydroxyl ion↗s contained within Martian minerals, is equal to or greater than that of Earth at 50–300 parts per million of water, which is enough to cover the entire planet to a depth of 200 -.

On 18 March 2013, NASA↗ reported evidence from instruments on the Curiosity rover↗ of mineral hydration↗, likely hydrated calcium sulfate↗, in several rock samples↗ including the broken fragments of "Tintina" rock↗ and "Sutton Inlier" rock↗ as well as in veins↗ and nodules↗ in other rocks like "Knorr" rock↗ and "Wernicke" rock↗. Analysis using the rover's DAN instrument↗ provided evidence of subsurface water, amounting to as much as 4% water content, down to a depth of 60 cm, during the rover's traverse from the Bradbury Landing↗ site to the Yellowknife Bay area in the Glenelg↗ terrain. In September 2015, NASA announced that they had found strong evidence of hydrated brine↗ flows in recurring slope lineae↗, based on spectrometer readings of the darkened areas of slopes. These streaks flow downhill in Martian summer, when the temperature is above −23 °C, and freeze at lower temperatures. These observations supported earlier hypotheses, based on timing of formation and their rate of growth, that these dark streaks resulted from water flowing just below the surface. However, later work suggested that the lineae may be dry, granular flows instead, with at most a limited role for water in initiating the process. A definitive conclusion about the presence, extent, and role of liquid water on the Martian surface remains elusive.

Researchers suspect much of the low northern plains of the planet were covered with an ocean↗ hundreds of meters deep, though this theory remains controversial. In March 2015, scientists stated that such an ocean might have been the size of Earth's Arctic Ocean↗. This finding was derived from the ratio of protium↗ to deuterium↗ in the modern Martian atmosphere compared to that ratio on Earth. The amount of Martian deuterium (D/H = 9.3 ± 1.7 10−4) is five to seven times the amount on Earth (D/H = 1.56 10−4), suggesting that ancient Mars had significantly higher levels of water. Results from the Curiosity rover had previously found a high ratio of deuterium in Gale Crater↗, though not significantly high enough to suggest the former presence of an ocean. Other scientists caution that these results have not been confirmed, and point out that Martian climate models have not yet shown that the planet was warm enough in the past to support bodies of liquid water. Near the northern polar cap is the 81.4 km wide Korolev Crater↗, which the Mars Express↗ orbiter found to be filled with approximately 2,200 km3 of water ice.

In November 2016, NASA reported finding a large amount of underground ice in the Utopia Planitia↗ region. The volume of water detected has been estimated to be equivalent to the volume of water in Lake Superior↗ (which is 12,100 cubic kilometers). During observations from 2018 through 2021, the ExoMars Trace Gas Orbiter spotted indications of water, probably subsurface ice, in the Valles Marineris canyon system.

Orbital motion

Main article: Orbit of Mars↗

See also: Timekeeping on Mars↗ Mars's average distance from the Sun is roughly 143 e6mi, and its orbital period is 687 (Earth) days. The solar day (or sol↗) on Mars is only slightly longer than an Earth day: 24 hours, 39 minutes, and 35.244 seconds. A Martian year is equal to 1.8809 Earth years, or 1 year, 320 days, and 18.2 hours. The gravitational potential↗ difference and thus the delta-v needed↗ to transfer between Mars and Earth is the second lowest for Earth.

The axial tilt of Mars is 25.19° relative to its orbital plane↗, which is similar to the axial tilt of Earth↗. As a result, Mars has seasons like Earth, though on Mars they are nearly twice as long because its orbital period is that much longer. In the present day, the orientation of the north pole↗ of Mars is close to the star Deneb↗.

Mars has a relatively pronounced orbital eccentricity↗ of about 0.09; of the seven other planets in the Solar System, only Mercury↗ has a larger orbital eccentricity. It is known that in the past, Mars has had a much more circular orbit. At one point, 1.35 million Earth years ago, Mars had an eccentricity of roughly 0.002, much less than that of Earth today. Mars's cycle of eccentricity↗ is 96,000 Earth years compared to Earth's cycle of 100,000 years.

Mars has its closest approach to Earth (opposition↗) in a synodic period↗ of 779.94 days. It should not be confused with Mars conjunction↗, where the Earth and Mars are at opposite sides of the Solar System and form a straight line crossing the Sun. The average time between the successive oppositions of Mars, its synodic period↗, is 780 days; but the number of days between successive oppositions can range from 764 to 812. The distance at close approach varies between about 54 e6km and 103 e6km due to the planets' elliptical↗ orbits, which causes comparable variation in angular size↗. At their furthest Mars and Earth can be as far as 401 e6km apart. Mars comes into opposition from Earth every 2.1 years. The planets come into opposition near Mars's perihelion↗ in 2003, 2018 and 2035, with the 2020 and 2033 events being particularly close to perihelic opposition.

The mean apparent magnitude↗ of Mars is +0.71 with a standard deviation of 1.05. Because the orbit of Mars is eccentric, the magnitude at opposition↗ from the Sun can range from about −3.0 to −1.4. The minimum brightness is magnitude +1.86 when the planet is near aphelion↗ and in conjunction↗ with the Sun. At its brightest, Mars (along with Jupiter↗) is second only to Venus in apparent brightness. Mars usually appears distinctly yellow, orange, or red. When farthest away from Earth, it is more than seven times farther away than when it is closest. Mars is usually close enough for particularly good viewing once or twice at 15-year or 17-year intervals. Optical ground-based telescopes are typically limited to resolving features about 300 km across when Earth and Mars are closest because of Earth's atmosphere.

As Mars approaches opposition, it begins a period of retrograde motion↗, which means it will appear to move backwards in a looping curve with respect to the background stars. This retrograde motion lasts for about 72 days, and Mars reaches its peak apparent brightness in the middle of this interval.

Moons

Main articles: Moons of Mars↗, Phobos (moon)↗, and Deimos (moon)↗

Mars has two relatively small (compared to Earth's) natural moons, Phobos↗ (about 22 km in diameter) and Deimos↗ (about 12 km in diameter), which orbit at 9,376 km and 23,460 km around the planet. The origin of both moons is unclear, although a popular theory states that they were asteroids captured into Martian orbit.

Both satellites were discovered in 1877 by Asaph Hall↗ and were named after the characters Phobos↗ (the deity of panic and fear) and Deimos↗ (the deity of terror and dread), twins from Greek mythology↗ who accompanied their father Ares↗, god of war, into battle. Mars↗ was the Roman equivalent to Ares. In modern Greek↗, the planet retains its ancient name Ares (Aris: Άρης).

From the surface of Mars, the motions of Phobos and Deimos appear different from that of the Earth's satellite, the Moon↗. Phobos rises in the west, sets in the east, and rises again in just 11 hours. Deimos, being only just outside synchronous orbit↗ – where the orbital period would match the planet's period of rotation – rises as expected in the east, but slowly. Because the orbit of Phobos is below a synchronous altitude, tidal force↗s from Mars are gradually lowering its orbit. In about 50 million years, it could either crash into Mars's surface or break up into a ring structure around the planet.

The origin of the two satellites is not well understood. Their low albedo and carbonaceous chondrite↗ composition have been regarded as similar to asteroids, supporting a capture theory. The unstable orbit of Phobos would seem to point toward a relatively recent capture. But both have circular orbit↗s near the equator, which is unusual for captured objects, and the required capture dynamics are complex. Accretion early in the history of Mars is plausible, but would not account for a composition resembling asteroids rather than Mars itself, if that is confirmed. Mars may have yet-undiscovered moons, smaller than 50 to 100 m in diameter, and a dust ring is predicted to exist between Phobos and Deimos.

A third possibility for their origin as satellites of Mars is the involvement of a third body or a type of impact disruption. More-recent lines of evidence for Phobos having a highly porous interior, and suggesting a composition containing mainly phyllosilicates↗ and other minerals known from Mars, point toward an origin of Phobos from material ejected by an impact on Mars that reaccreted in Martian orbit, similar to the prevailing theory↗ for the origin of Earth's satellite. Although the visible and near-infrared↗ (VNIR) spectra of the moons of Mars resemble those of outer-belt asteroids, the thermal infrared↗ spectra of Phobos are reported to be inconsistent with chondrite↗s of any class. It is also possible that Phobos and Deimos were fragments of an older moon, formed by debris from a large impact on Mars, and then destroyed by a more recent impact upon the satellite.

More recently, a study conducted by a team of researchers from multiple countries suggests that a lost moon, at least fifteen times the size of Phobos, may have existed in the past. By analyzing rocks which point to tidal processes on the planet, it is possible that these tides may have been regulated by a past moon.

Human observations and exploration

Main articles: Exploration of Mars↗ and History of Mars observation↗

The history of observations of Mars is marked by oppositions of Mars when the planet is closest to Earth and hence is most easily visible, which occur every couple of years. Even more notable are the perihelic opposition↗s of Mars, which are distinguished because Mars is close to perihelion, making it even closer to Earth.

Ancient observations

The ancient Sumer↗ians named Mars Nergal↗, the god of war and plague. During Sumerian times, Nergal was a minor deity of little significance, but, during later times, his main cult center was the city of Nineveh↗. In Mesopotamian texts, Mars is referred to as the "star of judgement of the fate of the dead". The existence of Mars as a wandering object in the night sky was also recorded by the ancient Egyptian astronomers↗ and, by 1534 BCE, they were familiar with the retrograde motion↗ of the planet. By the period of the Neo-Babylonian Empire↗, the Babylonian astronomers↗ were making regular records of the positions of the planets and systematic observations of their behavior. For Mars, they knew that the planet made 37 synodic periods↗, or 42 circuits of the zodiac, every 79 years. They invented arithmetic methods for making minor corrections to the predicted positions of the planets. In Ancient Greece↗, the planet was known as Πυρόεις↗. Commonly, the Greek name for the planet now referred to as Mars, was Ares. It was the Romans who named the planet Mars, for their god of war, often represented by the sword and shield of the planet's namesake.

In the fourth century BCE, Aristotle↗ noted that Mars disappeared behind the Moon during an occultation↗, indicating that the planet was farther away. Ptolemy↗, a Greek living in Alexandria↗, attempted to address the problem of the orbital motion of Mars. Ptolemy's model and his collective work on astronomy was presented in the multi-volume collection later called the Almagest↗ (from the Arabic for "greatest"), which became the authoritative treatise on Western astronomy↗ for the next fourteen centuries. Literature from ancient China confirms that Mars was known by Chinese astronomers↗ by no later than the fourth century BCE. In the East Asian↗ cultures, Mars is traditionally referred to as the "fire star" (火星) based on the Wuxing system↗.

Early modern observations

In 1609 Johannes Kepler↗ published a 10-year study of Martian orbit, using the diurnal parallax↗ of Mars, measured by Tycho Brahe↗, to make a preliminary calculation of the relative distance to the planet. From Brahe's observations of Mars, Kepler deduced that the planet orbited the Sun not in a circle, but in an ellipse↗. Moreover, Kepler showed that Mars sped up as it approached the Sun and slowed down as it moved farther away, in a manner that later physicists would explain as a consequence of the conservation of angular momentum↗. pp. 433–437

In 1610 the first use of a telescope for astronomical observation, including Mars, was performed by Italian astronomer Galileo Galilei↗. With the telescope the diurnal parallax of Mars was again measured in an effort to determine the Sun-Earth distance. This was first performed by Giovanni Domenico Cassini↗ in 1672. The early parallax measurements were hampered by the quality of the instruments. The only occultation↗ of Mars by Venus observed was that of 13 October 1590, seen by Michael Maestlin↗ at Heidelberg↗.

Martian "canals"

Main article: Martian canals↗

By the 19th century, the resolution of telescopes reached a level sufficient for surface features to be identified. On 5 September 1877, a perihelic opposition to Mars occurred. The Italian astronomer Giovanni Schiaparelli↗ used a 22 cm telescope in Milan↗ to help produce the first detailed map of Mars. These maps notably contained features he called canali, which, with the possible exception of the natural canyon Valles Marineris↗, were later shown to be an optical illusion↗. These canali were supposedly long, straight lines on the surface of Mars, to which he gave names of famous rivers on Earth. His term, which means "channels" or "grooves", was popularly mistranslated in English as "canals".

Influenced by the observations, the orientalist Percival Lowell↗ founded an observatory↗ which had 30- and 45-centimetre (12- and 18-in) telescopes. The observatory was used for the exploration of Mars during the last good opportunity in 1894, and the following less favorable oppositions. He published several books on Mars and life on the planet, which had a great influence on the public. The canali were independently observed by other astronomers, such as Henri Joseph Perrotin↗ and Louis Thollon↗ in Nice, using one of the largest telescopes of that time.

The seasonal changes (consisting of the diminishing of the polar caps and the dark areas formed during Martian summers) in combination with the canals led to speculation about life on Mars, and it was a long-held belief that Mars contained vast seas and vegetation. As bigger telescopes were used, fewer long, straight canali were observed. During observations in 1909 by Antoniadi↗ with an 84 cm telescope, irregular patterns were observed, but no canali were seen.

First exploration

The first spacecraft from Earth to visit Mars was Mars 1↗ of the Soviet Union↗, which flew by in 1963, but contact was lost en route. NASA↗'s Mariner 4↗ followed and became the first spacecraft to successfully transmit from Mars; launched on 28 November 1964, it made its closest approach to the planet on 15 July 1965. Mariner 4 detected the weak Martian radiation belt, measured at about 0.1% that of Earth, and captured the first images of another planet from deep space.

Once spacecraft↗ visited the planet during the 1960s and 1970s, many previous concepts of Mars were radically broken. After the results of the Viking life-detection experiments, the hypothesis of a dead planet was generally accepted. The data from Mariner 9 and Viking allowed better maps of Mars to be made.

Renewed exploration

Until 1997 and after Viking 1 shut down in 1982, Mars was only visited by three unsuccessful probes, two flying past without contact (Phobos 1↗, 1988; Mars Observer↗, 1993), and one (Phobos 2↗ 1989) malfunctioning in orbit before reaching its destination Phobos↗.

In 1997 Mars Pathfinder↗ became the first successful rover mission beyond the Moon and started together with Mars Global Surveyor↗ (operated until late 2006) an uninterrupted active robotic presence at Mars that has lasted until today. It produced complete, extremely detailed maps of the Martian topography, magnetic field and surface minerals.

Starting with these missions a range of new improved crewless spacecraft↗, including orbiter↗s, landers↗, and rovers↗, have been sent to Mars, with successful missions by the NASA (United States), Jaxa↗ (Japan↗), ESA↗, United Kingdom↗, ISRO↗ (India↗), Roscosmos↗ (Russia), the United Arab Emirates↗, and CNSA↗ (China↗) to study the planet's surface, climate, and geology, uncovering the different elements of the history and dynamic of the hydrosphere of Mars and possible traces of ancient life.

Current missions

As of 2023, Mars is host to ten functioning spacecraft↗.

Eight are in orbit: 2001 Mars Odyssey↗, Mars Express↗, Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter↗, MAVEN↗, ExoMars Trace Gas Orbiter↗, the Hope↗ orbiter, and the Tianwen-1↗ orbiter.

Another two are on the surface: the Mars Science Laboratory↗ Curiosity↗ rover and the Perseverance↗ rover.

Collected maps are available online at websites including Google Mars↗. NASA provides two online tools: Mars Trek, which provides visualizations of the planet using data from 50 years of exploration, and Experience Curiosity↗, which simulates traveling on Mars in 3-D with Curiosity.

Future

Planned missions to Mars include:

NASA's EscaPADE↗ spacecraft, launched on 13 November 2025.
The Rosalind Franklin rover↗ mission, designed to search for evidence of past life, which was intended to be launched in 2018 but has been repeatedly delayed, with a launch date pushed to 2028 at the earliest. The project was restarted in 2024 with additional funding.
A current concept for a joint NASA↗-ESA↗ mission to return samples from Mars↗ would launch in 2026.
China's Tianwen-3↗, a sample return mission, scheduled to launch in either 2028 or 2030.

As of February 2024, debris from these types of missions has reached over seven tons. Most of it consists of crashed and inactive spacecraft as well as discarded components.

In April 2024, NASA selected several companies to begin studies on providing commercial services to further enable robotic science on Mars. Key areas include establishing telecommunications, payload delivery and surface imaging.

In 2025, an ad hoc committee was convened by the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine↗ (NASEM) to prioritize science objectives to guide human exploration on Mars. Out of hundreds of possible projects, the four panels of the committee (Astrobiology, Geosciences, Atmospheric Science and Space Physics, and Biological and Physical Sciences and Human Factors) highlighted eleven as the top science objectives to pursue, with the top priority being searching for current or extinct indigenous life on Mars.

Habitability and habitation

During the late 19th century, it was widely accepted in the astronomical community that Mars had life-supporting qualities, including the presence of oxygen and water. However, in 1894 W. W. Campbell↗ at Lick Observatory↗ observed the planet and found that "if water vapor or oxygen occur in the atmosphere of Mars it is in quantities too small to have been detected by spectroscopes then available". That observation contradicted many of the measurements of the time and was not widely accepted. Campbell and V. M. Slipher↗ repeated the study in 1909 using better instruments, but with the same results. It was not until the findings were confirmed by W. S. Adams↗ in 1925 that the myth of the Earth-like habitability of Mars was finally broken. However, even in the 1960s, articles were published on Martian biology, putting aside explanations other than life for the seasonal changes on Mars.

The current understanding of planetary habitability↗ – the ability of a world to develop environmental conditions favorable to the emergence of life – favors planets that have liquid water on their surface. Most often this requires the orbit of a planet to lie within the habitable zone↗, which for the Sun is estimated to extend from within the orbit of Earth to about that of Mars. During perihelion, Mars dips inside this region, but Mars's thin (low-pressure) atmosphere prevents liquid water from existing over large regions for extended periods. The past flow of liquid water demonstrates the planet's potential for habitability. Recent evidence has suggested that any water on the Martian surface may have been too salty and acidic to support regular terrestrial life.

The environmental conditions on Mars are a challenge to sustaining organic life: the planet has little heat transfer↗ across its surface, it has poor insulation against bombardment↗ by the solar wind↗ due to the absence of a magnetosphere and has insufficient atmospheric pressure to retain water in a liquid form (water instead sublimes↗ to a gaseous state). Mars is nearly, or perhaps totally, geologically dead; the end of volcanic activity has apparently stopped the recycling of chemicals and minerals between the surface and interior of the planet.

Evidence suggests that the planet was once significantly more habitable than it is today, but whether living organism↗s ever existed there remains unknown. The Viking probes↗ of the mid-1970s carried experiments designed to detect microorganisms in Martian soil at their respective landing sites and had positive results, including a temporary increase in CO2 production on exposure to water and nutrients. This sign of life was later disputed by scientists, resulting in a continuing debate, with NASA scientist Gilbert Levin↗ asserting that Viking may have found life. A 2014 analysis of Martian meteorite EETA79001 found chlorate↗, perchlorate↗, and nitrate↗ ions in sufficiently high concentrations to suggest that they are widespread on Mars. UV and X-ray radiation would turn chlorate and perchlorate ions into other, highly reactive↗ oxychlorines↗, indicating that any organic molecules would have to be buried under the surface to survive.

Small quantities of methane↗ and formaldehyde↗ detected by Mars orbiters are both claimed to be possible evidence for life, as these chemical compound↗s would quickly break down in the Martian atmosphere. Alternatively, these compounds may instead be replenished by volcanic or other geological means, such as serpentinite↗. Impact glass↗, formed by the impact of meteors, which on Earth can preserve signs of life, has also been found on the surface of the impact craters on Mars. Likewise, the glass in impact craters on Mars could have preserved signs of life, if life existed at the site.

The Cheyava Falls↗ rock discovered on Mars in June 2024 has been designated by NASA as a "potential biosignature↗" and was core sampled by the Perseverance↗ rover for possible return to Earth and further examination. Although highly intriguing, no definitive final determination on a biological or abiotic origin of this rock can be made with the data currently available.

Human mission proposals

Several plans for a human mission to Mars↗ have been proposed, but none have come to fruition. The NASA Authorization Act of 2017 directed NASA to study the feasibility of a crewed Mars mission in the early 2030s; the resulting report concluded that this would be unfeasible. In addition, in 2021, China was planning to send a crewed Mars mission in 2033. Privately held companies↗ such as SpaceX↗ have also proposed plans to send humans to Mars↗, with the eventual goal to settle on the planet↗. As of 2024, SpaceX has proceeded with the development of the Starship↗ launch vehicle with the goal of Mars colonization. In plans shared with the company in April 2024, Elon Musk envisions the beginning of a Mars colony within the next twenty years. This would be enabled by the planned mass manufacturing↗ of Starship and initially sustained by resupply from Earth, and in situ resource utilization↗ on Mars, until the Mars colony reaches full self sustainability. Any future human mission to Mars will likely take place within the optimal Mars launch window↗, which occurs every 26 months. The moon Phobos has been proposed as an anchor point for a space elevator↗. Besides national space agencies and space companies, groups such as the Mars Society↗ and The Planetary Society↗ advocate for human missions to Mars.

In culture

Main articles: Mars in culture↗ and Mars in fiction↗

See also: Planets in astrology#Mars↗

Mars is named after the Roman↗ god of war↗ (Greek↗ Ares↗), but was also associated with the demi-god Heracles↗ (Roman Hercules↗) by ancient Greek astronomers, as detailed by Aristotle↗. This association between Mars and war dates back at least to Babylonian astronomy↗, in which the planet was named for the god Nergal↗, deity of war and destruction. It persisted into modern times, as exemplified by Gustav Holst↗'s orchestral suite The Planets↗, whose famous first movement labels Mars "The Bringer of War". The planet's symbol↗, a circle with a spear pointing out to the upper right, is also used as a symbol for the male gender. The symbol dates from at least the 11th century, though a possible predecessor has been found in the Greek Oxyrhynchus Papyri↗.

The idea that Mars was populated by intelligent Martian↗s became widespread in the late 19th century. Schiaparelli's↗ "canali" observations combined with Percival Lowell↗'s books on the subject put forward the standard notion of a planet that was a drying, cooling, dying world with ancient civilizations constructing irrigation works. Many other observations and proclamations by notable personalities added to what has been termed "Mars Fever". In the present day, high-resolution mapping of the surface of Mars has revealed no artifacts of habitation, but pseudoscientific speculation about intelligent life on Mars still continues. Reminiscent of the canali observations, these speculations are based on small scale features perceived in the spacecraft images, such as "pyramids" and the "Face on Mars↗". In his book Cosmos↗, planetary astronomer Carl Sagan↗ wrote: "Mars has become a kind of mythic arena onto which we have projected our Earthly hopes and fears."

The depiction of Mars in fiction has been stimulated by its dramatic red color and by nineteenth-century scientific speculations that its surface conditions might support not just life but intelligent life. This gave way to many science fiction↗ stories involving these concepts, such as H. G. Wells↗'s The War of the Worlds↗, in which Martians seek to escape their dying planet by invading Earth; Ray Bradbury↗'s The Martian Chronicles↗, in which human explorers accidentally destroy a Martian civilization; as well as Edgar Rice Burroughs↗'s series Barsoom↗, C. S. Lewis↗'s novel Out of the Silent Planet↗ (1938), and a number of Robert A. Heinlein↗ stories before the mid-sixties. Since then, depictions of Martians have also extended to animation. A comic figure of an intelligent Martian, Marvin the Martian↗, appeared in Haredevil Hare↗ (1948) as a character in the Looney Tunes↗ animated cartoons of Warner Brothers↗, and has continued as part of popular culture to the present. After the Mariner↗ and Viking↗ spacecraft had returned pictures of Mars as a lifeless and canal-less world, these ideas about Mars were abandoned; for many science-fiction authors, the new discoveries initially seemed like a constraint, but eventually the post-Viking knowledge of Mars became itself a source of inspiration for works like Kim Stanley Robinson↗'s Mars trilogy↗.

See also

Astronomy on Mars↗
Outline of Mars↗
List of missions to Mars↗
Magnetic field of Mars↗
Mineralogy of Mars↗

Notes

References

Further reading

Kelly Weinersmith↗ and Zach Weinersmith↗. A city on Mars: can we settle space, should we settle space, and have we really thought this through?. New York: Penguin Press↗, 2023. ISBN 978-1-9848-8172-4
Matthew Shindell. For the love of Mars: a human history of the red planet. Chicago; London: The University of Chicago Press↗, 2023. ISBN 978-0-226-82189-4

External links

Mars Trek, an integrated map browser of maps and datasets for Mars
Google Mars and Google Mars 3D, interactive maps of the planet
First TV image of Mars (15 July 1965), CNN News↗; 15 July 2023

Solar System

The Solar System is the gravitational↗ly bound system of the Sun and the masses that orbit↗ it, most prominently its eight planet↗s, of which Earth is one. The system formed about 4.6 billion years ago↗ when a dense region of a molecular cloud↗ collapsed, creating the Sun and a protoplanetary disc↗ from which the orbiting bodies assembled.

The Sun accounts for 99.86% of the Solar System's total mass. Inside the Sun's core↗, hydrogen is fused↗ into helium↗, releasing energy that is emitted through the Sun's photosphere↗. This creates the heliosphere↗ and a decreasing temperature gradient↗ across the Solar System.

The next most massive objects of the system↗ are the eight planets, which by definition dominate the orbits they occupy. Closest to the Sun in order of increasing distance are the terrestrial planet↗s – Mercury↗, Venus, Earth and Mars. These four planets are part of the inner Solar System↗. Earth and Mars are the only planets that orbit within the Sun's habitable zone↗, in which sunlight can keep surface water liquid under atmospheric pressure. Beyond the frost line↗ at about five astronomical unit↗s (AU), are the planets of the outer Solar System↗: two gas giant↗s (Jupiter↗ and Saturn↗) and two ice giant↗s (Uranus↗ and Neptune↗). Jupiter and Saturn possess nearly 90% of the non-stellar mass of the Solar System.

Objects of planetary mass↗ that do not dominate their orbit but directly orbit the Sun are called dwarf planet↗s. The International Astronomical Union↗'s Minor Planet Center lists Ceres↗, Pluto↗, Eris↗, Makemake↗, and Haumea↗ as dwarf planets. Four other Solar System object↗s are generally identified as such: Orcus↗, Quaoar↗, Gonggong↗, and Sedna↗. Less massive than the dwarf planets are the vast number of small Solar System bodies↗, such as asteroid↗s, comet↗s, centaurs↗, meteoroid↗s, and interplanetary dust cloud↗s. The dwarf planet Ceres and many of these smaller bodies are located in the asteroid belt↗ (between Mars's and Jupiter's orbit), while all other dwarf planets are members of populations of trans-Neptunian objects↗, which may be found in the Kuiper belt↗ just outside Neptune or in the further scattered disc↗.

Many objects in the Solar System do not orbit the Sun directly and are instead natural satellite↗s, commonly called 'moons', of larger bodies. These can be found throughout the Solar System in sizes from planetary-mass moons at their largest to much less massive moonlet↗s at their smallest. The largest two moons (Ganymede↗ of Jupiter and Titan↗ of Saturn) are larger (though less massive) than the smallest planet (Mercury), while the seven most massive, which includes Earth's Moon↗, are more massive and larger than any of the dwarf planets.

Within the heliosphere, the Solar System is constantly flooded by the charged plasma↗ particles of the solar wind↗, which, along with interplanetary dust, gas and cosmic rays↗, form an interplanetary medium↗ between the bodies of the Solar System. At around 70 – 90 AU from the Sun, the solar wind is halted by the interstellar medium↗, resulting in the heliopause↗ and the border of the interplanetary medium to interstellar space↗. Further out somewhere beyond 2000 AU from the Sun extends the outermost region of the Solar System, the theorized Oort cloud↗, the source for long-period comet↗s, stretching to the edge of the Solar System, the edge of its Hill sphere↗, at 178,000 -, where its gravitational potential becomes equal to the galactic potential. The Solar System currently moves through a cloud of interstellar medium called the Local Cloud↗. The closest star↗ to the Solar System, Proxima Centauri↗, is 4.25 ly away. Both are within the Local Bubble↗, a relatively small 1,000 light-years (ly) wide region of the Milky Way↗.

Definition

The Solar System includes the Sun and all objects that are bound to it by gravity and orbit it.

The International Astronomical Union↗ describes the Solar System as all objects that are bound by the gravity of the Sun, the Sun itself, its eight planets, and the other celestial bodies which orbit it. NASA↗ describes the Solar System as a planetary system↗, including the Sun and all objects that orbit it.

Capitalization↗ of the name varies. When not used as a proper noun and written without capitalization, "solar system" may refer to either the Solar System itself or any planetary system↗ reminiscent of the Solar System. The International Astronomical Union↗, the authoritative body regarding astronomical nomenclature↗, specifies capitalizing the names of all individual astronomical objects but uses mixed "Solar System" and "solar system" structures in their naming guidelines document.

Formation and evolution

Main article: Formation and evolution of the Solar System↗

Past

The Solar System formed at least 4.568 billion years ago from the gravitational collapse of a region within a large molecular cloud↗. This initial cloud was likely several light-years across and probably birthed several stars. As is typical of molecular clouds, this one consisted mostly of hydrogen, with some helium, and small amounts of heavier elements fused↗ by previous generations of stars.

As the pre-solar nebula↗ collapsed, conservation of angular momentum↗ caused it to rotate faster. The center, where most of the mass collected, became increasingly hotter than the surroundings. As the contracting nebula spun faster, it began to flatten into a protoplanetary disc↗ with a diameter of roughly 200 AU and a hot, dense protostar↗ at the center. The planets formed by accretion↗ from this disc, in which dust and gas gravitationally attracted each other, coalescing to form ever larger bodies. Hundreds of protoplanets may have existed in the early Solar System, but they either merged or were destroyed or ejected, leaving the planets, dwarf planets, and leftover minor bodies↗.

In the inner Solar System, heat from the accretion process exceeded the boiling point of hydrocarbon molecules for the first million years, leading to low carbon content for the inner planets. The boundary for this process has been dubbed the soot line. As the Solar System disk cooled, this line moved inward and now lies within Earth's orbit around the Sun. Material other than metals and silicates, due to their higher boiling points, could not persist in solid form. Here planets formed that are mainly rocky, which are Mercury, Venus, Earth, and Mars. Because these refractory↗ materials only comprised a small fraction of the solar nebula, the terrestrial planets could not grow very large.

The giant planets (Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, and Neptune) formed further out, beyond the frost line, the point between the orbits of Mars and Jupiter where material is cool enough for volatile↗ icy compounds to remain solid. The ices that formed these planets were more plentiful than the metals and silicates that formed the terrestrial inner planets, allowing them to grow massive enough to capture large atmospheres of hydrogen and helium↗, the lightest and most abundant elements. Leftover debris that never became planets congregated in regions such as the asteroid belt, Kuiper belt, and Oort cloud.

Within 50 million years, the pressure and density of hydrogen in the center of the protostar became great enough for it to begin thermonuclear fusion↗. As helium accumulates at its core, the Sun is growing brighter; early in its main-sequence life its brightness was 70% that of what it is today. The temperature, reaction rate↗, pressure, and density increased until hydrostatic equilibrium↗ was achieved: the thermal pressure counterbalancing the force of gravity. At this point, the Sun became a main-sequence↗ star. Solar wind from the Sun created the heliosphere↗ and swept away the remaining gas and dust from the protoplanetary disc into interstellar space.

Following the dissipation of the protoplanetary disk↗, the Nice model↗ proposes that gravitational encounters↗ between planetesimals and the gas giants caused each to migrate↗ into different orbits. This led to dynamical instability of the entire system, which scattered the planetesimals and ultimately placed the gas giants in their current positions. During this period, the grand tack hypothesis↗ suggests that a final inward migration of Jupiter dispersed much of the asteroid belt, leading to the Late Heavy Bombardment↗ of the inner planets.

Present and future

The Solar System remains in a relatively stable, slowly evolving state by following isolated, gravitationally bound↗ orbits around the Sun. Although the Solar System has been fairly stable for billions of years, it is technically chaotic↗, and may eventually be disrupted↗. There is a small chance that another star will pass through the Solar System in the next few billion years. Although this could destabilize the system and eventually lead millions of years later to expulsion of planets, collisions of planets, or planets hitting the Sun, it would most likely leave the Solar System much as it is today.

The Sun's main-sequence phase, from beginning to end, will last about 10 billion years for the Sun compared to around two billion years for all other subsequent phases of the Sun's pre-remnant↗ life combined. The Solar System will remain roughly as it is known today until the hydrogen in the core of the Sun has been entirely converted to helium, which will occur roughly 5 billion years from now. This will mark the end of the Sun's main-sequence life. At that time, the core of the Sun will contract with hydrogen↗ fusion occurring along a shell surrounding the inert helium, and the energy output will be greater than at present. The outer layers of the Sun will expand to roughly 260 times its current diameter, and the Sun will become a red giant↗. Because of its increased surface area, the surface of the Sun will be cooler (2,600 K at its coolest) than it is on the main sequence.

The expanding Sun is expected to vaporize Mercury as well as Venus, and render Earth and Mars uninhabitable (possibly destroying Earth as well). Eventually, the core will be hot enough for helium fusion; the Sun will burn helium for a fraction of the time it burned hydrogen in the core. The Sun is not massive enough to commence the fusion of heavier elements, and nuclear reactions in the core will dwindle. Its outer layers will be ejected into space, leaving behind a dense white dwarf↗, half the original mass of the Sun but only the size of Earth. The ejected outer layers may form a planetary nebula↗, returning some of the material that formed the Sun – but now enriched with heavier elements↗ like carbon – to the interstellar medium↗.

General characteristics

Astronomers sometimes divide the Solar System structure into separate regions. The inner Solar System↗ includes Mercury, Venus, Earth, Mars, and the bodies in the asteroid belt↗. The outer Solar System↗ includes Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, Neptune, and the bodies in the Kuiper belt↗. Since the discovery of the Kuiper belt, the outermost parts of the Solar System are considered a distinct region consisting of the objects beyond Neptune↗.

Composition

Further information: List of Solar System objects↗ and List of interstellar and circumstellar molecules↗

The principal component of the Solar System is the Sun, a G-type main-sequence star↗ that contains 99.86% of the system's known mass and dominates it gravitationally. The Sun's four largest orbiting bodies, the giant planets, account for 99% of the remaining mass, with Jupiter and Saturn together comprising more than 90%. The remaining objects of the Solar System (including the four terrestrial planets, the dwarf planets, moons, asteroid↗s, and comets) together comprise less than 0.002% of the Solar System's total mass.

The Sun is composed of roughly 98% hydrogen and helium, as are Jupiter and Saturn. A composition gradient exists in the Solar System, created by heat and light pressure↗ from the early Sun; those objects closer to the Sun, which are more affected by heat and light pressure, are composed of elements with high melting points. Objects farther from the Sun are composed largely of materials with lower melting points. The boundary in the Solar System beyond which those volatile substances could coalesce is known as the frost line↗, and it lies at roughly five times the Earth's distance from the Sun.

Orbits

The planets and other large objects in orbit around the Sun lie near the invariable plane of the Solar System↗, as does Earth's orbit, known as the ecliptic↗, and most closely the orbit of Jupiter, with an inclination to it of 0.3219°. Smaller icy objects such as comets frequently orbit at significantly greater angles to this plane. Most of the planets in the Solar System have secondary systems of their own, being orbited by natural satellites called moons. All of the largest natural satellites are in synchronous rotation↗, with one face permanently turned toward their parent. The four giant planets have planetary rings, thin discs of tiny particles that orbit them in unison.

As a result of the formation of the Solar System↗, planets and most other objects orbit the Sun in the same direction that the Sun is rotating. That is, counter-clockwise, as viewed from above Earth's north pole. There are exceptions, such as Halley's Comet↗. Most of the larger moons orbit their planets in prograde↗ direction, matching the direction of planetary rotation; Neptune's moon Triton↗ is the largest to orbit in the opposite, retrograde manner. Most larger objects rotate around their own axes in the prograde direction relative to their orbit, though the rotation of Venus is retrograde.

To a good first approximation, Kepler's laws of planetary motion↗ describe the orbits of objects around the Sun. pp. 433–437 These laws stipulate that each object travels along an ellipse↗ with the Sun at one focus↗, which causes the body's distance from the Sun to vary over the course of its year. A body's closest approach to the Sun is called its perihelion↗, whereas its most distant point from the Sun is called its aphelion↗. With the exception of Mercury, the orbits of the planets are nearly circular, but many comets, asteroids, and Kuiper belt objects follow highly elliptical orbits. Kepler's laws only account for the influence of the Sun's gravity upon an orbiting body, not the gravitational pulls of different bodies upon each other. On a human time scale, these perturbations can be accounted for using numerical models↗, but the planetary system can change chaotically over billions of years.

The angular momentum↗ of the Solar System is a measure of the total amount of orbital and rotational momentum↗ possessed by all its moving components. Although the Sun dominates the system by mass, it accounts for only about 2% of the angular momentum. The planets, dominated by Jupiter, account for most of the rest of the angular momentum due to the combination of their mass, orbit, and distance from the Sun, with a possibly significant contribution from comets.

+ Orbital periods and velocities of the planets | Planet | Orbital period (days) | Orbital period (Earth years) | Orbital velocity
Mercury | 87.969 | 0.241 | 47.9 km/s (29.8 mi/s)
Venus | 224.701 | 0.615 | 35.0 km/s (21.7 mi/s)
Earth | 365.256 | 1.000 | 29.8 km/s (18.5 mi/s)
Mars | 686.980 | 1.881 | 24.1 km/s (15.0 mi/s)
Jupiter | 4,332.589 | 11.862 | 13.1 km/s (8.1 mi/s)
Saturn | 10,759.22 | 29.457 | 9.7 km/s (6.0 mi/s)
Uranus | 30,688.5 | 84.020 | 6.8 km/s (4.2 mi/s)
Neptune | 60,182 | 164.8 | 5.4 km/s (3.4 mi/s)

Distances and scales

The radius of the Sun is 0.0047 AU. Thus, the Sun occupies 0.00001% (1 part in 107) of the volume of a sphere with a radius the size of Earth's orbit, whereas Earth's volume is roughly 1 millionth (10−6) that of the Sun. Jupiter, the largest planet, is 5.2 AU from the Sun and has a radius of 71000 km, whereas the most distant planet, Neptune, is 30 AU from the Sun.

With a few exceptions, the farther a planet or belt is from the Sun, the larger the distance between its orbit and the orbit of the next nearest object to the Sun. For example, Venus is approximately 0.33 AU farther out from the Sun than Mercury, whereas Saturn is 4.3 AU out from Jupiter, and Neptune lies 10.5 AU out from Uranus. Attempts have been made to determine a relationship between these orbital distances, like the Titius–Bode law↗ and Johannes Kepler's model↗ based on the Platonic solid↗s, but ongoing discoveries have invalidated these hypotheses.

Some Solar System model↗s attempt to convey the relative scales involved in the Solar System in human terms. Some are small in scale (and may be mechanical – called orreries↗) – whereas others extend across cities or regional areas. The largest such scale model, the Sweden Solar System↗, uses the 110-meter (361-foot) Avicii Arena↗ in Stockholm as its substitute Sun, and, following the scale, Jupiter is a 7.5-meter (25-foot) sphere at Stockholm Arlanda Airport↗, 40 km away, whereas the farthest current object, Sedna↗, is a 10 cm sphere in Luleå↗, 912 km away. At that scale, the distance to Proxima Centauri would be roughly 8 times further than the Moon is from Earth.

If the Sun–Neptune distance is scaled to 100 m, then the Sun would be about 3 cm in diameter (roughly two-thirds the diameter of a golf ball), the giant planets would be all smaller than about 3 mm, and Earth's diameter↗ along with that of the other terrestrial planets would be smaller than a flea↗ (0.3 mm) at this scale.

Habitability

Main article: Planetary habitability in the Solar System↗

The zone of habitability↗ of the Solar System is conventionally located in the inner Solar System around Earth, where atmospheric liquid water↗ is enabled by the Sun.

Besides solar energy, the primary characteristic of the Solar System enabling the presence of life is the heliosphere and planetary magnetic fields (for those planets that have them). These magnetic fields partially shield the Solar System from high-energy interstellar particles called cosmic ray↗s. The density of cosmic rays in the interstellar medium↗ and the strength of the Sun's magnetic field change on very long timescales, so the level of cosmic-ray penetration in the Solar System varies, though by how much is unknown.

Habitability in the Solar System is though not solely dependent on surface conditions, and furthermore the Solar environment, since there might be habitablity in potential subsurface ocean↗s of various Solar System bodies, or cloud layers of some planets, particularly Venus.

Comparison with extrasolar systems

Analysis of Kepler↗ data suggests that observed planetary systems in the Milky Way fall into three groups: "similar", which comprise planets of similar sizes similar distances apart and with highly circular orbits; "ordered", in which the masses of planets tend to increase with distance from their star, and "mixed", which show no pattern in masses whatsoever. The Solar System is an ordered system, as are 37% of observed systems. Similar systems however are the majority, comprising 59% of observed systems, while mixed systems comprise just 4%.

Compared to many extrasolar systems, the Solar System stands out in lacking planets interior to the orbit of Mercury. The known Solar System lacks super-Earth↗s, planets between one and ten times as massive as the Earth, although the hypothetical Planet Nine↗, if it does exist, could be a super-Earth orbiting in the edge of the Solar System.

Uncommonly, it has only small terrestrial and large gas giants; elsewhere planets of intermediate size are typical – both rocky and gas – so there is no "gap" as seen between the size of Earth and of Neptune (with a radius 3.8 times as large). As many of these super-Earths are closer to their respective stars than Mercury is to the Sun, a hypothesis has arisen that all planetary systems start with many close-in planets, and that typically a sequence of their collisions causes consolidation of mass into few larger planets, but in case of the Solar System the collisions↗ caused their destruction and ejection.

The orbits of Solar System planets are nearly circular. Compared to many other systems, they have smaller orbital eccentricity↗. Although there are attempts to explain it partly with a bias in the radial-velocity detection method↗ and partly with long interactions of a quite high number of planets, the exact causes remain undetermined.

Sun

Main article: Sun

The Sun is the Solar System's star and by far its most massive component. Its large mass (332,900 Earth mass↗es), which comprises 99.86% of all the mass in the Solar System, produces temperatures and densities in its core↗ high enough to sustain nuclear fusion of hydrogen into helium. This releases an enormous amount of energy↗, mostly radiated↗ into space↗ as electromagnetic radiation↗ peaking in visible light↗.

Because the Sun fuses hydrogen at its core, it is a main-sequence star. More specifically, it is a G2-type main-sequence star↗, where the type designation refers to its effective temperature↗. Hotter main-sequence stars are more luminous but shorter lived. The Sun's temperature is intermediate between that of the hottest stars↗ and that of the coolest stars. Stars brighter and hotter than the Sun are rare, whereas substantially dimmer and cooler stars, known as red dwarf↗s, make up about 75% of the fusor↗ stars in the Milky Way↗.

The Sun is a population I star↗, having formed in the galaxy's spiral arm↗s. It has a higher abundance of elements heavier than hydrogen and helium ("metals↗" in astronomical parlance) than the older population II stars in the galactic bulge↗ and halo↗. Elements heavier than hydrogen and helium were formed in the cores of ancient and exploding stars, so the first generation of stars had to die before the universe↗ could be enriched with these atoms. The oldest stars contain few metals, whereas stars born later have more. This higher metallicity is thought to have been crucial to the Sun's development of a planetary system↗ because the planets formed from the accretion of "metals".

The region of space dominated by the Solar magnetosphere↗ is the heliosphere↗, which spans much of the Solar System. Along with light↗, the Sun radiates a continuous stream of charged particles (a plasma↗) called the solar wind↗. This stream spreads outwards at speeds from 900000 km/h to 2880000 km/h, filling the vacuum between the bodies of the Solar System. The result is a thin↗, dusty atmosphere, called the interplanetary medium↗, which extends to at least 100 AU.

Activity on the Sun's surface, such as solar flare↗s and coronal mass ejection↗s, disturbs the heliosphere, creating space weather↗ and causing geomagnetic storm↗s. Coronal mass ejections and similar events blow a magnetic field and huge quantities of material from the surface of the Sun. The interaction of this magnetic field and material with Earth's magnetic field funnels charged particles into Earth's upper atmosphere, where its interactions create aurorae↗ seen near the magnetic poles↗. The largest stable structure within the heliosphere is the heliospheric current sheet↗, a spiral form created by the actions of the Sun's rotating magnetic field on the interplanetary medium.

Inner Solar System

The inner Solar System is the region comprising the terrestrial planets↗ and the asteroid↗s. Composed mainly of silicate↗s and metals, the objects of the inner Solar System are relatively close to the Sun; the radius of this entire region is less than the distance between the orbits of Jupiter and Saturn. This region is within the frost line↗, which is a little less than 5 AU from the Sun.

Inner planets

Main article: Terrestrial planet↗

The four terrestrial or inner planets have dense, rocky compositions, few or no moons↗, and no ring systems↗. They are composed largely of refractory↗ minerals such as silicates↗—which form their crusts↗ and mantles↗—and metals such as iron and nickel which form their cores↗. Three of the four inner planets (Venus, Earth, and Mars) have atmosphere↗s substantial enough to generate weather; all have impact craters and tectonic↗ surface features, such as rift valley↗s and volcanoes.

Mercury↗ (0.31–0.59 AU from the Sun) is the smallest planet in the Solar System. Its surface is grayish, with an expansive rupes↗ (cliff) system generated from thrust fault↗s and bright ray system↗s formed by impact event remnants↗. The surface has widely varying temperature, with the equator↗ial regions ranging from -170 °C at night to 420 °C during sunlight. In the past, Mercury was volcanically active, producing smooth basalt↗ic plains similar to the Moon. It is likely that Mercury has a silicate crust and a large iron core. Mercury has a very tenuous atmosphere, consisting of solar-wind↗ particles and ejected atoms. Mercury has no natural satellites.
Venus (0.72–0.73 AU) has a reflective, whitish atmosphere that is mainly composed of carbon dioxide↗. At the surface, the atmospheric pressure is ninety times as dense as on Earth's sea level. Venus has a surface temperatures over 400 °C, mainly due to the amount of greenhouse gas↗es in the atmosphere. The planet lacks a protective magnetic field to protect against stripping↗ by the solar wind, which suggests that its atmosphere is sustained by volcanic activity. Its surface displays extensive evidence of volcanic activity with stagnant lid tectonics↗. Venus has no natural satellites.
Earth (0.98–1.02 AU) is the only place in the universe where life↗ and surface liquid water↗ are known to exist. Earth's atmosphere contains 78% nitrogen↗ and 21% oxygen↗, which is the result of the presence of life. The planet has a complex climate↗ and weather↗ system, with conditions differing drastically between climate region↗s. The solid surface of Earth is dominated by green vegetation↗, deserts↗ and white ice sheet↗s. Earth's surface is shaped by plate tectonics↗ that formed the continental masses. Earth's planetary magnetosphere↗ shields the surface from radiation, limiting atmospheric stripping↗ and maintaining life habitability.
The Moon↗ is Earth's only natural satellite. Its diameter is one-quarter the size of Earth's. Its surface is covered in very fine regolith↗ and dominated by impact crater↗s. Large dark patches on the Moon, maria↗, are formed from past volcanic activity. The Moon's atmosphere is extremely thin, consisting of a partial vacuum↗ with particle densities of under 107 per cm−3.
Mars (1.38–1.67 AU) has a radius about half of that of Earth. Most of the planet is red due to iron oxide↗ in Martian soil, and the polar regions are covered in white ice caps↗ made of water and carbon dioxide↗. Mars has an atmosphere composed mostly of carbon dioxide, with surface pressure 0.6% of that of Earth, which is sufficient to support some weather phenomena. During the Mars year (687 Earth days), there are large surface temperature swings on the surface between -78.5 to 5.7 °C. The surface is peppered with volcanoes and rift valley↗s, and has a rich collection of mineral↗s. Mars has a highly differentiated↗ internal structure, and lost its magnetosphere 4 billion years ago. Mars has two tiny moons↗:
Phobos↗ is Mars's inner moon. It is a small, irregularly shaped object with a mean radius of 11 km. Its surface is very unreflective and dominated by impact craters. In particular, Phobos's surface has a very large Stickney impact crater↗ that is roughly 4.5 km in radius.
Deimos↗ is Mars's outer moon. Like Phobos, it is irregularly shaped, with a mean radius of 6 km and its surface reflects little light. However, the surface of Deimos is noticeably smoother than Phobos because the regolith partially covers the impact craters.

Asteroids

Main article: Asteroid↗

Asteroids, except for the largest, Ceres↗, are classified as small Solar System bodies↗ and are composed mainly of carbon↗aceous, refractory rocky and metallic minerals, with some ice. They range from a few meters to hundreds of kilometers in size. Many asteroids are divided into asteroid group↗s and families↗ based on their orbital characteristics. Some asteroids have natural satellites that orbit them↗, that is, asteroids that orbit larger asteroids.

Mercury-crossing asteroids↗ are those with perihelia↗ within the orbit of Mercury. At least 362 are known to date, and include the closest objects to the Sun known in the Solar System. No vulcanoid↗s, asteroids between the orbit of Mercury and the Sun, have been discovered. As of 2024, one asteroid has been discovered to orbit completely within Venus's orbit, 594913 ꞌAylóꞌchaxnim↗.
Venus-crossing asteroid↗s are those that cross the orbit of Venus. There are 2,809 as of 2015.
Near-Earth asteroids↗ have orbits that approach relatively close to Earth's orbit, and some of them are potentially hazardous object↗s because they might collide with Earth in the future. There are over 37,000 known as of 2024. A number of solar-orbiting meteoroid↗s were large enough to be tracked in space before striking Earth. It is now widely accepted that collisions in the past have had a significant role in shaping the geological and biological history of Earth.
Mars-crossing asteroids↗ are those with perhihelia above 1.3 AU which cross the orbit of Mars. As of 2024, NASA lists 26,182 confirmed Mars-crossing asteroids.

Asteroid belt

Main article: Asteroid belt↗ The asteroid belt occupies a torus-shaped region between 2.3 and 3.3 AU from the Sun, which lies between the orbits of Mars and Jupiter. It is thought to be remnants from the Solar System's formation that failed to coalesce because of the gravitational interference of Jupiter. The asteroid belt contains tens of thousands, possibly millions, of objects over one kilometer in diameter. Despite this, the total mass of the asteroid belt is unlikely to be more than a thousandth of that of Earth. The asteroid belt is very sparsely populated; spacecraft routinely pass through without incident.

Below are the descriptions of the three largest bodies in the asteroid belt. They are all considered to be relatively intact protoplanet↗s, a precursor stage before becoming a fully-formed planet (see List of exceptional asteroids↗):

Ceres↗ (2.55–2.98 AU) is the only dwarf planet in the asteroid belt. It is the largest object in the belt, with a diameter of 940 km. Its surface contains a mixture of carbon↗, frozen water and hydrate↗d minerals. There are signs of past cryovolcanic↗ activity, where volatile↗ material such as water are erupted onto the surface, as seen in surface bright spots↗. Ceres has a very thin water vapor atmosphere, but practically speaking it is indistinguishable from a vacuum.
Vesta↗ (2.15–2.57 AU) is the second-largest object in the asteroid belt. Its fragments survive as the Vesta asteroid family↗ and numerous HED meteorite↗s found on Earth. Vesta's surface, dominated by basalt↗ic and metamorphic↗ material, has a denser composition than Ceres's. Its surface is marked by two giant craters: Rheasilvia↗ and Veneneia↗.
Pallas↗ (2.13–3.41 AU) is the third-largest object in the asteroid belt. It has its own Pallas↗ asteroid family↗. Not much is known about Pallas because it has never been visited by a spacecraft, though its surface is predicted to be composed of silicates.

Hilda asteroid↗s are in a 3:2 resonance with Jupiter; that is, they go around the Sun three times for every two Jovian orbits. They lie in three linked clusters between Jupiter and the main asteroid belt.

Trojan↗s are bodies located within another body's gravitationally stable Lagrange points↗: L4, 60° ahead in its orbit, or L5, 60° behind in its orbit. Every planet except Mercury is known to possess at least one trojan. The Jupiter trojan↗ population is roughly equal to that of the asteroid belt. After Jupiter, Neptune possesses the most confirmed trojans, at 28.

Outer Solar System

The outer region of the Solar System is home to the giant planet↗s and their large moons. The centaurs↗ and many short-period comet↗s orbit in this region. Due to their greater distance from the Sun, the solid objects in the outer Solar System contain a higher proportion of volatiles such as water, ammonia, and methane, than planets of the inner Solar System because their lower temperatures allow these compounds to remain solid, without significant sublimation↗.

Outer planets

Main article: Giant planet↗

The four outer planets, called giant planets or Jovian planets, collectively make up 99% of the mass orbiting the Sun. All four giant planets have multiple moons and a ring system, although only Saturn's rings are easily observed from Earth. Jupiter and Saturn are composed mainly of gases with extremely low melting points, such as hydrogen, helium, and neon↗, hence their designation as gas giant↗s. Uranus and Neptune are ice giants↗, meaning they are largely composed of 'ice' in the astronomical sense↗ (chemical compounds with melting points of up to a few hundred kelvin↗s such as water, methane, ammonia, hydrogen sulfide↗, and carbon dioxide↗.) Icy substances comprise the majority of the satellites of the giant planets and small objects that lie beyond Neptune's orbit.

Jupiter↗ (4.95–5.46 AU) is the biggest and most massive planet in the Solar System. On its surface, there are orange-brown and white cloud bands moving via the principles of atmospheric circulation↗, with giant storms swirling on the surface such as the Great Red Spot↗ and white 'ovals'↗. Jupiter possesses a strong enough magnetosphere↗ to redirect ionizing radiation↗ and cause aurora↗s on its poles. As of 2026, Jupiter has 115 confirmed satellites↗, which can roughly be sorted into three groups:
The Amalthea group, consisting of Metis↗, Adrastea↗, Amalthea↗, and Thebe↗. They orbit substantially closer to Jupiter than other satellites. Materials from these natural satellites are the source of Jupiter's faint ring.
The Galilean moons↗, consisting of Ganymede↗, Callisto↗, Io↗, and Europa↗. They are the largest moons of Jupiter and exhibit planetary properties.
Irregular satellites, consisting of substantially smaller natural satellites. They have more distant orbits than the other objects.
Saturn↗ (9.08–10.12 AU) has a distinctive visible ring system↗ orbiting around its equator composed of small ice and rock particles. Like Jupiter, it is mostly made of hydrogen and helium. At its north and south poles, Saturn has peculiar hexagon-shaped storms↗ larger than the diameter of Earth. Saturn has a magnetosphere↗ capable of producing weak auroras. As of 2026, Saturn has 292 confirmed satellites↗, grouped into:
Ring moonlet↗s and shepherds↗, which orbit inside or close to Saturn's rings. A moonlet can only partially clear out dust in its orbit, while the ring shepherds are able to completely clear out dust, forming visible gaps in the rings.
Inner large satellites Mimas↗, Enceladus↗, Tethys↗, and Dione↗. These satellites orbit within Saturn's E ring↗. They are composed mostly of water ice and are believed to have differentiated internal structures.
Trojan moons Calypso↗ and Telesto↗ (trojans of Tethys), and Helene↗ and Polydeuces↗ (trojans of Dione). These small moons share their orbits with Tethys and Dione, leading or trailing either.
Outer large satellites Rhea↗, Titan↗, Hyperion↗, and Iapetus↗. Titan is the only satellite in the Solar System to have a substantial atmosphere.
Irregular satellites, consisting of substantially smaller natural satellites. They have more distant orbits than the other objects. Phoebe↗ is the largest irregular satellite of Saturn.
Uranus↗ (18.3–20.1 AU), uniquely among the planets, orbits the Sun on its side with an axial tilt↗ >90°. This gives the planet extreme seasonal variation as each pole points alternately toward and then away from the Sun. Uranus's outer layer has a muted cyan↗ color, but underneath these clouds are many mysteries about its climate↗, such as unusually low internal heat↗ and erratic cloud formation. As of 2026, Uranus has 29 confirmed satellites↗, divided into three groups:
Inner satellites, which orbit inside Uranus's ring system. They are very close to each other, which suggests that their orbits are chaotic↗.
Large satellites, consisting of Titania↗, Oberon↗, Umbriel↗, Ariel↗, and Miranda↗. Most of them have roughly equal amounts of rock and ice, except Miranda, which is made primarily of ice.
Irregular satellites, having more distant and eccentric orbits than the other objects.
Neptune↗ (29.9–30.5 AU) is the furthest planet known in the Solar System. Its outer atmosphere has a slightly muted cyan color, with occasional storms on the surface that look like dark spots. Like Uranus, many atmospheric phenomena of Neptune are unexplained, such as the thermosphere↗'s abnormally high temperature or the strong tilt (47°) of its magnetosphere. As of 2026, Neptune has 16 confirmed satellites↗, divided into two groups:
Regular satellites, which have circular orbits that lie near Neptune's equator.
Irregular satellites, which as the name implies, have less regular orbits. One of them, Triton↗, is Neptune's largest moon. It is geologically active, with erupting geyser↗s of nitrogen gas, and possesses a thin, cloudy nitrogen atmosphere.

Centaurs

Main article: Centaur (small Solar System body)↗

The centaurs are icy, comet-like bodies whose semi-major axes↗ are longer than Jupiter's and shorter than Neptune's (between 5.5 and 30 AU). These are former Kuiper belt and scattered disc objects↗ (SDOs) that were gravitationally perturbed↗ closer to the Sun by the outer planets, and are expected to become comets or be ejected out of the Solar System. While most centaurs are inactive and asteroid-like, some exhibit cometary activity, such as the first centaur discovered, 2060 Chiron↗, which has been classified as a comet (95P) because it develops a coma just as comets do when they approach the Sun. The largest known centaur, 10199 Chariklo↗, has a diameter of about 250 km and is one of the few minor planets possessing a ring system.

Trans-Neptunian region

Beyond the orbit of Neptune lies the area of the "trans-Neptunian region↗", with the doughnut-shaped Kuiper belt, home of Pluto and several other dwarf planets, and an overlapping disc of scattered objects, which is tilted toward the plane↗ of the Solar System and reaches much further out than the Kuiper belt. The entire region is still largely unexplored↗. It appears to consist overwhelmingly of many thousands of small worlds – the largest having a diameter only a fifth that of Earth and a mass far smaller than that of the Moon – composed mainly of rock and ice. This region is sometimes described as the "third zone of the Solar System", enclosing the inner and the outer Solar System.

Kuiper belt

Main article: Kuiper belt↗

The Kuiper belt is a great ring of debris similar to the asteroid belt, but consisting mainly of objects composed primarily of ice. It extends between 30 and 50 AU from the Sun. It is composed mainly of small Solar System bodies, although the largest few are probably large enough to be dwarf planets. There are estimated to be over 100,000 Kuiper belt objects with a diameter greater than 50 km, but the total mass of the Kuiper belt is thought to be only a tenth or even a hundredth the mass of Earth. Many Kuiper belt objects have satellites, and most have orbits that are substantially inclined (~10°) to the plane of the ecliptic.

The Kuiper belt can be roughly divided into the "classical↗" belt and the resonant trans-Neptunian object↗s. The latter have orbits whose periods are in a simple ratio to that of Neptune: for example, going around the Sun twice for every three times that Neptune does, or once for every two. The classical belt consists of objects having no resonance with Neptune, and extends from roughly 39.4 to 47.7 AU. Members of the classical Kuiper belt are sometimes called "cubewanos", after the first of their kind to be discovered, originally designated 1992 QB1↗, (and has since been named Albion); they are still in near primordial, low-eccentricity orbits.

There is strong consensus among astronomers that five members of the Kuiper belt are dwarf planets. Many dwarf planet candidates are being considered, pending further data for verification.

Pluto↗ (29.7–49.3 AU) is the largest known object in the Kuiper belt. Pluto has a relatively eccentric orbit, inclined 17 degrees to the ecliptic plane↗. Pluto has a 2:3 resonance↗ with Neptune, meaning that Pluto orbits twice around the Sun for every three Neptunian orbits. Kuiper belt objects whose orbits share this resonance are called plutino↗s. Pluto has five moons↗: Charon, Styx↗, Nix↗, Kerberos↗, and Hydra↗.
Charon↗, the largest of Pluto's moons, is sometimes described as part of a binary system↗ with Pluto, as the two bodies orbit a barycenter↗ of gravity above their surfaces (i.e. they appear to "orbit each other").
Orcus↗ (30.3–48.1 AU), is in the same 2:3 orbital resonance with Neptune as Pluto, and is the largest such object after Pluto itself. Its eccentricity and inclination are similar to Pluto's, but its perihelion lies about 120° from that of Pluto. Thus, the phase↗ of Orcus's orbit is opposite to Pluto's: Orcus is at aphelion (most recently in 2019) around when Pluto is at perihelion (most recently in 1989) and vice versa. For this reason, it has been called the anti-Pluto. It has one known moon, Vanth↗.
Haumea↗ (34.6–51.6 AU) was discovered in 2005. It is in a temporary 7:12 orbital resonance with Neptune. Haumea possesses a ring system, two known moons named Hiʻiaka↗ and Namaka↗, and rotates so quickly (once every 3.9 hours) that it is stretched into an ellipsoid↗. It is part of a collisional family↗ of Kuiper belt objects that share similar orbits, which suggests a giant impact on Haumea ejected fragments into space billions of years ago.
Makemake↗ (38.1–52.8 AU), although smaller than Pluto, is the largest known object in the classical Kuiper belt (that is, a Kuiper belt object not in a confirmed resonance with Neptune). Makemake is the brightest object in the Kuiper belt after Pluto. Discovered in 2005, it was officially named in 2008. Its orbit is far more inclined than Pluto's, at 29°. It has one known moon, S/2015 (136472) 1↗.
Quaoar↗ (41.9–45.5 AU) is the second-largest known object in the classical Kuiper belt, after Makemake. Its orbit is significantly less eccentric and inclined than those of Makemake or Haumea. It possesses a ring system and one known moon, Weywot↗.

Scattered disc

Main article: Scattered disc↗

The scattered disc, which overlaps the Kuiper belt but extends out to near 500 AU, is thought to be the source of short-period comets. Scattered-disc objects are believed to have been perturbed into erratic orbits by the gravitational influence of Neptune's early outward migration↗. Most scattered disc objects have perihelia within the Kuiper belt but aphelia far beyond it (some more than 150 AU from the Sun). SDOs' orbits can be inclined up to 46.8° from the ecliptic plane. Some astronomers consider the scattered disc to be merely another region of the Kuiper belt and describe scattered-disc objects as "scattered Kuiper belt objects". Some astronomers classify centaurs as inward-scattered Kuiper belt objects along with the outward-scattered residents of the scattered disc.

Currently, there is strong consensus among astronomers that two of the bodies in the scattered disc are dwarf planets:

Eris↗ (38.3–97.5 AU) is the largest known scattered disc object and the most massive known dwarf planet. Eris's discovery contributed to a debate about the definition of a planet because it is 25% more massive than Pluto and about the same diameter. It has one known moon, Dysnomia↗. Like Pluto, its orbit is highly eccentric, with a perihelion of 38.2 AU (roughly Pluto's distance from the Sun) and an aphelion of 97.6 AU, and steeply inclined to the ecliptic plane at an angle of 44°.
Gonggong↗ (33.8–101.2 AU) is a dwarf planet in a comparable orbit to Eris, except that it is in a 3:10 resonance with Neptune. It has one known moon, Xiangliu↗.

Extreme trans-Neptunian objects

Main article: Extreme trans-Neptunian object↗

Some objects in the Solar System have a very large orbit, and therefore are much less affected by the known giant planets than other minor planet populations. These bodies are called extreme trans-Neptunian objects, or ETNOs for short. Generally, ETNOs' semi-major axes↗ are at least 150–250 AU wide. For example, 541132 Leleākūhonua↗ orbits the Sun once every ~32,000 years, with a distance of 65–2000 AU from the Sun.

This population is divided into three subgroups by astronomers. The scattered↗ ETNOs have perihelia↗ around 38–45 AU and an exceptionally high eccentricity↗ of more than 0.85. As with the regular scattered disc objects, they were likely formed as result of gravitational scattering↗ by Neptune and still interact with the giant planets. The detached↗ ETNOs, with perihelia approximately between 40–45 and 50–60 AU, are less affected by Neptune than the scattered ETNOs, but are still relatively close to Neptune. The sednoid↗s or inner Oort cloud↗ objects, with perihelia beyond 50–60 AU, are too far from Neptune to be strongly influenced by it.

Currently, there is one ETNO that is classified as a dwarf planet:

Sedna↗ (76.2–937 AU) was the first extreme trans-Neptunian object to be discovered. It is a large, reddish object, and takes ~11,400 years to complete one orbit. Mike Brown↗, who discovered the object in 2003, asserts that it cannot be part of the scattered disc or the Kuiper belt because its perihelion is too distant to have been affected by Neptune's migration. The sednoid population↗ is named after Sedna.

Statistical variance has been observed in the orbits of some extreme trans-Neptunian objects, whose closest approaches to the Sun are mostly clustered around one sector and who display a similar orbital tilt to each other. Some astronomers have suggested that this may be the result of the influence of a large planet beyond Neptune; this hypothetical planet has been termed Planet Nine↗. Others credit this statistical variance to observational biases or sheer coincidence↗.

Oort cloud

The Oort cloud↗ is a theorized spherical shell of up to a trillion icy objects that is thought to be the source for all long-period comets, which were originally ejected from the planetary region by gravitational interactions with the gas giants. Oort cloud objects move very slowly, and can be perturbed by infrequent events, such as collisions, the gravitational effects of a passing star, or the galactic tide↗, the tidal force↗ exerted by the Milky Way. No direct observation of the Oort cloud is possible with present imaging technology.

The Oort cloud is theorized to surround the Solar System from potentially ~2,000 AU from the Sun to up to ~200,000 AU. Lower estimates for the radius of the Oort cloud, by contrast, do not place it farther than 50,000 AU. Most of the mass is orbiting in the region between 3,000 and 100,000 AU. The furthest known objects, such as Comet West↗, have aphelia around 70,000 AU from the Sun.

Gravitationally unstable populations

Meteoroids, meteors and dust

Main articles: Meteoroid↗, Interplanetary dust cloud↗, and Cosmic dust↗

Solid objects smaller than one meter are usually called meteoroids and micrometeoroids (grain-sized), with the exact division between the two categories being debated over the years. By 2017, the IAU designated any solid object having a diameter between ~30 micrometers↗ and 1 meter as meteoroids, and depreciated the micrometeoroid categorization, instead terms smaller particles simply as 'dust particles'.

Some meteoroids formed via disintegration of comets and asteroids, while a few formed via impact debris ejected from planetary bodies. Most meteoroids are made of silicates and heavier metals like nickel↗ and iron↗. When passing through the Solar System, comets produce a trail of meteoroids; it is hypothesized that this is caused either by vaporization of the comet's material or by simple breakup of dormant comets. When crossing an atmosphere, these meteoroids will produce bright streaks in the sky due to atmospheric entry↗, called meteor↗s. If a stream of meteoroids enter the atmosphere on parallel trajectories, the meteors will seemingly 'radiate' from a point in the sky, hence the phenomenon's name: meteor shower↗.

The inner Solar System is home to the zodiacal dust cloud↗, which is visible as the hazy zodiacal light↗ in dark, unpolluted skies. It may be generated by collisions within the asteroid belt brought on by gravitational interactions with the planets; a more recent proposed origin is materials from planet Mars. The outer Solar System hosts a cosmic dust cloud. It extends from about 10 AU to about 40 AU, and was probably created by collisions within the Kuiper belt.

Comets

Main article: Comet↗

Comets are small Solar System bodies↗, typically only a few kilometers across, composed largely of volatile ices. They have highly eccentric orbits, generally a perihelion within the orbits of the inner planets and an aphelion far beyond Pluto. When a comet enters the inner Solar System, its proximity to the Sun causes its icy surface to sublimate↗ and ion↗ise, creating a coma↗: a long tail of gas and dust often visible to the naked eye.

Short-period comets have orbits lasting less than two hundred years. Long-period comets have orbits lasting thousands of years. Short-period comets are thought to originate in the Kuiper belt, whereas long-period comets, such as Hale–Bopp↗, are thought to originate in the Oort cloud. Many comet groups, such as the Kreutz sungrazer↗s, formed from the breakup of a single parent. Some comets with hyperbolic↗ orbits may originate outside the Solar System, but determining their precise orbits is difficult. Old comets whose volatiles have mostly been driven out by solar warming are often categorized as asteroids.

Boundary region and uncertainties

See also: List of Solar System objects by greatest aphelion↗

Much of the outer reaches of the Solar System is still unknown. The region beyond 100 AU away is virtually unexplored and learning about this region of space is difficult. Study of this region depends upon inferences from those few objects whose orbits happen to be perturbed such that they fall closer to the Sun, and even then, detecting these objects has often been possible only when they happened to become bright enough to register as comets. Many objects are yet to be discovered in the Solar System's outer region.

The Sun's Hill sphere↗, its gravitational potential↗ reaching the galactic potential, the potential of the galactic nucleus, the effective range of its gravitational influence, is thought to encompass the Oort cloud, and extend to up to 230,000 AU from the Sun.

The boundaries of the heliosphere↗ and of the Hill sphere↗, the Sun's gravitational potential in respect to the interstellar medium↗ and the galactic gravitational potential, at the edge of the Oort cloud↗, represent the boundaries of the Solar System with the galactic environment it is in.

Edge of the heliosphere

The Sun's stellar-wind bubble↗, the heliosphere↗, a region of space dominated by the Sun, has its boundary at the termination shock. Based on the Sun's peculiar motion↗ relative to the local standard of rest↗, this boundary is roughly 80–100 AU from the Sun upwind of the interstellar medium and roughly 200 AU from the Sun downwind. Here the solar wind collides with the interstellar medium and dramatically slows, condenses and becomes more turbulent, forming a great oval structure known as the heliosheath↗.

The heliosheath has been theorized to look and behave very much like a comet's tail, extending outward for a further 40 AU on the upwind side but tailing many times that distance downwind to possibly several thousands of AU. Evidence from the Cassini↗ and Interstellar Boundary Explorer↗ spacecraft has suggested that it is forced into a bubble shape by the constraining action of the interstellar magnetic field, but the actual shape remains unknown.

The shape and form of the outer edge of the heliosphere is likely affected by the fluid dynamics↗ of interactions with the interstellar medium as well as solar magnetic field↗s prevailing to the south, e.g. it is bluntly shaped with the northern hemisphere extending 9 AU farther than the southern hemisphere. The heliopause is considered the beginning of the interstellar medium. Beyond the heliopause, at around 230 AU, lies the bow shock↗: a plasma "wake" left by the Sun as it travels through the Milky Way. Large objects outside the heliopause remain gravitationally bound to the Sun, but the flow of matter in the interstellar medium homogenizes the distribution of micro-scale objects.

Celestial neighborhood

Main articles: List of nearest stars↗, List of nearest exoplanets↗, and List of nearby stellar associations and moving groups↗

Within 10 light-years of the Sun there are relatively few stars, the closest being the triple star system Alpha Centauri↗, which is about 4.4 light-years away and may be in the Local Bubble's G-Cloud↗. Alpha Centauri A and B are a closely tied pair of Sun-like stars↗, whereas the closest star to the Sun, the small red dwarf↗ Proxima Centauri↗, orbits the pair at a distance of 0.2 light-years. In 2016, a potentially habitable exoplanet↗ was found to be orbiting Proxima Centauri, called Proxima Centauri b↗, the closest confirmed exoplanet to the Sun.

The Solar System is surrounded by the Local Interstellar Cloud↗, although it is not clear if it is embedded in the Local Interstellar Cloud or if it lies just outside the cloud's edge. Multiple other interstellar cloud↗s exist in the region within 300 light-years of the Sun, known as the Local Bubble↗. The latter feature is an hourglass-shaped cavity or superbubble↗ in the interstellar medium roughly 300 light-years across. The bubble is suffused with high-temperature plasma, suggesting that it may be the product of several recent supernovae.

The Local Bubble is a small superbubble compared to the neighboring wider Radcliffe Wave↗ and Split linear structures (formerly Gould Belt↗), each of which are some thousands of light-years in length. All these structures are part of the Orion Arm↗, which contains most of the stars in the Milky Way that are visible to the unaided eye.

Groups of stars form together in star cluster↗s, before dissolving into co-moving associations. A prominent grouping that is visible to the naked eye is the Ursa Major moving group↗, which is around 80 light-years away within the Local Bubble. The nearest star cluster is Hyades↗, which lies at the edge of the Local Bubble. The closest star-forming regions are the Corona Australis Molecular Cloud↗, the Rho Ophiuchi cloud complex↗ and the Taurus molecular cloud↗; the latter lies just beyond the Local Bubble and is part of the Radcliffe wave.

Stellar flybys that pass within 0.25 pc of the Sun occur roughly once every 100,000 years. The closest well-measured approach↗ was Scholz's Star↗, which approached to ~50,000 AU of the Sun some ~70 thousand years ago, likely passing through the outer Oort cloud. There is a 1% chance every billion years that a star will pass within 100 AU of the Sun, potentially disrupting the Solar System.

Galactic position

See also: Location of Earth↗, Galactic year↗, and Orbit of the Sun↗

The Solar System is located in the Milky Way↗, a barred spiral galaxy↗ with a diameter of about 100,000 light-year↗s containing more than 100 billion stars. The Sun is part of one of the Milky Way's outer spiral arms, known as the Orion–Cygnus Arm↗ or Local Spur. It is a member of the thin disk↗ population of stars orbiting close to the galactic plane.

Its speed around the center of the Milky Way is about 220 km/s, so that it completes one revolution every 240 million years. This revolution is known as the Solar System's galactic year↗. The solar apex↗, the direction of the Sun's path through interstellar space, is near the constellation Hercules↗ in the direction of the current location of the bright star Vega↗. The plane of the ecliptic lies at an angle of about 60° to the galactic plane↗.

The Sun follows a nearly circular orbit around the Galactic Center↗ (where the supermassive black hole↗ Sagittarius A*↗ resides) at a distance of 26,660 light-years, orbiting at roughly the same speed as that of the spiral arms. If it orbited close to the center, gravitational tugs from nearby stars could perturb bodies in the Oort cloud↗ and send many comets into the inner Solar System, producing collisions with potentially catastrophic implications for life on Earth. In this scenario, the intense radiation of the Galactic Center could interfere with the development of complex life.

The Solar System's location in the Milky Way is a factor in the evolutionary history of life↗ on Earth. Spiral arms are home to a far larger concentration of supernova↗e, gravitational instabilities, and radiation that could disrupt the Solar System, but since Earth stays in the Local Spur and therefore does not pass frequently through spiral arms, this has given Earth long periods of stability for life to evolve. However, according to the controversial Shiva hypothesis↗, the changing position of the Solar System relative to other parts of the Milky Way could explain periodic extinction events↗ on Earth.

Discovery and exploration

Main article: Discovery and exploration of the Solar System↗

Humanity's knowledge of the Solar System has grown incrementally over the centuries. Up to the Late Middle Ages↗–Renaissance↗, astronomers from Europe to India believed Earth to be stationary at the center↗ of the universe and categorically different from the divine or ethereal objects that moved through the sky. Although the Greek↗ philosopher Aristarchus of Samos↗ had speculated on a heliocentric↗ reordering of the cosmos, Nicolaus Copernicus↗ was the first person known to have developed a mathematically predictive heliocentric system↗.

Heliocentrism did not triumph immediately over geocentrism, but the work of Copernicus had its champions, notably Johannes Kepler↗. Using a heliocentric model that improved upon Copernicus by allowing orbits to be elliptical, and the precise observational data of Tycho Brahe↗, Kepler produced the Rudolphine Tables↗, which enabled accurate computations of the positions of the then-known planets. Pierre Gassendi↗ used them to predict a transit of Mercury↗ in 1631, and Jeremiah Horrocks↗ did the same for a transit of Venus↗ in 1639. This provided a strong vindication of heliocentrism and Kepler's elliptical orbits.

In the 17th century, Galileo↗ publicized the use of the telescope in astronomy; he and Simon Marius↗ independently discovered that Jupiter had four satellites in orbit around it. Christiaan Huygens↗ followed on from these observations by discovering Saturn's moon Titan↗ and the shape of the rings of Saturn↗. In 1677, Edmond Halley↗ observed a transit of Mercury across the Sun, leading him to realize that observations of the solar parallax↗ of a planet (more ideally using the transit of Venus) could be used to trigonometrically↗ determine the distances between Earth, Venus, and the Sun. Halley's friend Isaac Newton↗, in his magisterial Principia Mathematica↗ of 1687, demonstrated that celestial bodies are not quintessentially different from Earthly ones: the same laws of motion↗ and of gravity↗ apply on Earth and in the skies. p. 142

The term "Solar System" entered the English language by 1704, when John Locke↗ used it to refer to the Sun, planets, and comets. In 1705, Halley realized that repeated sightings of a comet↗ were of the same object, returning regularly once every 75–76 years. This was the first evidence that anything other than the planets repeatedly orbited the Sun, though Seneca↗ had theorized this about comets in the 1st century. Careful observations of the 1769 transit of Venus allowed astronomers to calculate the average Earth–Sun distance as 93726900 mi, only 0.8% greater than the modern value.

Uranus↗, having occasionally been observed since 1690 and possibly from antiquity, was recognized to be a planet orbiting beyond Saturn by 1783. In 1838, Friedrich Bessel↗ successfully measured a stellar parallax↗, an apparent shift in the position of a star created by Earth's motion around the Sun, providing the first direct, experimental proof of heliocentrism. Neptune↗ was identified as a planet some years later, in 1846, thanks to its gravitational pull causing a slight but detectable variation in the orbit of Uranus. Mercury's orbital anomaly↗ observations led to searches for Vulcan↗, a planet interior of Mercury, but these attempts were quashed with Albert Einstein↗'s theory of general relativity↗ in 1915.

In the 20th century, humans began their space exploration around the Solar System, starting with placing telescopes in space↗ since the 1960s. By 1989, all eight planets have been visited by space probes. Probes have returned samples from comets and asteroids, as well as flown through the Sun's corona↗ and visited two dwarf planets (Pluto↗ and Ceres↗). To save on fuel, some space missions make use of gravity assist maneuvers↗, such as the two Voyager probes↗ accelerating when flying by planets in the outer Solar System and the Parker Solar Probe↗ decelerating closer towards the Sun after its flyby of Venus.

Humans have landed on the Moon during the Apollo program↗ in the 1960s and 1970s and are planning to return to the Moon in the 2020s with the Artemis program↗. Discoveries in the 20th and 21st century has prompted the redefinition of the term planet↗ in 2006, hence the demotion of Pluto to a dwarf planet, and further interest in trans-Neptunian object↗s.

See also

Interplanetary spaceflight↗
List of gravitationally rounded objects of the Solar System↗
List of Solar System extremes↗
List of Solar System objects by size↗
Lists of geological features of the Solar System↗
Outline of the Solar System↗
Planetary mnemonic↗
Solar System in fiction↗

Notes

References

Data sources

Other sources

External links

"Solar System" in Encyclopædia Britannica↗ (11th ed., 1911)
If the Moon were only 1 Pixel: A Tediously Accurate Map of the Solar System (web based scroll map scaled to the Moon being 1 pixel)
NASA's Eyes on the Solar System
NASA's Solar System Exploration
NASA's Solar System Simulator